<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth and innocency vindicated and the people called Quakers defended in principle and practice, against invidious attempts and calumnies, being a just examination of two books against the said people, entituled, I. examined by G. Whitehead ...</title>
            <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12292219</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12292219</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58919</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65893)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58919)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 930:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth and innocency vindicated and the people called Quakers defended in principle and practice, against invidious attempts and calumnies, being a just examination of two books against the said people, entituled, I. examined by G. Whitehead ...</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Beckham, Edward, 1637 or 8-1714. --  Brief discovery of some of the blasphemous and seditious principles.</term>
               <term>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724? --  Pilgrim's progress from Quakerism to Christianity.</term>
               <term>Meriton, John, 1666-1717. --  Antidote against the venom of Quakerism.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58919:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58919:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> VINDICATED: And the PEOPLE called <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS</hi> DEFENDED, IN <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> Againſt Invidious Attempts and Calumnies.</p>
            <p>BEING A Juſt EXAMINATION of Two Books againſt the ſaid People: ENTITULED,
<list>
                  <item>I. A <hi>Brief Diſcovery,</hi> &amp;c. By Three <hi>Norfolk-Prieſts.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Some few of the Quakers many horrid Blaſphemies,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list> Being a Scandalous Libel.</p>
            <p>Containing alſo many of the Repeated Abuſes in <hi>John Meriton</hi>'s <hi>Antidote,</hi> and <hi>Francis Bugg</hi>'s <hi>Pilgrim's Progreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Examined by <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> a Servant of Chriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm 37.12.</hi>
                  </bibl> The Wicked plotteth againſt the Juſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Plalm 35.20.</hi>
                  </bibl> They deviſe deceitful matters againſt them that are quiet in the Land.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Gracious-ſtreet,</hi> and at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Leaden-Hall-ſtreet,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58919:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58919:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Ingenuous Reader.</head>
            <p>WE knowing the Foundation of God, which ſtandeth ſure, the Tried Stone, Elect and Precious, and that the goodneſs of the Lord endures for ever, to all who truly love and fear him, and that he will proſper his own Work in the Earth, that the Kingdom of Chriſt may be Promoted and Renowned, to the Subduing and Overthrow of the Kingdom of Satan and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, which God will accompliſh fully by his own Power in his own Day and Time: We are not diſmayed nor diſcouraged at <hi>Satan's Rage,</hi> nor at the Fury, or Envious Attempts of any of his <hi>Agent</hi>'s ſtrenuous Endeavours or Deſigns for renewed <hi>Perſecution</hi> againſt the Innocent. But through the Lord's Power and Goodneſs his Faithful People and Children are the more ſtrengthned and confirmed in their moſt holy <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Confidence</hi> in Chriſt Jeſus and his Divine Power; that as thereby the Kingdom of Satan and Anti-Chriſt is already greatly ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſo therefore <hi>Satan's Rage</hi> is the more increaſed and heightned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſhortneſs of his Time.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Lord our God is ſecretly at work by his Inviſible Power in many hearts, ſeriouſly inclining them towards himſelf, his bleſſed Truth and People, that they may flock to his Houſe and Family, as <hi>Doves</hi> to the <hi>Window;</hi> Therefore Avaricious, Self-intereſted Perſons, (whoſe Gain is their Godlineſs, and Lucre their Religion, and their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry Mercenary) are the more uneaſie and offended at our Religious Freedom and Liberty; which through God's Goodneſs, Over-ruling Power and Providence, influencing the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> we do enjoy, as we have of late years done: For which we are humbly thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Almighty God, and Gratefully acknowledge the ſame to the <hi>King,</hi> and all our <hi>Superiors,</hi> who are made Inſtrumental therein.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58919:3"/>
            <p>And to be branded and perſecuted with Calumnies, Reproaches, and virulent Invectives, as <hi>Blaſphemous, Hereticks, movers</hi> of <hi>Sedition, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable,</hi> and what not, of the like import; is no new thing or ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zal to us, to have theſe black Characters put upon us; they being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the <hi>
                  <hi>All</hi> manner of Evil</hi> ſpoken of againſt the true Followers of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> according as he himſelf hath expreſly foretold his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> pronouncing thereupon a Bleſſing unto them for their Incouragement againſt their <hi>Revilers</hi> and <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Malicious Men's Plotting againſt the Righteous, and the Wicked's deviſing Miſchief againſt the Innocent and the Quiet in the Land; we doubt not, but as their <hi>Miſchievous Deſigns</hi> have taken Air, and come to Light, and thereby become weakned; ſo the juſt and holy God will fruſtrate and make them void in the end to their perpetual <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> who are therein concern'd.</p>
            <p>'Tis a great ſign, that our preſent buſie Adverſaries are at a <hi>Low Ebb,</hi> and they are very feeble, and independent upon God, and their Cauſe without Divine Support, ſeeing that they are fain to make uſe of ſuch perfidious <hi>Agents,</hi> as invidious <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> and Angry Reſtleſs <hi>Backſliders,</hi> as <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> &amp;c. whoſe mercenary and perverſe work of implacable <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Reproach, Forgeries</hi> and <hi>Contempt</hi> againſt us, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame and ſcandalize us, (both as to our Chriſtian <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> Religious and Civil <hi>Reputations,</hi>) will no ways redound to their <hi>Honour</hi> or good <hi>Fame,</hi> who <hi>gratifie</hi> and encourage him in <hi>ſuch</hi> his injurious work againſt the innocent and quiet in the Land, but it will turn to their great ſhame and diſgrace who abet him, and reward him with higher ſums of Mony, than ever <hi>Judas</hi> had of the Chief Prieſts for betraying Chriſt into the hands of his <hi>Perſecutors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the World may know, what <hi>Famous, Learned Men</hi> theſe are, who are join'd with <hi>F. Bugg</hi> in the preſent <hi>Quarrel,</hi> and high defaming Charge againſt us, they have afforded us their <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Titles</hi> in the <hi>Title-page</hi> of their <hi>Brief Diſcovery,</hi> ſet down in this Order, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Edward Beckham,</hi> D. D. and Rector of <hi>Gayten-Thorp. NORFOLK.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry Meriton,</hi> Rector of <hi>Oxborow. NORFOLK.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lancaſter Topcliff,</hi> L. B. ſometimes Sen. Fell. of <hi>Gon.</hi> and <hi>Cajus</hi> Coll. <hi>Cambr. NORFOLK.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And now, <hi>Reader,</hi> that thou mayſt underſtand what Eminent <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> and Victorious Champions theſe Perſons would make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their <hi>Reply</hi> to our Friends in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> dated <hi>Nov.</hi> 16. 1698. They inſultingly tell them thus, viz. <hi>Nay, did not you reject</hi> F. Bugg
<pb facs="tcp:58919:3"/>
               <hi>for this Reaſon, becauſe he had been anſwered as you pretend over and over again, and was unreaſonable, as if we had nothing to do, but</hi> Actum Agere? <hi>And may we not ſay the ſame of your Hackney-Diſputants, they have drudged ſo long in that Road,</hi> and <hi>have been ſpurr'd and gaul'd by us enough already; and therefore in reaſon we ought to turn them off a while, and give them Reſt, till another occaſion,</hi> as in their Relation unduly ſtil'd <hi>The Quakers Challenge,</hi> p. 21. See here the <hi>Boaſting, Scorn</hi> and <hi>Inſulting</hi> of theſe Men, and what Language they give us, whilſt they are very <hi>Teachy,</hi> if but a little <hi>Toucht</hi> with <hi>Plain Dealing.</hi> But pray, how agrees this their Inſulting Deriſion againſt our Diſputants, with their Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> words, viz. <hi>We Ingenuouſly told them, that we never had ſo right an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of their Principles, as of late,</hi> p. 6. How have they then ſpurr'd and gaul'd our <hi>Hackney-Diſputants,</hi> (as they call them) <hi>enough already?</hi> How could they ſpur and gaul us by diſpute, when they did not rightly underſtand our Principles, if they had not a right underſtanding thereof till of late? We have for many years refuſed to be Prieſt-ridden, eſpecially to be made <hi>Hackneys</hi> of by them in the Dark, where they do not ſee their way. But their pretended <hi>Conference</hi> with the <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Norfolk</hi> is turn'd into Petitioning and Soliciting the Parliament (of late againſt us) for more Knocking Arguments than their Diſputes will afford. How came they of late to underſtand our Principles? How long hath <hi>F. Bugg</hi> and <hi>G. Keith</hi> been their Tutors, furniſh'd them with Quotations, or their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity been of value with them? Who tho' they have ſtrenuouſly labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bring us under Contempt and Reproach, 'twill be to their own Shame and Trouble, being expreſly contrary to their former extant Teſtimonies in behalf of our Chriſtian Principle, and of us as the People of God and True Chriſtians under his Spiritual Diſpenſation of the New Covenant.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems theſe Learned Doctors have been greatly beholding to their Tutor <hi>F. Bugg</hi> of late for Inſtruction to a right underſtanding of our Principles (as they think) what Dignity is he then promoted unto of late! How is he advanced to be a <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Doctors!</hi> But the Truth of it is, we have Cauſe to have the leſs eſteem of their Learning, whilſt inſtructed by ſuch a Tutor, who has ſpent much time in <hi>ſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> one Scurrilous Romancing Book and Pamphlet after another againſt us, heaping and repeating Forgeries and Defamations, ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Miſchief, and ſo Fool-hardy, as to Counterfeit a Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature of <hi>Oyer and Terminer</hi> therein to forge a Trial to ridicule, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame, ſcandalize and arraign for <hi>Perjury,</hi> divers Citizens of <hi>London</hi> (of our Friends) by Name, men of good Repute, forging Anſwers,
<pb facs="tcp:58919:4"/>acting both Accuſer, Judge and Executioner alſo, condemning them to the <hi>Pillory,</hi> as <hi>Perjur'd</hi> Perſons, with a Figure or Form of a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lory; and twelve Pictures in it, with the firſt Letters of their Names, and the Title of PERJURY over their Heads: And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all this Defamation and Scandal, to repreſent the Perſons ſo highly Defamed by him, as this groſs and abominable Defamation and Forgery may be ſeen at large, in <hi>F. Bugg's New Rome Arraign'd,</hi> Printed 1693. As alſo his Figure of a Cage, with many Names ſet croſs-wiſe in it, to repreſent a <hi>Cage of every unclean and hateful Bird,</hi> p. 50.</p>
            <p>This buſie Agent has alſo preſum'd to Print an-Impeachment againſt us, in <hi>Behalf of the Commons of</hi> England, without being Legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Authorized thereby, or ſhewing any Legal Authority for the ſame. And moreover, in his late great Book, his ſuppoſed Maſter-Piece, Printed 1698. Stiled the <hi>Pilgrims Progreſs,</hi> he takes upon him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive, frame and forge a Ridiculous Romance, calling it a <hi>Sermon for</hi> G. Whitehead <hi>to hold forth at their Convocation, or Yearly Meeting,</hi> which alſo he expreſly calls, <hi>George Whitehead</hi>'s <hi>Sermon;</hi> and in it he has a Figure, containing many Pictures, ſome with Names of our Friends over them, and others with <hi>Deputies</hi> over their Heads. And this Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure he makes to repreſent the <hi>Quakers Synod,</hi> and in it has Inſerted divers notorious Lies; as, <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> asking, <hi>Are the Doors ſhut?</hi> And <hi>W. Bingley</hi> Anſwers <hi>Yea, the Doors are lock'd,</hi> with divers more abominable Lies. And this ſame Sermon, which he calls <hi>George White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi>'s <hi>Sermon,</hi> from page 108, to page 127. contains two Sheets of Paper; to which pretended Sermon, he alſo adds a Lying Romance, and Invented Speech, in <hi>W. Bingley</hi>'s Name, in Teſtimony thereto; which Romance I do in good Conſcience Teſtifie againſt, as a horrid Piece of Forgery, containing in it many groſs Lies, Abſurdities, and perverted Quotations alſo; repreſenting me as calling the <hi>Scriptures Beaſtly Ware, &amp;c.</hi> and as Exhorting to <hi>throw down the Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>to make no Confeſſion of Sins,</hi> &amp;c. with many more groſs Lies and Abſurdities: And alſo his repreſenting <hi>W. Bingley,</hi> as Preaching, <hi>That our deſign is the ſupplanting Chriſtianity,</hi> &amp;c. with divers more Falſhoods and Abſurdities, in <hi>W. Bingley</hi>'s Name, and many more in my Name, in his ſaid Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Romance, wherein he preſumptuouſly uſes and repeats the Sacred <hi>Name of God, Chriſt, the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. What horrid Preſumption, abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Prophaneneſs and Immorality is this Agent arriv'd to, who dare thus audaciouſly take the Name of the Holy God in vain, thus Prophanely to make uſe of the Sacred Name of God, and of his Dear Son, Chriſt the Lord, in ſuch his idle Forgery, and ſcurrilous Stuff!
<pb facs="tcp:58919:4"/>Oh horrid Prophanation! Oh abominable Preſumption! Is this your Convert, O ye Clergy-men, who abet, countenance, and gratifie ſuch an Impious, Preſumptuous Perſon, who dare make ſo bold with the Sacred Name of God and Chriſt, as thus (Atheiſt-like) to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane the ſame! The Righteous Lord and Judge of all, beholds ſuch great Impiety and Wickedneſs, and a Day of Reckoning and Account will come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ingenuous Reader,</hi> theſe are but ſhort Hints of the groſs Abuſes we have ſuffered from this prophane, wicked, apoſtate Spirit; we pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently commit our Innocent Cauſe to Him that judgeth Righteouſly, and thee to his Divine Grace and Light for a clear Underſtanding of, and Conduct in the Way of Truth and Peace, to thy Everlaſting Felicity, which is the Sincere Deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend in Chriſt, <hi>G. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>A <hi>Table</hi> of the <hi>Heads</hi> of this <hi>Examination,</hi> about which the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> are unjuſtly charged.</head>
            <list>
               <head>PART. I.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF our Adverſaries</hi> Title, Page 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Light, Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 2. to p. 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Soul, p. 7. to p. 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Perfection <hi>and</hi> Infallibility, p. 9. to p. 16.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Bible, Holy Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 16, 17.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Immediate Revelation, p. 18, 19.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Letter <hi>and</hi> Holy Scriptures, p. 19. to p. 23.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Churches Power to determine differences, p. 23, 24.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Chriſt in the Fleſh, and extent <hi>of the Word, <hi>Type, Figure,</hi> and of</hi> Chriſt crucified, p. 24, 25.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Baptiſm, Carnal Ordinances, Liberty Spiritual, p. 26, 27.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:58919:5"/>
               <item>Of <hi>Government, Earthly Kings, Princes, Parliaments,</hi> &amp;c. p. 28, to 36</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Samuel Fiſher's Meſſage to Oliver Cromwell, in</hi> 1656. p. 37, 38</item>
               <item>Of <hi>our Aſſemblies, Contributions, and the Innocency thereof,</hi> p. 39, to 44</item>
               <item>Of <hi>the Sufferings of the People of God,</hi> p. 44, 45, 46</item>
               <item>Of <hi>the ſame Intentions,</hi> differently <hi>worded,</hi> p. 47</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Bugg's Poſtſcript, Old Lies and Calumnies,</hi> p. 47, 48</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>PART II.</head>
               <item>OF the <hi>Furious Title</hi> of the Libel, p. 49</item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> p. 50, 51, 52</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Chriſt our Bleſſed Lord,</hi> p. 52, 53, 54, 55</item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Blood of Chriſt,</hi> p. 55, 56</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Body,</hi> p. 57</item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> p. 57, 58</item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> (ſo called) p. 58</item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> p. 59</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Equality with God,</hi> (falſly charged) p. 59, 60</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Chriſt's coming to Judge the Quick and the Dead,</hi> p. 61, 62</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt's Kingdom,</hi> p. 62, 63</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Kingly Government, Parliaments, Lords and Commons,</hi> p. 64</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Human Laws, Authority, Aſſociating, Governments, Tythes,</hi> &amp;c. p. 65</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Divine Authority, Governments, Meetings, Toleration, Perſecutors,</hi> &amp;c. p. 66, 67, 68.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Treatment of Kings, Clergy, and other Diſſenters,</hi> p. 68, 69</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Penn's Anſwer to ſeveral Charges againſt him,</hi> p. 70, 71, 72</item>
            </list>
            <p>Where any Literal or other Faults have eſcaped the Preſs, 'tis hoped the Ingenuous Reader will excuſe the Author, and recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame by the Senſe and Coherence of the Matter.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58919:5"/>
            <head>Truth <hi>and</hi> Innocency <hi>VINDICATED,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>PART I.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT is obſervable, that the Title of the ſaid <hi>Brief Diſcovery,</hi> is a general and moſt ſevere Charge againſt ſome of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Practices of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> without exception.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the ſaid <hi>Brief Diſcovery</hi> conſiſts chiefly of Quotations, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be taken out of <hi>their moſt noted and approved Authors;</hi> unto which theſe Three <hi>Clergy-Men</hi> of <hi>Norfolk</hi> have given the Black and Odious Character,—<hi>Blaſphemous and Seditious Principles and Practices of the People called Quakers;</hi> on purpoſe to make the whole Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as Offenſive and Obnoxious as they could Miſchievouſly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the ſaid <hi>Clergy-Men</hi> have <hi>Humbly</hi> (as they feign) <hi>Offered</hi> their ſaid pretended <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> and bitter Charge againſt the ſaid People, <hi>to the Conſideration of the King and both Houſes of Parliament;</hi> under ſuch Pretences, endeavouring to Incenſe them againſt the ſaid Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and conſequently to deprive them of their Religious Liberty (legally Granted them, and others by Authority) under that invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, as well as falſe Pretence of their being <hi>Blaſphemous and Seditious</hi> in Principle and Practice.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That we may juſtly take for granted, that the Opinion of theſe Three <hi>Norfolk Clergy-Men</hi> is contrary to what they have quoted, as <hi>Blaſphemous</hi> and <hi>Seditious,</hi> in each particular ſo quoted by them, and that they hold Principles and Practices contrary to thoſe ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by them, as Blaſphemous and Seditious.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:58919:6"/>
               <p>There's two things to be Examin'd in the Sequel:</p>
               <p n="1">1ſt. Their Quotations, whether Partial or Impartial, Juſt or Unjuſt, True or Falſe?</p>
               <p n="2">2d. Where Quotations, or Citations, are truly given either by them, or made appear as they are by us: Whether the matter it ſelf be of a <hi>Blaſphemous</hi> Import, or their ſo Charging the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> That many Words and Things are Partially and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly left out in their Quotations, are in this Examen truly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, or References had hereto.</p>
               <p>Now let's proceed to examine ſome of theſe Three <hi>Clergy-Men</hi>'s Principal Quotations, charg'd upon us as <hi>Blaſphemous.</hi> Their Firſt and Principal Quotations ſo Charged follows.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I. <hi>Of the Light.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Their firſt Charge of <hi>Blaſphemous Principles againſt the ſaid People, viz.</hi> George Fox. <hi>the Firſt Founder and great Apoſtle of this Sect,</hi> Great Myſtery, p. 209. <hi>ſaith againſt his Opponent thus,</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">This Light that doth enlighten every one that cometh into the World, which he calls Conſcience <hi>[Is the Light that doth enlighten every Man that cometh into the World,
<note place="margin">Theſe Lines are left out of their Citation.</note> that through him they might believe]</hi> and is not Conſcience, <hi>[and he that believes, hath the Witneſs in himſelf, and that all might hear the Son, and confeſs him to the Glory of God; and therefore are enlightened,</hi> &amp;c.</q> And in p. 331. he further ſaith, <q rend="margQuotes">The Light which every one that cometh into the World is enlightned withall, is not Conſcience; for the Light was before any thing was made, or Conſcience named.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here obſerve, that they alſo leave out of the very next diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing words, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>So the Light is that which exerciſeth the Conſcience towards God and towards Man, where it is loved, and the Voice heard: But where it is hated, and the Voice not heard, the Conſcience is Seared, and the Light is their Condemnation, whoſe Conſciences is Seared; which</hi> (i. e. <hi>Light) was before Conſcience was.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now pray obſerve, where's the <hi>Blaſphemous Principle?</hi> Is it in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That this Light which doth enlighten every Man that cometh into the World,</hi> John 1.4, 9. is not Conſcience, but was before any thing was made, or Conſcience named? Have not theſe <hi>Clergy-Men</hi> herein charged both <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel-Teſtimony with Blaſphemy, and <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58919:6"/>own Teſtimony alſo? See <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 4, to verſ. 10. How clear and evident the Evangeliſt is in this caſe for us; That the <hi>Word <hi>which was in the beginning, which was with God, and was God; by which all things were made; and in which was Life, and the Life was the Light of Men; even that</hi>
                     </hi> Word (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Son of God) <hi>was the true Light which enlightens every Man that cometh into the World.</hi> 'Tis no Blaſphemy to ſay, That God was before Conſcience was, or Man was made; and that this <hi>Word</hi> (this Eternal Son of God) was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Conſcience was, and before any thing was made, or Conſcience named: Seeing <hi>All things were made by him, and without him was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing made that was made.</hi> So that the Charge of Blaſphemy in this caſe does not only affect us (the People called <hi>Quakers</hi>) but <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, who ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the World, he that followeth me, ſhall not abide in Darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life,</hi> John 8.12. And <hi>Believe in the Light, that you may be Children of the Light.</hi> And the whole <hi>Soul, Mind</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> of Man muſt be Exerciſed, Inſtructed and Swayed by this Light, or elſe Man's Conſcience is not only weak, but defiled alſo, and may become Seared: But ſo is not this Divine Light, it remains Pure and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible. So that the Light, whereby not only we, but every Man ought to be guided, is the true Eternal God, and Chriſt the Word, which ſo to teach or aſſert, is not Blaſphemy, as you (our Adverſaries) have Reproach'd us.</p>
                  <p>We pity your Ignorance in this principal Point; for let's take your contrary Opinion to what you have here charg'd with Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and then 'tis, <hi>That Light which enlightens every Man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the World,</hi> John 1.4, 9. <hi>was not before any thing was made, or Conſcience named;</hi> which is to oppoſe the Deity or Divinity of the Son of God, the Word which was with God, by which both Man and all things were made.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Charge of Blaſphemy, p. 3. viz. <hi>And</hi> G. F. Junior, <hi>in his Works, Reprinted</hi> 1665. p. 50. <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>I the Light will fall upon you, and grind you to Powder. All — who will not own me the Light in you. And — I will make you know that I the Light am the true Eternal God, which Created all things; and that by me, the Light, all things are upheld, and that there is not another beſides me that can ſave.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſerve,</hi> Though what's here be very Partially Cited, 'tis no Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy; the Quotation is very unfairly taken by theſe our Accuſers, not taking notice either of the Title of this part of <hi>G. F. Junior</hi>'s Book, or to whom writ, or what he further clearly ſaith for the Light.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58919:7"/>
                  <p>His Title of what he writes in that part, being <hi>The Words of the Everlaſting and True Light, who is the Eternal Living God, and the King of Saints, which he gave unto me his Servant, to declare unto the Inhabitants of the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. He ſpeaks therefore in the Name of God and Chriſt, as the true Light, and not in his own name; and thoſe to whom he ſaith, <hi>I the Light will grind you to Powder,</hi> are ſuch as <hi>Murderers, Whoremongers, Thieves, Cheaters, Swearers, Lyars,</hi> &amp;c. and all Workers of Iniquity, who hate the Light, which hath made <hi>manifeſt their Abominations,</hi> and reproved them for them. Theſe, with other words, previous to what's quoted, are left out, <hi>As I have been preſt with your Iniquities: But I the Light will ariſe upon you, and if you will not hear and return ſpeedily, I'll fall upon you, and grind you to Powder.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And is this Blaſphemous pray? Have you not here ſo charged the Teſtimony of Chriſt himſelf, who is the <hi>Light of the World,</hi> and the <hi>Chief Corner-Stone,</hi> the <hi>Foundation-Stone,</hi> ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.42, 44. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.18. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall fall on this Stone, he ſhall be broken: But on whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it ſhall fall, it ſhall Grind him to Powder.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">After [I'll make you know, that I the Light (theſe are left out) <hi>(which lighteth every Man which cometh into the World, that all through me ſhould believe) am the true Eternal God, which Created all things.</hi> &amp;c.</q> Where's the Blaſphemy in all theſe? Surely none, feeing <hi>God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all,</hi> 1 John 1.5. <hi>The Lord is my Light and my Salvation,</hi> Pſalm 27.1. <hi>And there is one God the Father, who is above all, and through all, and <hi>in</hi> you all,</hi> Epheſ. 4.6. <hi>And know you not, how that Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (the true Light) <hi>is in you, except you be Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates?</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5. God, who is Light, and Chriſt the Light of the World, is ſo in all, as he enlightens all Mankind: <hi>God who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhined in our Hearts,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. Now it is evident, what theſe Adverſaries call <hi>Blaſphemous,</hi> is teſtified in <hi>Holy Scripture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Charge of <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> p. 3. <q rend="margQuotes">In <hi>Geo. Fox</hi>'s Book, ſtyled, <hi>The Pearl found in England,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1658. where ſpeaking in the Perſon of the <hi>Quaker's Light,</hi> he hath theſe Paſſages, p. 15, 16. <hi>I'll break in Pieces, I'll make Nations like Dirt, I'll tread them into the Mire,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>With divers other Prophetical Paſſages, partially pick'd up, minced and curtailiz'd; and many Lines left out, where the daſhes are; as againſt <hi>Pride, Hypocriſie, Covetous Practices, Hypocrites, Falſe Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. All within the Threats, and Propheſied againſt in the Name of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58919:7"/>Lamb, and Life of God, and if truly read, agreeable to the Holy Prophets in Scripture, <hi>Thou ſhalt cruſh them with a Scepter of Iron, or with a Rod of Iron, and break them in Pieces like a Potters Veſſel,</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied of the Son of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8, 9. And will not the Lord tread down his Enemies? <hi>I will Tread them in mine Anger, and Trample them in my Fury,</hi> Iſa. 63.3. Now is it not great Preſumption to deem ſuch Propheſies Blaſphemous?</p>
                  <p>Theſe words are alſo quoted and included in their charge of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, <hi>i. e.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">The Wrath of the Lamb is riſen upon all Apoſtates, who are gathered in the Apoſtacy, Apoſtatiz'd from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's Life, the Apoſtles Life, the Life of the Lamb, the Lamb is Riſen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the pure Life of God is Riſen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Juſt will Rule, <hi>the Lamb will have the Victory:</hi> Woes, Woes and Miſeries are out-going upon all the Heads of the Wicked. What our Hands have Handled, and what our Eyes have Seen, what was from the Beginning, the Word of Life, this declare we unto you.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>What a ſtrange Preſumption is it, that theſe Men ſhould charge us with Blaſphemy, for ſuch paſſages as theſe, which are directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with Holy Scripture Prophecies, againſt the Wicked, and for the Lamb's Power, Dominion and Judgment, againſt them, Apoſtates and others? And for our handling and ſeeing the Word of Life, which was from the Beginning; we knowing, and ſincerely profeſſing, the Lord God and the Lamb to be our Light, and no other, ſee, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Nahum</hi> 1.2. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.14, 15. <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.12. <hi>John</hi> 3.36. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1, 18. and 2.5, 8. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16, 17. and 14.10. and 15.1.7. and 18.3. See Wo, and Woes, and to whom, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.8, 11. and 18.20. and 10.1.</p>
                  <p n="4">4th Charge of Blaſphemy, p. 4.</p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>G. Fox,</hi> in his Book, ſtiled, <hi>The Teachers of the World <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd,</hi> &amp;c. in p. 27. thus ſaith, <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>I am the Light of the World,</hi> him by whom the World was made; if you love the Light, with which you are enlightened withall; you love Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Learn of me:</hi> But if you hate that Light, there is your Condemnation, from him who is one with the <hi>Truth</hi> in every Man, who of the Lord was moved thus to write. — whoſe name, of the World, is called <hi>G. Fox.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Here are ſeveral Lines left out, before the laſt words relating to <hi>G. F</hi>'s name; wherein mention is made of what he means, that 'twas the <hi>Light which the Apoſtles were in:</hi> Which could not be meant of <hi>G. F. himſelf,</hi> who was not in the Apoſtles days, nor born in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, until many hundred Years after their days;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58919:8"/>thus perverſe and impertinent are theſe Men in their Charge and Proofs.</p>
                  <p>'Tis evident, <hi>G. F.</hi> here ſpeaks in the name of Chriſt, and for him, and not of himſelf, or in his own name, but of Chriſt the Light, who <hi>Enlightneth every Man, — and who is Lord over all:</hi> And <hi>G. F.</hi> writes as his Servant, <hi>moved by him,</hi> and therefore 'twas very unjuſt, as well as great Envy in theſe Perſons, to make this an Inſtance of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Blaſphemy, ſee <hi>John</hi> 1.9. and 3.19.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Their next Charge of <hi>Blaſpemy againſt us,</hi> p. 4. Is, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">And to <hi>This,</hi> another of their Eminent Teachers, one of their Prophets, ſays <hi>Amen,</hi> in his Book, <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>Challenge,</hi> &amp;c. print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, </q> 1668.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of</hi> G. F. <hi>'tis ſaid, who is a Prophet indeed, and hath been Faithful in the Lord's Buſineſs from the Beginning. It was ſaid of Chriſt, that he was in the World, and the World was made by him, and the World knew him not: So it may be ſaid of this true Prophet</hi> [George Fox added] <hi>whom</hi> John <hi>ſaid he was not. But thou wilt feel this Prophet</hi> [George Fox again added] <hi>one day as heavy as a Milſtone upon thee. And altho' the World knows him not, yet he is known,</hi> p. 5.</p>
                  <p>Theſe words [whom <hi>John</hi> ſaid he was not] we diſown in that place, they are confuſedly miſplaced.</p>
                  <p>And the Author was not one of the moſt Approved or Eminent among us, as falſly repreſented, tho a more Honeſt and well Intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man, than Skilful in Expreſſion; as in this caſe his Intention ought to be conſidered.</p>
                  <p>He could not intend, that the World was made by <hi>G. F.</hi> (as he did after explain himſelf in Print) but by Jeſus Chriſt, by whom <hi>God Created all things,</hi> Epheſ. 3.9. Heb. 1.2. but that the World knew him not, he intended relative both to Chriſt, and to his Servant, as 'tis ſaid of the Sons of God, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.1. The World knoweth us not, becauſe it knew not him.</p>
                  <p>As there could be no Blaſphemy or Reproach to God or Chriſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the aforeſaid recited Paſſage, ſo neither can the People call'd <hi>Quakers</hi> be juſtly charged therewith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">That we-may ſee cauſe to word ſome things otherwiſe than ſome have, and yet mean the ſame thing, is often repeated by <hi>F. Bugg,</hi>
                     </q> and theſe Perſons, tho I ſee no real advantage they get by it againſt us: For ſuppoſe any one does unſafely, or untelligibly, or dubiouſly word any matter? And I find his meaning to be ſafe, and give a true Explication thereof, according to the Honeſt or Innocent mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Author, from other paſſages, his meaning therein, is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58919:8"/>to mine (which I ſafely and ſincerely expreſs) tho' his words are not altogether the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="6">6th Charge of <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Edw. Burroughs, <hi>In his works,</hi> p. 149. <hi>Has an Anſwer to this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, is that very Man, with that very Body, within you,</hi> Yea <hi>or</hi> Nay? <hi>He ſaith, the very Chriſt of God is within us, we dare not deny him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> To Inſtance this for a Proof of Blaſphemy againſt us, is to Charge the Holy Apoſtle with Blaſphemy, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Examine your ſelves whether you be in the Faith, Prove your own ſelves, know ye not your own ſelves, how that Jeſus Chriſt is <hi>in</hi> you, except ye be Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quaery,</hi> Was not this the very Chriſt of God, ſuppoſe ye? Or is there any more than one Lord Jeſus Chriſt? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. though his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance hath been in divers manners, as in the Fleſh and in the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>He who is the very Chriſt of God, is truly Spiritually in true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſee alſo, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.27. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. which is no Blaſphemy to aſſert, as we are unjuſtly aſperſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the SO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L.</head>
                  <p n="7">7th. Inſtance of <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> charg'd p. 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>G. F.</hi> Great Myſt. p. 91. <hi>They ſhall ſee the Biſhop of their</hi> Souls, <hi>Chriſt the Power of God, which is Immortal, brings the Immortal Soul into the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal God, Chriſt, their Sanctification, who Sanctifies their Spirits and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and brings the Soul up into God, from whence it came, whereby they came to be one Soul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qu.</hi> Where's the Blaſphemy here, pray?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That Chriſt is the Biſhop of the Soul, is true, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That he is the Power of God, and the Wiſdom of God, is alſo true, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That Chriſt of God, is made unto us Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification, and Redemption, is alſo true, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.4.</p>
                  <p>The Rational <hi>Soul</hi> or <hi>Spirit</hi> of Man is Immortal; and 'tis Chriſt that Redeems and brings it up into God that gave it, and they that are joyned to the Lord, are one Spirit, is alſo true. See <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.21. &amp; ch. 12.7. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.</p>
                  <p>I wiſh theſe Men that are ſo ready to call ſuch-like Doctrine Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, would more ſeriouſly read the Holy Scriptures.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58919:9"/>
                  <p>As for <hi>G. F</hi>'s Queſtion, Is not <hi>this</hi> that cometh out from God, <hi>Part of God,</hi> of God, and from God, <hi>&amp;c. and that 'tis not horrid Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy ſo to ſay?</hi> Gr. Myſt. p. 100, 273. The Term <hi>Part</hi> of God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be Originally by ſome Adverſaries obtruded upon the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> and not <hi>G. F</hi>'s, but only admitted by him, as from them, and then Queſtions them in their own Improper Terms, for God is not to be divided into <hi>Parts.</hi> And where 'tis ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">God breathed into Man <hi>the breath of Life, and he became a living Soul,</hi> and thereupon Queſtion'd, Is not <hi>this</hi> that cometh out from God, or <hi>that</hi> which came out from God, of God's Being?</q> 
                     <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 100. <hi>This</hi> and <hi>that</hi> expreſly relates to that <hi>Divine Inſpiration, or Breath of Life</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Man became a Living Soul) and not to the Creature, Man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or the Rational Soul, or Spirit of Man, as ſuch. The Queſtion is not whether the diſtinct Souls or Spirits of Men, are not of God's Being? For that were as abſurd, as to ask if the Creature Man be not God? About this Point our Adverſaries quote <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 91, 100, 273, 100, 90. Thus back and forward: but ſtill leaves our what's moſt Material and Explanatory, about the Soul or Spirit of Man, and <hi>that</hi> which came out from God, whereby <hi>Man became</hi> a <hi>living Soul,</hi> as <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 91.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">The Soul being in Death in Tranſgreſſion, ſo Man's Spirit there is not Sanctified, and the Soul is in Death. But he further declares on the other hand, where the living of the Soul or Spirit is, That 'tis there Sanctified, and the Counſel of God diligently hearken'd unto, and ſtood in, and Chriſt their Sanctification, Sanctifies their Spirits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 100. <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>God breathed into Man the breath of Life, and he</hi> (i. e. Man) <hi>became a living Soul.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe Paſſages our Adverſaries leave out, which ſhews their great Injurious Partiality, and how inconſiderate they are of the diſtinction included between God and Man, the Creator and the Creature; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>that</hi> Divine Breath or Spirit of Life, which came out from God, and the Creature Man, who <hi>thereby</hi> became a living Soul.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Soul</hi> is ſometime put for God, (<hi>Prov.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38.) his Divine Life, Breath or Spirit, as the Great and Univerſal Soul of Mankind, even the Soul (or Life) of the Soul, as ſome Phraſe it.</p>
                  <p>The Objection againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> in this Point, is more fully Anſwered, in my Treatiſe, Entituled, <hi>The Chriſtianity of the People, commonly call'd</hi> Quakers, <hi>Vindicated from Antichriſtian Oppoſition,</hi> Printed 1690, p. 4. as followeth:</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58919:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Here the Doctor <hi>(i. e. Forde)</hi> has unfairly Quoted <hi>G. F.</hi> upon Truſt, leaving out what's moſt Material, both Diſtinction and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation, about the Soul or Spirit of Man, both with relation to its Creator, and to the Creature Man, being ſpoken of in both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects by our Friend. 1. Where <hi>G. F.</hi> inſiſts on the Words, <hi>God breathed into Man the breath of Life, and he became a Living Soul.</hi> It was to this Breath (or Spirit) of Life (as immediately coming from God) that his Words related, as his Queſtion plainly ſhews, <hi>i. e.</hi> was not <hi>that</hi> of God, and of his Being, which came out from God? Meaning, that <hi>Divine Breath,</hi> or <hi>Spirit of Life,</hi> by which <hi>Man</hi> became a <hi>Living Soul;</hi> and from whence came not only Man's Natural Breath and Life, but alſo his Spiritual: And this does di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between the Divine Being, and the Creature Man, and not confound their Beings. And for the Soul or Spirit of Sanctified Man to center with God, this is not to render it the Being of God, or God Himſelf. We know none (profeſſing the true God and Chriſt) ſo groſly abſurd, as to ſay, <hi>That Man made himſelf,</hi> or <hi>was his own Maker, Saviour,</hi> or <hi>Redeemer.</hi> 2. Our Friend ſpeaks plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſame Book, quoted againſt him. <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 90, 91, 100. <hi>That the Soul ſhould be ſubject to the Power of God; That Chriſt is the Biſhop of the Soul, who brings it up into God; the Soul being in Death in Tranſgreſſion, Man's Spirit not Sanctified,</hi> &amp;c. This could not intend the <hi>Being of God,</hi> for <hi>that</hi> never ſinned, though there be ſomething thereof in the Soul; even in that Reaſonable Soul or Spirit of Man, which God (by his Divine Word, Breath, or Spirit) formed in Man, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.1. And ſo <hi>made</hi> Man a Living Soul.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>do not make themſelves Equal with God, and of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="8">8th. Inſtance. <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> Printed 1654. p. 8. <hi>He that hath the ſame Spirit that raiſed up Jeſus Chriſt, is equal with God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We deny the Words, as there Printed, to be according to <hi>G. F</hi>'s Senſe, or ours, which is, <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>That the Holy Ghoſt, and the Son, is equab with the Father in Power and Glory; then if any come to witneſs the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, they come to Wieneſs <hi>that</hi> which is Equal in Power and Glory with the Father. What if any come to Witneſs the Son of God, revealed in them (which he that hath not Him, hath not Life) do they not come to witneſs <hi>Him</hi> who is Equal in Power and Glory with the Father,</hi> as in <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 100.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58919:10"/>
                  <p>Therefore the Words [He that hath] in the ſaid Inſtance, ſhould be left out, being contrary to <hi>G. F</hi>'s, and our Principle, and to his own very Words and Confeſſion, a little before, in the ſame Book, where, <q rend="margQuotes">being charg'd with Profeſſing himſelf to be <hi>equal</hi> with God, he poſitively denies the Charge, but confeſſes the Father and the Son are <hi>one,</hi> and that Chriſt and the Holy Spirit are equal with God, p. 5, 6. And ſo Chriſt Jeſus, hoth as He was of the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi>and alſo as he was Equal with God (<hi>i. e.</hi> both to his <hi>Manhood and Divinity.</hi>)</q> Therefore 'tis falſly noted in their Margent, <hi>That they</hi> (i. e. <hi>the Quakers) make themſelves Equal with God.</hi> Though they believe a Renewing into his Image, by his Spirit and Power, and to be thereby made Conformable to the Image of his Son, and ſo to be made <hi>like</hi> him, as every really Godly Man, and true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in Chriſt is, in ſome degree, as Partakers of the Divine Nature; yet the Creature Man is not <hi>Eſſentially Equal</hi> with his Maker, that was never our Principle ſo to confound their <hi>Beings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. Again, to prove the <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt us, <hi>Fr. Howgill</hi>'s Works, p. 232. is quoted, <hi>viz. He that is joined to the Lord, is one Spirit: There is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity ſtands in</hi> Equality <hi>it ſelf. When the Son is revealed, and ſpeaks, the Father ſpeaks in him, and dwells in him, and he in the Father, in</hi> that <hi>which is equal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Here the <hi>Equality</hi> is placed between the Father and the Son, as the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is between Him and them, who are joined to Him in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and live and dwell in that Spirit which is Equal. Where's then the Blaſphemy? See Chriſt's Prayer, <hi>John</hi> 17.21. <hi>That they all may be one, as thou, O Father, art in Me, and I in Thee, that they may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo one in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, that the World may believe that Thou haſt ſent me.</hi> Ver. 22. <hi>And the Glory which thou gaveſt Me, I have giventhem, that they may be one, as We are one.</hi> Ver. 23. <hi>I in them, and Thou in Me, that they may be made Perfect in one, that the World may know that Thou haſt ſent Me, and haſt loved them, as Thou haſt loved Me.</hi> See alſo Ver. 26.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Equality in Nature</hi> (objected) relates to the Divine Nature, which the Child of God partakes of in meaſure, <hi>Tho' not in Stature,</hi> relates to the Child; <hi>that</hi> Divine Nature is one, and unchangeable; but our participating of it, and growth in it, is Gradual until all, (<hi>i. e.</hi> Chriſt's whole Church and Body) come unto the meaſure of the Stature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12, 13. Now if <hi>Equality</hi> be <hi>apply'd</hi> to the Saints, it can be intended no otherwiſe, than their hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them a living <hi>Reſemblance</hi> or <hi>Likeneſs,</hi> of him who has renewed them into his own Image by the Power of his Spirit, that is, into his Righteouſneſs, and true Holineſs, ſo as to be partakers thereof
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58919:10"/>in Chriſt Jeſus: And <hi>not</hi> an Eſſential Equality between them (being Creatures) and <hi>him</hi> that created and renewed them. Perfect Holineſs and Righteouſneſs being required and believed, of all true and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtians in Chriſt Jeſus: Yet we do not pretend to the Infinite Fulneſs of Wiſdom and Knowledge, as it is in God and Chriſt; or to his manifold Wiſdom, but to a Degree of Divine Wiſdom and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, according as his Spirit reveals it is to us (and we capable to receive it) which therefore is perfectly true and certain, in every Meaſure and Degree thereof.</p>
                  <p>Now, Serious Reader, note by the way, that we have more right to interpret our deceaſed Friends words (with whom we were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant, when living to ſuch an Evangelical Senſe, as we knew they intended) than theſe Adverſaries have to Charge them and us with <hi>Blaſphemous Principles,</hi> from their own Partial, Minced, Mangled and Broken Quotations, as are and may be juſtly enumerated upon them, together with their divers falſe notes in the Margent.</p>
                  <p n="9">9th Inſtance to prove <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt us, p. 6, 7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>G. F. Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 107. <hi>He ſaith (ſpeaking of the Prieſt) the Holyeſt Man that is, is not able to give an Infallible Character of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man:</hi> To which he anſwers, <hi>Haſt not thou, in this, diſcovered thy ſelf to be no Miniſter of Chriſt, or of the Spirit, who cannot give an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Character of another Man? How canſt thou Miniſter to his condition?</hi> p. 96. <hi>and thou not being Infallible, thou art not in the Spirit, and ſo art not a Miniſter of Chriſt, and art not able to Judge of Powers, that is not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, nor Magiſtrates, nor Kingdoms, nor Churches,</hi> p. 33. <hi>And are they Miniſters of Chriſt that are Fallible?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Tho' theſe Inſtances to prove us Guilty of Blaſphemous Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, are very unfairly quoted, the principal and moſt demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Words (both precedent and ſubſequent eſpecially) being left out by theſe Three <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> as from the laſt words [are they Miniſters of Chriſt that are Fallible?] they leave out theſe material Queſtions, both before and after them, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Now he that is not Infallible in his Counſel, Judgment and Advice, is not he in Error? And are not the Miniſters of Chriſt, the Miniſters of the Spirit? And is not <hi>that</hi> out of the Error, which is Infallible in Counſel and Judgment? And are they Miniſters of Chriſt that are Fallible? And is not the Power, the Goſpel Infallible?</q> Thus <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 33.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding they have quoted ſufficient, to ſhew what they deem Blaſphemy, and what they hold to the contrary, and their own not only Fallibility, but great Darkneſs, for to invert their ſenſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58919:11"/>contrary to what they have here quoted for Blaſphemy; and it muſt run thus, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Holieſt Man that is, is not able to give an Infallible Character of another Man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That a Miniſter of Chriſt, or of the Spirit, cannot give an Infallible Character of another Man, and yet Miniſter to his Condition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That a Minſter that's Fallible, is in the Spirit a Miniſter of Chriſt; and yet cannot diſcern another Man's State or Condition, ſo as to give an Infallible Character of him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Conſequently Chriſt's Miniſters, without exception, the Holieſt of them all are hereby rendred not only Fallible but Uncertain in their Miniſtry, Blind and Ignorant of the Spiritual States and Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others.</p>
                  <p>All which ſhews theſe Guides to be in the Dark, and very uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, blind, and Ignorant, as well as Envious in their Calumniating us with <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> for confeſſing to Infallibility, ſound Judgment and Diſcerning, which we aſcribe not to our ſelves alone, without the Spirit's Teachings and Guidance; but originally and principally to the Spirit of Truth, which Guides true Chriſtians into all <hi>Truth,</hi> which in it ſelf is Infallible, Unerring and Certain; and ſo is the Teaching and Miniſtry thereof: And ſo far as we are taught and led by the Spirit, we are aſſured by it, and led into ſound Judgment, Certainty and full Aſſurance both of Faith and Doctrine in matters of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Revealed in the Goſpel and Spiritual Miniſtry of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord and Bleſſed Saviour, (tho' we aſcribe not omniſcience to our ſelves in any ſtate.) He that abides in Chriſt ſinneth not, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3.6. conſequently errs not, is certain, and <hi>as <hi>in</hi>
                     </hi> Chriſt, is infallible in matters of Salvation and Chriſt's Kingdom, he is <hi>in</hi> the way of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>in</hi> which the wayfaring-man ſhall not err, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 35.8. If we follow our own Spirits, and lean to our own Natural Underſtandings, or Humane Reaſon, we may err and miſtake; but if we adhere cloſely to the Spirit of Chriſt, the Truth, and be attentive to its Teaching and Guidance, we ſhall not err nor be deceived. <hi>My Sheep hear my voice,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and a Stranger they will not follow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if there muſt be no diſcerning of Spirits, no infallible or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Character to be given of other Men's States or Conditions by an inward ſenſe or diſcerning of Spirits, then Chriſt's Sheep may follow Strangers, Wolves, Dogs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo be devoured, contrary to his own Doctrine, and below the ſenſe and inſtinct of the very Sheep which leads them to ſhun Dogs and Wolves, when they make at them, whether they Bark, or Howl, or be Mute.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58919:11"/>
                  <p>And who dare adventure their Bodies in the hands of ſuch ignorant Phyſicians as have no certain underſtanding of Diſeaſes or of <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines?</hi> How much leſs their Souls with ſuch Doctors?</p>
                  <p>And how ſhall Satan, transform'd, be prevented from making ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock in the Church of Chriſt, if no certain diſcerning in the Church of his Attempts?</p>
                  <p>Then as to the certainty and infallibility of Chriſt's Miniſters in the work of his Miniſtry. We are not as many who corrupt, (or make merchandize) of the Word of God, but as of ſincerity, but as of God in the ſight of God, <hi>ſo</hi> ſpeak we in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.17.</p>
                  <p>And our Goſpel was not unto you in Word only, but alſo in Power and in the Holy Ghoſt, and in <hi>much</hi> aſſurance, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p n="10">10th. Inſtance to prove <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt us, p. 7.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> p. 862. <hi>Such</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> Hereticks) <hi>are infallibly known and diſcerned by the Spirit of God in the true Chunch of Chriſt, and by every member of the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Seeing this is made a proof of Baſphemy againſt us, let the contrary be Inverted upon theſe accuſers; and then it muſt be, <hi>That Hereticks are not infallibly known and diſcerned by the Spirit of God in the true Church of Chriſt, nor by the members thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Contrary to what God has promiſed his People; and to what has been, and is experienced in the true Church, where the Spirit and Power of Chriſt is preſent among them, and humbly Obeyed.</p>
                  <p>Then ſhall you return and diſcern between the Righteous and the Wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.18. and <hi>Job.</hi> 6.30.</p>
                  <p>A wiſe Man's heart diſcerneth both Time and Judgment, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.8. <hi>He that is Spiritual judgeth all things, yet himſelf is judged of no Man,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.15. And there was, and is, true Judgment and Diſcerning in the Church of Chriſt, proceeding from his Spirit in the true and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Believers in Chriſt; ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2, 3, 4, 5. and Chap. 14.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14.</p>
                  <p>Yea further, It was propheſied by <hi>Enoch,</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> againſt ſuch Apoſtates as are mentioned in <hi>Juda</hi>'s Epiſtle, ſaying, <hi>behold the Lord cometh in ten Thouſands of his Saints</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>] <hi>[in Sanctis Millibus ſuis.]</hi> To execute Judgment upon all, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince all that are ungodly among them of all their Ungodly Deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard Speeches which Ungodly Sinners have ſpoken againſt him, <hi>Jude.</hi> 14.15.</p>
                  <p>And theſe our Adverſaries are accountable to God for all their Hard Speeches, Severe and Unjuſt Judgment and Condemnation againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58919:12"/>his People, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> preſuming to condemn us all as Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Hereticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from their own uncertain fallible and errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgments and Spirits; but he that juſtifieth the wicked, and he that condemneth the Innocent, are both abomination to the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="11">11th Inſtance for proof of <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> againſt us, p. 7.</p>
                  <p>G. F. Gr. Myſt. p. 282. <hi>Whereas Mr.</hi> Cawdry <hi>ſaid, ſurely they cannot be perfect here or hereafter in Equality but only in Quality.</hi> Fox <hi>Anſwers, Chriſt makes no diſtinction in his words, but ſaith, be ye perfect, even as your Heavenly Father is; and as he is, ſo are we, and that which is perfect, as he is perfect, is in Equality with the ſame thing which is of God, and from God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Within the ſame Period here are ſeveral material Words left out, wherein theſe Men have dealt very diſingenuouſly; next after the words [Be ye perfect, as your Heavenly Father is] <hi>and be ye mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful as he is,</hi> left out: After <hi>[that which is perfect] and merciful,</hi> left out. Again, after [as he is perfect] <hi>and merciful,</hi> left out.</p>
                  <p>Now where's the Blaſphemy pray? Was it not Chriſt's own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? Be ye Perfect, even <hi>as</hi> your Father which is in Heaven is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. In the Old Bible, printed in 1576. dedicated to Queen <hi>Elizabeth, Ye ſhall therefore be perfite, as your Father which is in Heaven is perfite;</hi> and noted in the Margent, <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>We muſt labour to attain unto the perfection of God, who of his free Liberality doth Good to them that are unworthy.</hi>
                     </q> And Luke 6.36. <hi>Be ye therefore merciful as your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is merciful.</hi> Now what diſtinction doſt Chriſt make in theſe Words and Precepts, as in point of Purity? And where's the Perfection in <hi>Quality</hi> granted then? And wherein muſt this Perfection conſiſt? 'Tis not for any Man or Men to be perfect God, but perfect Men, true Men, <hi>as</hi> their Heavenly Father is true God; Men after God's own heart, in Sincerity and Truth.</p>
                  <p>And was not Perfection of Holineſs, Righteouſneſs and Purity the holy Apoſtles Doctrine, Intent and End of their Miniſtry? Yea ſure. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.12, 13. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.28. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1. and Chap. 3.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. verſes.</p>
                  <p n="12">12th <hi>Inſtance, or Charge of Blaſphemy againſt us,</hi> p. 7.</p>
                  <p>G. F. Gr. Myſt. p. 101. ſaith, <hi>It is the Doctrine of Devils, that Preacheth, that Men ſhall have ſin, and be in a Warfare ſo long as they be on Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>P. 231. <hi>All who come to Chriſt, the Second</hi> Adam, <hi>they come to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and all who attain to Him, they attain to Perfection in the Life of God, out of the Firſt</hi> Adam.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58919:12"/>
                  <p>P. 271. <hi>For who are Sanctified have Perfect <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Perfect Knowledge, Perfect Holineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Not to inſiſt upon the Unfairneſs of theſe Men, in the Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Paſſages, leaving out the fore-going Lines, which carry Proof in them thereof, what's the Tendency and Conſequence of their Judging theſe Blaſphemous? But Firſt, <hi>That Men ſhall have ſin, and none obtain Victory over it (though they war againſt it) ſo long as they be on Earth.</hi> Secondly, <hi>That none who come to Chriſt, or attain to him, do attain to be perfect in Him, or in the Life of God.</hi> As if Perfection were not attainable in Chriſt, contrary to the Holy Apoſtles Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Miniſtry, which was for the Perfecting of the Saints, and to preſent them perfect in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Gol.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>And if Sin be the work of the Devil, and Chriſt be manifeſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it, then it is a Doctrine of Devils to Preach, That Men ſhall have Sin, and not overcome it, while on Earth; but Sin is the work of the Devil, and Chriſt is manifeſt to deſtroy it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis the Devils work to lead into Sin, but 'tis Chriſt's work to lead out of it. Chriſt's Miniſters are ſent to turn People from Satan's Power, to God's Power; conſequently from Satan's work and ſervice; they are the Devil's Miniſters, who Preach up Sin, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue term of Life, and that it ſhall not be overcome, nor perfect Sanctification obtain'd, during life, which therefore tends to keep People in Unbelief of Chriſt's Power and Work.</p>
                  <p n="13">13th <hi>Inſtance, or Charge of Blaſphemy,</hi> p. 7.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Will. Penn,</hi> in his <hi>Truth Exalted,</hi> Re-Printed 1671. <hi>Laughs at the Church of</hi> England <hi>Men, for confeſſing themſelves Sinners, and praying to God for Mercy—Alas, poor Souls!</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are not you at, Have Mercy upon us miſerable Sinners; there is no Health in us, from Seven to Seventy?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Alas poor Sinners! is not a ſign of Laughter at them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lamentation and Pity over their miſerable State, who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways confeſſing, but not forſaking their Sins. You may ſee what Proofs of Blaſphemy theſe Men produce againſt us.</p>
                  <p n="14">14th <hi>Inſtance, or Charge,</hi> p. 7.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> p. 33. ſaith, <hi>That God doth not accept any, where there is any Failing; all who do not fulfill the Law, and Anſwer every Demand of Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though none are accepted in any Act of Injuſtice, or Omiſſion of real Duty required, yet coming under Judgment for the ſame, and repenting thereof (as they ought to do) they obtain Mercy and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of God for Chriſt's ſake; whoſe Grace, though it Pardons
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58919:13"/>Sins paſt, through Faith and Repentance, yet does not Indulge or Juſtifie any in their Continuance in Sin, nor in wilful Sinning after Conviction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> His meaning is; <hi>Firſt,</hi> God doth not accept them in their Failing in Duty, and in their not doing what's Juſt; as when ſome complain their beſt Duties are ſinful, and they do not anſwer or obey Truth in their Actions. For our Acceptance is in Chriſt, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, and not out of Him. 2. If Men ſeek acceptance by their own Legal Performances, they fall ſhort. See <hi>James</hi> 2.10.</p>
                  <p>But theſe <hi>Adverſaries</hi> have unjuſtly left out the fore-going Words in their Quotation, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">But thoſe that love God, keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and they are not grievous: And theſe left out within the ſame <hi>Period.</hi>
                     </q> Now, doth God accept of any that do not <hi>love</hi> Him, who do <hi>Injuſtice</hi> and <hi>Iniquity?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now theſe <hi>Adverſaries</hi> having oppoſed the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim, Light</hi> and <hi>Perfection</hi> (Typified in the Breſt-plate of Judgment, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.30.) as teſtified and witneſſed in the Goſpel-Diſpenſation, they proceed to other <hi>Charges,</hi> to prove the People called <hi>Quakers, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous</hi> in <hi>Principle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15th <hi>Charge,</hi> p. 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In</hi> Truth defending the <hi>Quakers,</hi> written <hi>from the Spirit of Truth, in</hi> G. W. <hi>and</hi> G. F. <hi>Jun.</hi> Printed 1659. p. 7. <hi>The Queſtion being put, Whether the</hi> Quakers <hi>did eſteem their Speakings to be of as great Authority, as any Chapter in the Bible? 'Tis Anſwered;</hi> That which is ſpoken from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth <hi>In</hi>
                     </hi> any, is of as great Authority as the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Chapters</hi> are, and greater.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſerve;</hi> Here they have unjuſtly quoted <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> leaving out the Annexed Explanatory Words, which are within the ſame <hi>Period. viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">As <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Words were of greater Authority, when He <hi>Spoke,</hi> than the <hi>Phariſees</hi> reading the <hi>Letter;</hi> and they in whom that Spirit ſpeaks not, are out of the Authority of the Scriptures, and their Speaking we deny.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus far the Anſwer. <hi>Note</hi> here, that the Compariſon is not plac'd upon our <hi>Speakings,</hi> nor yet the <hi>Authority</hi> diſtinct from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth;</hi> but upon the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth ſpeaking <hi>in</hi> Man,</hi> in the firſt place, and <hi>through and by the Miniſters thereof,</hi> in the next place. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Spirit</hi> has not loſt his own <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Power,</hi> ſince it firſt gave out the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the next place, that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth immediately</hi> Miniſtring <hi>In</hi> Man, or by any Spiritual Miniſter, is of <hi>greater Authority, Power,</hi> or <hi>Efficacy,</hi> than the <hi>Chapters</hi> are (ſimply conſidered, as without the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58919:13"/>And as to the <hi>Diviſion</hi> of <hi>Chapters</hi> and <hi>Verſes,</hi> can theſe Men ſay, <hi>That was done by Divine Authority?</hi> I ſuppoſe not. Yet we ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely ſtill acknowledge the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to be of <hi>Divine Authority,</hi> as given by <hi>Divine Inſpiration,</hi> and prefer them before, and above all other Writings or Books, and in no wiſe queſtion the Truth of them. <q rend="margQuotes">But we muſt needs allow the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> (from whence they came) the Preference, and its <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Teaching</hi> and <hi>Speaking</hi> in the Soul, as of greater Efficacy, Power and Authority to that Soul, than the bare Writing, or <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture without,</hi> or only <hi>reading</hi> thereof, though it contain the ſame Words immediately taught: And ſo Chriſt and his Apoſtles living and powerful <hi>Preaching,</hi> in and from the Powerful Motion of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> as being of greater Efficacy, Power and Authority, than the <hi>outward Writing</hi> or <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf, ſimply or abſtractly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as diſtinct from that Spirit: Though the <hi>Words Preached,</hi> and the <hi>Words Written,</hi> may be the ſame. As when Chriſt had opened the <hi>Scriptures</hi> unto his Diſciples, they ſaid one to another, <hi>Did not our hearts burn within us, while he talked to us by the way, and while he opened to us the Scriptures?</hi> which concerned his Suffering, and entering into his Glory, <hi>Luke,</hi> 24.32. But how many by reading Chriſt's Words and Expoſition of the Prophets without his Spirit, do ever cauſe Peoples <hi>Hearts ſo to burn within</hi> them? The Goſpel, as livingly Preached, <hi>came not in Words only, but alſo in Power, and in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.5. For the real Authority, Efficacy, and Service the <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> has upon a Soul, is from the <hi>Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> or <hi>Word of Life,</hi> giving the true Belief, and right Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof:</q> As Anſwered in my <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> Intituled, <hi>The Chriſtianity of the People called Quakers, Vindicated,</hi> in <hi>Anſwer to Doctor</hi> Ford, p. 13. And in <hi>Chriſt's Lambs Defended,</hi> to the <hi>Reader,</hi> p. 7.</p>
                  <p>Their Inference in the Margent, <hi>That they</hi> (i.e. the Quakers) <hi>have immediate Revelations, equal with the Prophets and Apoſtles,</hi> Is not truly inferred; for we may have <hi>Immediate Revelation</hi> from the ſame <hi>Spirit,</hi> yet not in the ſame <hi>Degree.</hi> There are manifold <hi>Gifts, Openings,</hi> and <hi>Diſcoveries,</hi> given by the Holy Spirit, and yet ſome above, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling others: And ſo there are many <hi>Teſtimonies</hi> and Writings, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and given forth from the ſame Spirit, yet ſome far excelling others; as there are many <hi>Varieties</hi> in <hi>God's Creation.</hi> And it ever was, and is far from me, to prefer any of our <hi>Books</hi> or <hi>Writings</hi> (how true ſoever) to the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> or Bible.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58919:14"/>
                  <p n="16">16th. Charge, p. 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>G. F. Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 242. tells us, <hi>that the Prieſt ſaith, That the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were Eye-witneſſes, and underſtood by immediate Revelation from God, Inſpired with the Gift of the Spirit, more than any Man could hope for ſince, and ſaith, They do not pretend any ſuch Gift, nor depend upon any ſuch Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Miraculous Revelation from Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which <hi>G. E.</hi> Anſwers; <q rend="margQuotes">Then all may ſee now in this, what ye have receiv'd that hath been from Man, which is not from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Immediate, nor the Gifts of the Spirit, nor receiv'd the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by the ſame Means the Apoſtles did, who are not the Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, as the Apoſtles were. Neither have ye attained to the ſame Knowledge and Underſtanding, as the Apoſtles did, nor receiv'd it from Heaven.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now, let all People queſtion, Whether it is the ſame Goſpel, which is not receiv'd from Heaven, nor immediately, nor by Revelation, for the Goſpel is Immediate, which is the Power of God,</hi> Rom. 1. <hi>They</hi> (i. e. Quakers) <hi>are in the ſame Power, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Knowledge, and Immediate Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from Heaven, that the Apoſtles were in.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> The laſt Part is Partially quoted to abuſe us <hi>(i. e. Quakers)</hi> is added, and the Senſe perverted, by leaving out the laſt Words of the Sentence, as after the Words, [<q rend="margQuotes">they are in the ſame Power, Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Knowledge, and Immediate Revelation from Heaven, that the Apoſtles were in] — <hi>That <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand the Goſpel,</hi> left out: As alſo, "And they that be in another, cannot underſtand the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, for theſe Men to charge us with <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> for Confeſſing to Immediate Revelation and Inſpiration from God, by the Gift of the Spirit, and thence receiving the Goſpel, and a Spiritual Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Knowledge thereof, by Revelation from Heaven: Herein have they oppoſed the True Knowledge of God, and Jeſus Chriſt, and conſequently charged his own, and his Apoſtles Doctrine and Teſtimony as Blaſphemous, <hi>For neither knoweth any Man the Father but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveal Him,</hi> Mat. 11.27. <hi>And the things of God knows no Man, but by the Spirit of God, as they are reveal'd unto us by the Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9. They who oppoſe this Evangelical Doctrine, ſhew themſelves both Ignorant of God, of Chriſt, and of the things of God, and of his Teachings, which he has promiſed his Children, <hi>They ſhall all be taught of God,</hi> John 6.45. Iſa. 54.13. Jer. 31.33. Where, on <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.13. It is noted in the Margent in the old Bible (of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>By the hearing of his Word, and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> moving of his Spirit.</hi> And on <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. it is alſo noted,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58919:14"/>
                        <hi>viz.</hi> Under the Kingdom of Chriſt, there ſhall be none blinded with Ignorance, but I will give them Faith and Knowledge of God for Remiſſion of their Sins, and daily increaſe the ſame; ſo that it ſhall not ſeem to come ſo much by the Preaching of my Miniſters, as by the <hi>Inſtruction</hi> of my <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">17th Charge, p. 8, 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>G. F.</hi> further tells us, p. 213. <hi>That the Prieſt ſays, Thou doſt not ſpeak in that degree of the Holy Ghoſt, as the Prophets and Apoſtles did, that ſpoke forth Scriptures. To which he Anſwer, Then thou muſt take heed of Exalting thy ſelf above thy Meaſures, for thou canſt not know Scripture, but by the ſame degree of the Spirit, the Prophets and Apoſtles had.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. The Caution againſt Self-Exaltation was Seaſonable.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Scripture (<hi>i. e.</hi> the whole Scripture) cannot be truly known, but by a high degree of the Spirit, if not the ſame degree the Prophets and Apoſtles had, who gave it forth. But if any true Knowledge of Scripture be receiv'd, it muſt be by a Degree of the ſame Spirit, as I ſuppoſe, the Words before cited, ſhould be ſo Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, and ſo intended.</p>
                  <p>18th Charge, p. 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>News coming out of the North,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1655. p. 14. <hi>Your Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal is Carnal, Hebrew, Greek, and Latine, and your Word is Carnal, the Letter.</hi>—</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> The <hi>Letter</hi> it ſelf is not made up of Spiritual Matter, or Laſting Materials, but of ſuch as will decay, and turn to Duſt; but the Matter contain'd (that is, the <hi>Holy Doctrine</hi>) will continue, and is permanent. And this is no Vilifying or Contemning of Holy <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Holy Doctrine thereof.) Though this <hi>News out of the North,</hi> is quoted againſt us, yet it is very Partially and unfairly done. For in the ſame Book the Holy <hi>Scripture</hi> is clearly own'd, <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>As Spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Lord, and his Holy Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> p. 5.8. <hi>But the Promiſes and Words of the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applied by the firſt Birth and Serpent,</hi> p. 11, 12, 13, 16. <hi>The Law of God, and the Prophet of the Lord, who ſpake freely from his Mouth,</hi> expreſly ſo owned, page 23, 28. Though they that put the <hi>Letter</hi> for the <hi>Light,</hi> Preaching their own Words and Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereupon, are diſowned, page 12. Conſequently, the Holy Scriptures are own'd, but the <hi>Perverters</hi> and <hi>Perverſions</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own'd.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58919:15"/>
                  <p n="19">19th Charge, p. 9.</p>
                  <p>Tho. Lawſon, <hi>in his</hi> Brief Diſcovery of a Threefold Eſtate of Anti-Chriſt, <hi>printed,</hi> 1653. <hi>written from the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> p. 9. <hi>calls the Miniſters,</hi> Babylon<hi>'s Merchants, Selling Beaſtly Wares for a large Price,—the Letter, which is Duſt and Death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Their Injuſtice, and Falſe Quotation, in this Paſſage alſo, and and how they vary it from their Agent, <hi>Bugg</hi>'s, who often over, has herein accuſed us with calling the <hi>Scriptures, Beaſtly Ware,</hi> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of his Books, and alſo in his late great Sheet, ſtil'd, <hi>Some Reaſons Humbly Offered to the Honourable Houſe of Commons,</hi> p. 1. col. 1, 4. He has this <hi>Groſs Lie</hi> twice over, after divers times detected for it: So that theſe Three <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> do not agree in what they wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; like the <hi>Falſe Witneſſes</hi> againſt Chriſt: For, in the ſaid <hi>Brief Diſcovery,</hi> quoted, the words are theſe,—<q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Merchants, Selling Beaſtly Wares for a large Price, all the Week-time, heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a <hi>Rabble</hi> of <hi>Notions</hi> into the Brain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that <hi>Beaſtly Wares</hi> relate to their <hi>Rabble</hi> of <hi>Notions,</hi> of their own heaping up, and not to the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> nor to the <hi>Letter</hi> thereof, but to their bruitiſh Imaginations and Divinations of their own Brain; neither was this ſpoken of the <hi>Miniſters</hi> without Exception (as in the Quotation) much leſs of <hi>Chriſt's Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> but of the <hi>Falſe Miniſters,</hi> as the Title of that part is, p. 7.</p>
                  <p n="20">20th Charge, p. 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul's Errand to</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>printed,</hi> 1654. p. 7. <hi>Q. againſt</hi> G. F. <hi>All that ſtudy to raiſe a living thing out of a Dead, to raiſe the Spirit out of the Letter; are Conjurers, and draw Points and Reaſons, and ſo do ſpeak a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vination of their own Brain,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Here they are <hi>partial</hi> in Quotation again, leaving out the preceeding Paſſages, which diſtinguiſhing between the <hi>Letter</hi> and the <hi>Light,</hi> the <hi>Letter</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> judging them Blind that put the <hi>Letter</hi> for the <hi>Light,</hi> and ſay, <hi>The Letter and the Spirit are inſeparable.</hi> When the Spirit ſays, <hi>The Letter is Death and Killeth,</hi> according to 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7. now who will <hi>Study to raiſe a living thing out of a Dead, or to raiſe the Spirit out of the Letter?</hi> Is ſuch ſtudying warrantable? Who dare juſtifie it? And will not the Lord make Diviners Mad? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.25. and does not ſuch ſtudying to raiſe a Living thing out of a Dead, ſomewhat reſemble Conjuration? And did not the Prophet, <hi>Micah,</hi> Propheſie againſt ſuch Prieſts as <hi>Teach</hi> for <hi>Hire,</hi> and ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets as <hi>Divine</hi> for <hi>Mony?</hi> See <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.11.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58919:15"/>
                  <p n="21">21th Charge, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Truth's Defence, by</hi> G. F. <hi>and</hi> R. H. <hi>printed</hi> 1653. p. 101. <hi>It is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to read</hi> (viz. <hi>the Scriptures</hi>) <hi>which the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſpoke forth freely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Again, what abuſe this is in the Quotation, for here they leave out the very Intent of the matter, becauſe it touches themſelves, as Perſons Conſcious: 'Tis not ſaid in thoſe general words, that it is <hi>dangerous to read the Scriptures,</hi> &amp;c. but it is dangerous to read and to make a Trade of that, which the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles ſpake forth freely, and to give meanings to it contrary than it is. And further it is ſaid, <hi>You wreſt the Scriptures to your own Deſtruction</hi> (Pſal. 56.5.)</p>
                  <p>Theſe Men were willing to leave out what concerns their making a <hi>Trade</hi> of the Scriptures, or of that which the Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles, ſpake forth freely: 'Tis not ſaid to be <hi>dangerous</hi> to all Men to <hi>read the Scriptures,</hi> but to them that pervert them, and make a <hi>Trade</hi> of them: So 'tis dangerous for any to read them, for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful end, but not for any to read them for a good end: For, it is expreſly ſaid (in the ſame page quoted) <hi>Bleſſed is he that doth read, and doth underſtand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to what they object in the latter part of their Quotation, I anſwer that it is a great Evil to condemn either the Scriptures to the Fire, or any other Books given forth from the Eternal Spirit of God; the Evil in both is of the ſame kind, tho' the <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Fact</hi> may differ in degree. It was a great Evil, and wicked Act, in <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hoiakim,</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> to burn <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s <hi>Roll,</hi> or Book writ by <hi>Barack,</hi> Jer. 36. but it would be a greater Act of Wickedneſs, to <hi>burn</hi> all the <hi>Books</hi> of the <hi>Holy Prophets,</hi> or the <hi>whole Bible.</hi> There are <hi>Degrees</hi> of <hi>Robbery,</hi> but all of the ſame kind.</p>
                  <p n="22">22th <hi>Charge,</hi> p. 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Edw. Burroughs</hi> p. 47. <hi>of his Works, That is no Command from God to me, what he commands to another; neither did any of the Saints, which we read of in Scripture, act by the Command which was to another, not having the Command to themſelves.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here they leave out the next words, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">I challenge to find an Example for it, they were obliged every one by their own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: One was ſent to Baptiſm, and to preach the Goſpel, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ſent not to Baptiſe, but to Preach the Goſpel; all theſe left out: And then they go on with their Charge,</q> 
                     <hi>viz. And thou or any other, who go to Duty (as you call it) by Imitation from the Letter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out (which was a Command to others) in your Wills and Time, your Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58919:16"/>is not accepted, but is abomination to the Lord; for you go without the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Spirit in your own Wills and Strength, which God hates, and which his wrath is upon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> From what theſe Men have partially left out in their Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he intended <hi>Special Commands,</hi> or Commiſſions, as to <hi>Baptiſe,</hi> to <hi>Preach</hi> or <hi>to pray,</hi> &amp;c. which they that perform in their own Wills and Time, and go to Prayer, or other Acts of Worſhip or Devotion towards God, without the Moving and Aſſiſtance of his Spirit, 'tis but Will-worſhip, and they are not accepted therein, but rejected of the Lord; as <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their obſerving their Sacrifices, Oblations, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, New Moons, Sabbaths, and calling of Aſſemblies, and making many Prayers, were rejected of the Lord and teſtified againſt by his Prophet, tho' they imitated the Letter of the Law in theſe things, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>But there are Univerſal and Moral Commands of Juſtice and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and Prohibitions of the Contrary, which are univerſally bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Mankind; but chiefly from Inward Light and Conviction. And God has not left man without Light and Grace to oblige him therein, it being Conviction, that can Effectually only oblige to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>W. P.</hi> (who is alſo quoted in this Caſe againſt us, out of his <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queriſm a New Nickname,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1673. p. 71, 72.) is further explanatory and diſtinguiſhing in this point, as between <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Extraordinary</hi> Caſes: and I am perſuaded, theſe Adverſaries cannot anſwer him in Juſtification of their Charge againſt us. And therefore very partially quote him on the ſame Subject, after theſe words, [<hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">No Command in the Scripture is any further obliging upon any Man, than as he finds a conviction upon his Conſcience; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Men ſhould be engaged without, if not againſt Conviction; a thing unreaſonable in a Man.]</q> They leave out theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>viz.</hi> [<q rend="margQuotes">Therefore the Apoſtle, when he wrote to the Churches, exhorted them, not to do thoſe things, whereof they were aſhamed, and to ſhun, what was manifeſted to be evil; and affirms, <hi>That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever might be known of God, was manifeſted within, for God had ſhewn it unto them.]</hi>
                     </q> To which I further add, how can Man truly know, that there is an All-ſeeing God, who is Judge of all; and that he is to be loved, feared and worſhipped? And how can he truly believe the Holy Scriptures, and obey the Good Precepts thereof, without Inward Illumination and Conviction by the Holy Spirit, Light and Grace in his Heart?</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58919:16"/>
                  <p>Charge 23. p. 10, 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Shield of the Truth,</hi> by James Parnel, Printed 1655. p. 11. <hi>He that ſaith, the Letter is the Rule and Guide of the People of God, is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, feeding upon the Husk, and is ignorant of the true Light.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Edw. Burr.</hi> p. 515. tells us, <hi>That the Scriptures are not the Rule and Guide of Faith and Life unto the Saints, but the Spirit of God, that gave forth the Scriptures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Theſe two Inſtances are both brought to prove, that we <hi>ſlight</hi> or contemn the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which is very unjuſtly ſurmiſed. For if they had honeſtly obſerv'd, what both write upon the ſame Subject, they might have ſeen, there is no denial or <hi>ſlighting</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> As firſt, <hi>J. P.</hi> on the place quoted, confeſſeth, <q rend="margQuotes">that who are guided by the true Light, cannot walk contrary thereto, (<hi>i. e.</hi> to the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.).</hi> And Secondly, <hi>E. B.</hi> on the place quoted alſo confeſſeth, that the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are profitables, and were given forth to be read, and to be fulfulled; and that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which is the <hi>Rule</hi> of the Saints Faith and Life, leads them to walk in the fulfilling of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and according to them.</q> Which therefore cannot Import any Contempt of them, but the contrary. And their Preferring the <hi>Spirit</hi> to the <hi>Letter,</hi> and to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as the only or chief <hi>Rule</hi> of Faith and Life unto the Saints, as it was before the <hi>Scripture</hi> was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; this can be no undervaluing of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſeeing they teſtifie of Chriſt, the Way, the Truth and the Life; and of the <hi>Spirit</hi> as <hi>that</hi> which guides true Believers into all Truth; and even into a right Underſtanding and profitable Uſe of the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or Doctrine contain'd in them.</p>
                  <p>To that other Part of their Charge, relating to <hi>Difference,</hi> p. 11. As they make nothing of it againſt us, but only give us a Quotation, whether altogether true or not, is a Queſtion; So I ſee no advantage they can make of it againſt us, ſuppoſe it as it is, That <hi>if any Difference ariſe in the Church, or among them that profeſs themſelves Members thereof, the Church, with the Spirit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, hath power to determine the ſame, if any pretend to be of us; and in caſe of Controverſie, will nor admit to be tried by the Church of Chriſt Jeſus, nor ſubmit to the Judgment given by the Spirit of Truth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſuch to be rejected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what of all this? Is there either Blaſphemy or Sedition here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? How is this purſuant to the <hi>Prieſts Charge</hi> in their <hi>Title Page?</hi> Doth not our bleſſed Lord ſay concerning the offending Brother, if he ſhould <hi>neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee as an Heathen-man, and a Publican,</hi> Mat. 18.17. But firſt he preſcribes a due Order of Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure towards ſuch an <hi>Offender:</hi> Firſt privately, then before Witneſſes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58919:17"/>
                     <hi>verſ.</hi> 15, 16. And the Apoſtle ſeverely reprehends <hi>one Brother going to Law with another,</hi> and that before Unbelievers, ſaying, <hi>Do ye not know, that the Saints ſhall judge the World? and if then ye have judgments of things pertaining to this Life, ſet them to judge, who are leaſt eſteemed in the Church;</hi> See more at large, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1, to <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>As to the Story againſt <hi>Sam. Jennings</hi> about the proceeding againſt <hi>G. K.</hi> in <hi>Pennſilvania,</hi> I queſtion the Truth of it; however, if theſe Prieſts do eſteem <hi>G. K.</hi> ſuch an Eminent or Good Chriſtian, and not a <hi>Quaker,</hi> why do they not openly receive him into their <hi>Society,</hi> and Arms of their Church, and promote him, as well as privately Conſult with him, and Credit and Accept his Accuſations againſt us? It ſeems they are hard put to it for <hi>Aid</hi> in their Deſigns, that they muſt be beholden to ſuch as <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> and <hi>G. K.</hi> for their Help againſt the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who for many Years were own'd by them for God's Choſen and Peculiar People: And <hi>G. K.</hi> will never be able to obliterate all he has written in their behalf, with all his pretended Retractations.</p>
                  <p n="24">24th Charge, p. 12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand,</hi> p. 14. <hi>The Queſtion was put to</hi> G. F. <hi>Whether Chriſt in the Fleſh be a Figure, or not? and if a Figure, how, and in what? To which he Anſwers: Chriſt is the Subſtance of all Figures, and his Fleſh is a Figure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in <hi>Truth Defending the Quakers,</hi> by <hi>G. W.</hi> &amp;c. p. 20. <hi>It is ſaid expreſly, That Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh is but a Figure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> I deny, that it is <hi>ſo ſaid expreſly</hi> by <hi>G. W. That Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh is but a Figure;</hi> it is an expreſs Falſhood, as it ſeems to Charge me with the Words; for they are in the Prieſt's Queſtion, (Queſt. 35.) <hi>Did R. H. well in Writing, That Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh was</hi> BUT <hi>a Figure?</hi> Theſe were none of my Words, but the Prieſts. In my Anſwer, I have neither the Word <hi>[But]</hi> nor the Aſſertion. So I ask, haſt thou not read, <hi>That he was the expreſs Figure of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Subſtance?</hi> And I underſtood, that by the Word <hi>[Figure] R. H.</hi> and <hi>G. F.</hi> meant <hi>Example,</hi> that is, that they look'd on Chriſt, as in the Fleſh, as an <hi>Example,</hi> rendring <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Figure, Synonimous,</hi> and yet confeſs Chriſt to be the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of all Figures, Types and Shadows; as in <hi>Saul's Errand,</hi> p. 8, and 14. but do not ſay, that Chriſt in the Fleſh is <hi>but</hi> a <hi>Figure;</hi> neither did I ſo ſay or aſſert, as is falſly caſt upon me. But in my <hi>Antitode</hi> againſt the <hi>Snake in the Graſs,</hi> I fully explain this Point according to Scriptures, from p. 155, to 178. part whereof follows, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58919:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Type</hi> or <hi>Figure</hi> ſometimes points at a thing to come, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14. who was the, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Figure</hi> of him that was to come. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Type</hi> or <hi>Figure</hi> denotes a preſent <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Pattern,</hi> as in <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Mark them which walk ſo, as ye have us for</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Example.</hi> And the ſame word is uſed in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.9. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.7. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. only in different <hi>Caſes</hi> or <hi>Terminations;</hi> And alſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, an <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Type (John</hi> 13.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.23.) Thus <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Type</hi> are made <hi>Synonimous</hi> in <hi>T. C</hi>'s <hi>Lexicon,</hi> and the like in <hi>Crit. Sacr.</hi> but more fully explained. For there <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, i. e. <hi>Exemplum, Exemplar, triplicem habet in Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſignificatum.</hi> (1.) <hi>Significat</hi> Typum <hi>ſeu figuram rerum vel praeteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum,</hi> Heb. 8.5. <hi>vel futurarum,</hi> Heb. 9.23. (2.) <hi>Exemplum Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis,</hi> John 13.15. 1 Tim. 4.12. Tit. 4.7. (3.) <hi>Exemplum Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis ſive Cautelae,</hi> ut 2 Pet. 2.6. That is to ſay: <hi>Exemplum</hi> or <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar</hi> hath a threefold ſignification in Scripture. (1.) It ſignifies a <hi>Type</hi> or <hi>Figure</hi> of things, either <hi>paſt,</hi> or to <hi>come.</hi> (2.) An <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</hi> of <hi>Imitation.</hi> (3.) An <hi>Example</hi> of <hi>Warning</hi> or Caution. Now ſee, how <hi>Synonimouſly</hi> the Terms, <hi>Type, Figure, Pattern</hi> and <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> are rendred in Scripture; and of what extent, not only in relation to the <hi>Types</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> but in ſome reſpect to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Miniſters, tho' he be alſo confeſſed to be the <hi>Antitype,</hi> Subſtance and End of all Legal Shadows, Types and Figures. But I have not called <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf a <hi>Type</hi> of our <hi>Light</hi> within, nor ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified the ſame. Thus far <hi>Antidote,</hi> p. 176, 177.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="25">25th Charge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>G. F.</hi> Great Myſtery, p. 206. <hi>The Apoſtles preached Chriſt that was crucified within, and not another, him that was raiſed up from the Dead, was riſen, that Lord Jeſus Chriſt within.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> Not to inſiſt on their following broken and lame Quotations, with their nonſenſical <hi>Daſhes;</hi> here they ſillily carp at the manner of theſe Expreſſions, they wanting due points, as, <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>The Apoſtles preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt</hi> (that's crucified) <hi>within,</hi> and not another; there wanted this <hi>Parentheſis.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">For 'tis plainly expreſt before, <hi>viz. If Chriſt, that is, crucified, be not within, and Chriſt, that's Riſen, be not within, I ſay, that you are all Reprobates</hi> (Great Myſtery, <hi>Ibid.</hi>) And he that hath not this Chriſt (that was riſen and crucified) within, is a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate <hi>(Ibid.)</hi> here wanted the <hi>Parentheſis</hi> again, tho' explained in the foregoing words, <hi>viz.</hi> If Chriſt that was crucified, be not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis certain there is but one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. who came both in the Fleſh and in the Spirit.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58919:18"/>
                  <p>What they Charge, <hi>News coming up,</hi> &amp;c. p. 14. <hi>Your Baptiſm is Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> here they leave out <hi>[Sprinkling Infants, which God never command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed] and their Sacrament (as they call it) is carnal,</hi> and here again they leave out <hi>[and there is not a word in the Scripture that ſpeaks of a Sacrament] and their Communion is Carnal, a little Bread and Wine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>whereupon I propoſe to theſe our ſevere Judges, that if theſe <hi>Expreſſions</hi> be offenſive to them, and they deem them Erroneous, we muſt take them to be of a contrary Opinion, namely, that their <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> to wit, <hi>Sprinkling Infants,</hi> is not Carnal, but <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and commanded of God, and that their <hi>Sacrament, Communion, Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> is not Carnal but <hi>Spiritual:</hi> But how can that be without <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> pray? (A Doctrine wholly diſown'd by us) which if they prove all this by Scripture, and the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> alſo, then all that hold they are Carnal, and not Spiritual, ought to retract and confeſs their Error: I'll not exclude my ſelf on theſe Terms.</p>
                  <p>But I wiſh theſe Men would not be too hot and fierce about <hi>words,</hi> I would not have them take the word <hi>Carnal,</hi> as a word of <hi>Contempt</hi> againſt any thing that God ever commanded; for they may read of <hi>Carnal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> ſpoken of things which God once commanded, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.9. which ſtood only in <hi>Meats</hi> and <hi>Drinks,</hi> and [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>variis Baptiſmatibus] divers Baptiſms,</hi> and <hi>
                        <hi>Carnal Ordinances</hi> impos'd on them, until the time of Reformation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>W. Smith's Primer</hi> is charged, that <hi>Baptiſm, Bread and Wine, aroſe from the Pope's Invention,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I having found <hi>W. S.</hi> in like manner wronged in this heretofore, by ſome called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> upon ſearch I gave them this Anſwer from his own Explication, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">That it was not <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> nor <hi>Baptiſm</hi> without diſtinction, that he rendred the <hi>Pope's Invention,</hi> but ſprinkling Water in a Child's Face, ſigning it with the <hi>Sign</hi> of the <hi>Croſs</hi> on it's Fore-head, God-fathers and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers to undertake for it; <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> ſo uſed and received (<hi>i. e.</hi> by a ſort of Prieſts and People) as the Body and Blood of Chriſt, which they tell them, is broken and ſhed for them (which implies <hi>Tranſubſtantiation)</hi> and did not theſe, thus conſidered, riſe from the <hi>Pope's Invention,</hi> trow ye? See the <hi>Contemned Quaker, and his Chriſtian Religion defended,</hi> p. 23, 24.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>To their Charge againſt <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Reaſon againſt Railing,</hi> printed 1673. p. 108, 109. his ſaying, <hi>I affirm by that one Scripture</hi> (Heb. 9.10.) <hi>that Circumciſion is as much in force as Water-Baptiſm, and the Paſchal Lamb, as Bread and Wine, they were both Shadows, and both Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58919:18"/>and Periſhable</hi> [And here they leave out divers explanatory Lines.]</p>
                  <p>Whereupon I ask theſe Men,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> if the <hi>Paſchal Lamb</hi> (which was a principal part of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> Luke 22.) be in force among Chriſtians?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Second,</hi> If <hi>Water Baptiſm, Bread and Wine,</hi> be not Shadows, and Elementary, and Periſhable? If it be an Offence to ſay, <hi>they are,</hi> then I would ask theſe Men, if they believe their <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> are not Periſhable, Elementary, and of a decaying Nature? If not, how will they clear themſelves of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation!</hi> But I would charitably think better of them, than their Charges in theſe matters Import.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe charged with <hi>Cain</hi>'s <hi>Sacrifice in their Ordinances, Churches and Teachings</hi> (for which <hi>News coming up,</hi> is again quoted againſt us, p. 4.14.) were ſuch as were in the Firſt Birth, and Envious Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, and Wicked Perſons, as were juſtly reprehended in thoſe days, when that was writ, in 1654. even as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied againſt <hi>Iſrael, Iſa.</hi> 1. becauſe of their Iniquities, tho' they obſerv'd Outward Ordinances.</p>
                  <p>What they quote about one <hi>Quaker</hi> writing to another, in a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaning Letter, called, <hi>The Spirit of the Hat,</hi> printed 1673. p. 12. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of <hi>G. Fox, not allowing any Liberty,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>That's not true, nor the compariſon juſt, between <hi>G. F.</hi> and the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for he was always againſt Perſecution and Coertion by <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> for matters purely relating to Conſcience, or Worſhip toward God, and for all to have their Liberty to Worſhip him, as inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſuaded, which <hi>Popery</hi> will not allow: And for <hi>G. F</hi>'s ſaying, <hi>No Liberty out of the Power,</hi> and aſſerting <hi>Goſpel-Liberty,</hi> this we knew related to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> there being no true <hi>Liberty,</hi> but in the Power and Spirit of the Lord; and the Church deſires no other than what's agreable to Truth.</p>
                  <p>And <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Brief Examination, and State of Liberty Spiritual,</hi> Printed 1681. (which is alſo quoted againſt us) Imports no other than a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> in <hi>Truth,</hi> and for Unity, Society, and good Order therein, and againſt the Spirit of Strife, Diviſion, and Self-Separation, which would cloak it ſelf under Pretence of claiming <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and being left to the Grace and Spirit of God within, when its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is to be at <hi>Liberty,</hi> both to break good Order and Unity, and to lead into Looſneſs, fleſhly and corrupt Liberty. It follows not, that we allow no <hi>Liberty</hi> to any, who differ from us (as is falſly noted in their Margent againſt us) for the <hi>Liberty</hi> God allows to all Mankind in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58919:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58919:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58919:20"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58919:20"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58919:21"/>Creation, we would debar none of; though we cannot receive them into Society with us, who walk not after the Spirit, but after the Fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of GOVERNMENT.</head>
                  <p n="26">26th Charge, p. 15.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Margent</hi> it's noted, <hi>They declare themſelves againſt Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> for which they quote <hi>Edw. Burrough</hi>'s Works, p. 244. <hi>The Lord is riſen to overturn, to overturn Kings and Princes, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Laws— And He will change Times, and Laws, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Now obſerve, That theſe Prophetical Paſſages (with many other of the like Import) were writ in the Year 1657. and have they not been in a great Meaſure fulfilled, by the various Overturnings and Revolutions, which ſince have come to paſs? Can any deny a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo apparent? But does this argue that we are againſt a Kingly Government, when God will have it? No ſure. As there was Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Him in Prophecying ſuch Truths, ſo there hath been, and is on our parts, in what He brings to paſs, concerning Revolutions and Governments; and it muſt be known and acknowledged, <hi>That the Moſt High rules in the Kingdoms of Men, and giveth them to whomſoever he pleaſeth,</hi> Dan. 4.17, 25. 'Tis alſo obſervable, that theſe our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers, who render us <hi>Seditious,</hi> have very Partially left out the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the afore recited Prophecies; as <q rend="margQuotes">O what cruel Injuſtice and Tyranny in Civil Governments! O what abominable Superſtitions and Idolatries have been in ſuppoſed Church-Governments! It's a Vexation to the Spirit of the Lord to conſider it; and the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soul hath long cried and mourned under it: And becauſe of this is the Lord of Heaven and Earth now riſen to overturn, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And after the Words quoted, theſe are left out, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">And he will confound and break down all Tyranny and Oppreſſion under which the Poor have groaned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now obſerve, how Univerſal and Impartial theſe Prophecies were, being directed in general, under the Title of a <hi>Standard lifted up, and an Enſign held forth unto all Nations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now ſuppoſe any one ſhould be ſtirr'd up to Prophecy againſt any King or Prince, in any Nation, where great Perſecution and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is upheld or maintain'd, whether in <hi>France,</hi> or in any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Popiſh Countries, were it a good Inference to ſay, <hi>It were a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58919:21"/>Declaration againſt Kingly Government in general?</hi> No ſure: And what Prophecies are for <hi>Chriſt's Kingdom, or the Government of the Lamb?</hi> This we muſt own, and that He ſhall Rule the Nations, and He ſhall Rule in the <hi>midſt of his Enemies,</hi> and that the Kingdoms of this World ſhall become the Kingdoms of God, and of His Chriſt. Theſe, and ſuch like, the Holy Scriptures do expreſly warrant and teſtifie.</p>
                  <p>And to <hi>G. F</hi>'s ſaying, <hi>That the Quakers are in the Power of God, and in the Authority of the Lamb, above all Houſes, and into Houſes creep not, but are upon the Throne.</hi> Gr. Myſt. p. 31. He meant <hi>Spiritually,</hi> no doubt, and not <hi>Literally,</hi> for they are not upon an outward Throne. They that ſuffer with Chriſt, ſhall Reign with Him, as Kings and Prieſts upon Earth, though their Kingdom be not of this World. And it is teſtified, That HE <hi>(God) with-draweth not his Eyes from the Righteous, but with Kings are they on the Throne; yea, He doth eſtabliſh them for ever, and they are exalted,</hi> Job 36.7.</p>
                  <p>Again, theſe Adverſaries charge <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>G. F. Junior,</hi> out of <hi>Truth Defending the Quakers,</hi> Printed 1659. p. 9, 10. with Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That the Magiſtrate, that is ſent of God, he receives the Law from the Mouth of God; and he is the Prophet whom Moſes ſpoke of,</hi> Deut. 18.18.</p>
                  <p>We are very wrongfully quoted in this place, for our Words are, <hi>The Magiſtrate that is ſent of God, and is his Miniſter, he receives the Law at the Mouth of God, and hears the Prophet, whom Moſes ſaid, the People ſhould hear in all things,</hi> Deut. 18.18. Acts 3.22. And what <hi>Sedition</hi> are in theſe Words, <hi>Pray,</hi> or <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> either? ſeeing <hi>He that Rules over Men, muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3. And Divine <hi>Wiſdom</hi> (which is confeſt to be the Eternal Son of God) ſaith, <hi>By me Kings reign, and Princes decree Juſtice,</hi> Prov. 8. Muſt they not then receive <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> from Him, who is the Wiſdom and Power of God? And if his People muſt hear him in <hi>All</hi> things, how ſhall Matters of Juſt Government be excepted?</p>
                  <p>As to what theſe Men quote againſt us, in their ſixteenth Page, to prove us, the aforeſaid People, <hi>Anti-Monarchical,</hi> they are very bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in their Quotations, with their many ſenſeleſs Daſhes: like the <hi>Snake in the Graſs,</hi> Second Edition, p. 220. but varying in the Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame Paſſage. Theſe Men have the Words, <hi>[Are not all theſe Elders that will dote ſo much of an Earthly King.]</hi> But the <hi>Snake</hi> has it <hi>[Are not all theſe Chriſtians that will dote ſo much,</hi> &amp;c. And both leaving out what may more plainly import the Intent of the Author.</p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58919:22"/>
                  <p>And yet by what's ſo abruptly quoted, his meaning may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. As ſome then <hi>doting ſo much on an Earthly King to rule over them,</hi> as Chriſtians he meant no other, but ſuch <hi>Earthly Kings,</hi> as were perſecuting <hi>Kings,</hi> as he mentions <hi>Herod,</hi> the <hi>King, who was mad at the Child Jeſus;</hi> ſuch <hi>Earthly Kings</hi> as would rule over Men's Conſciences; ſuch as the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> ſet up, and ſuch corrupt and wicked Kings as the Holy Prophets propheſied againſt, as <hi>David, Iſaiah, Ezekiel,</hi> and others did; ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.40. <hi>Job.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.3, 6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.9. It's ſaid in Iſaiah 24.21. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day, that the Lord ſhall puniſh the Hoſt of the high Ones, and the Kings of the Earth upon the Earth,</hi> ſee alſo verſ. 22. and Iſai. 30.33. <hi>Tophet is ordained of old, yea for the King it is prepared,</hi> &amp;c. Yet theſe Prophets were for Good Kings and Righteous Government; and ſuch Kings were foretold of, who ſhould be <hi>nurſing-Fathers, and Queens nurſing-Mothers,</hi> Iſai. 49.23. therefore theſe were not <hi>Anti-monarchical</hi> without exception. And I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded <hi>G. F.</hi> never intended to reflect upon any good <hi>Kings,</hi> or ſuch as were againſt Perſecution and Oppreſſion, but againſt ſuch as he compares to <hi>Herod,</hi> who was <hi>mad at the Child Jeſus.</hi> And we have known him ſpeak well, and give good commendation of our preſent King, with reſpect to his Moderation and Tenderneſs, and the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience in Religious Worſhip owned and granted by him.</p>
                  <p>When Chriſt told his Diſciples, <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe Lordſhip over them, but it ſhall not be ſo among you,</hi> Matt. 20.25, 26. was he therefore an Enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as he was accuſed? No ſure, he did not thereby preach <hi>Sedition</hi> againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or the Kings of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> nor diſſuade the Chriſtians from their due ſubjection unto them.</p>
                  <p>We may further obſerve, that thoſe Kings of the Earth, and thoſe Great and Mighty Men, and Chief Captains, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred the wrath of God, and of the Lamb, ſo as to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Dens and in the Rocks of the Mountains, and to call to the Mountains and Rocks to fall on them, and hide them from the face of <hi>him</hi> that ſitteth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lamb. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.15. Theſe, no doubt, were wicked Kings, who were concern'd in this Propheſie. But there's another Propheſie which beſpeaks a Great Reformation among the Nations: And the Kings of the Earth, when the Nations of them that are ſaved, ſhall walk in the Light of the Holy City of God, and the Kings of the Earth bring their Glory and Honour into it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24, 26. Therefore all Kings are not condemnable, as the wicked are.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58919:22"/>
                  <p>We have been accuſed to be <hi>one while againſt,</hi> another while <hi>for Kingly Government,</hi> particularly in a Scandalous Libel, ſtiled, <hi>A Letter to the Quakers,</hi> and alſo in the <hi>Snake in the Graſs;</hi> to which the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Anſwer was given, which may now ſerve for a General Anſwer to theſe Adverſaries, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">The firſt part of the <hi>Charge</hi> is <hi>falſe,</hi> as 'tis charged on us. For tho' it's true, that ſome were rather in their judgments for a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi> duly qualified for the <hi>Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> than ſuch a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> that might (as they ſuppoſed) be <hi>oppreſſive</hi> and <hi>perſecuting</hi> for Conſcience; yet not againſt ſuch a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> as is juſtly qualified for the <hi>Good</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> under which they might enjoy their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties,</hi> as Men and Chriſtians; ſuch <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth</hi> being not inconſiſtent, as to the good Ends of Government, i. e. <hi>Salus Populi</hi> in true <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property:</hi> (And it's evident, the Common-wealth (or Weal of <hi>England</hi>) is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with, and allowed by <hi>Monarchy.</hi>) But many honeſt Men were in their judgments rather for ſuch a <hi>Common-wealth-Government,</hi> than an <hi>Oppreſſive, Perſecuting Monarchy.</hi> And what then? Did they ſin againſt <hi>God</hi> therein? No: Did they offend againſt <hi>Man,</hi> or any <hi>Humane Laws</hi> thereby? They are pardoned by divers <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Indemnity,</hi> which thoſe <hi>Libellizing Informers</hi> manifeſtly violate, by upbraiding them <hi>now</hi> in ſuch <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Government:</hi> Pray, let this be obſerved. And to obviate further <hi>Objections</hi> of <hi>Prejudice</hi> in this Caſe; ſet Caſe, ſome of our Friends in <hi>former days</hi> expreſſed their Reſpect to a <hi>Republick,</hi> rather than a <hi>Monarchy then,</hi> when they feared, it would prove more <hi>burthenſome;</hi> and yet, as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> quietly ſubmit to, and acknowledged <hi>Monarchy</hi> to be ſet up by the <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Providence</hi> of God, when the time came, were they <hi>Hypocritical Temporizers</hi> therein? No ſuch matter: They might be conſciencious in <hi>both.</hi> As <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet was in the Caſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was diſpleaſed at the <hi>Peoples</hi> deſiring a <hi>King,</hi> and foretold the manner of one, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. And yet when God gave them one, he own'd him as the Lord's Annointed, and choſen, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. This is apt to our Purpoſe, ſo far as it is Applicable. Who dare ſay, the Prophet was a <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> or a <hi>Temporizer</hi> in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Our Conſtancy and Confidence we place not in <hi>Perſons,</hi> but the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the thing that is juſt, as to <hi>Governments;</hi> Perſons are mututable, but <hi>Truth</hi> is not: <hi>Good Kings</hi> and <hi>Governments</hi> we never oppoſed. And tho' we like not bad ones, we have always been true and conſtant to the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Obedience:</hi> And our Patient and Deep Sufferings by <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments</hi>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58919:23"/>and <hi>Spoil,</hi> &amp;c. under the various Revolutions of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> till of late have ſufficiently cleared us from the Infamous Charge of <hi>Hypocritical Temporizers,</hi> &amp;c. moſt unjuſtly and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly caſt upon us. Thus far the ſaid Anſwer.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis farther obſervable, that theſe Men's notifying the <hi>Quakers</hi> in their Margents, as againſt <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> againſt the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Lords,</hi> againſt the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> againſt <hi>Judges, Juſtices</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables,</hi> againſt <hi>Lawyers</hi> and againſt <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Mannors</hi> (as in their p. 15, to p. 20.) They ſhould rather have added, and againſt <hi>Covetous Perſecuting Prieſts;</hi> but this they have omitted in their Margent, as they have left out many other things in their <hi>Citations,</hi> which touch themſelves to the quick.</p>
                  <p>And if the whole Tenure and Intent of thoſe Writings, lamely and partially quoted by them, were ſeriouſly read and duly conſidered, it would appear, that it was the <hi>Corruption</hi> of thoſe <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Offices</hi> that was ſtruck at, rather than the <hi>Places</hi> themſelves, conſidered in their firſt Inſtitution. Who can ſay, that there was never <hi>Monarchy,</hi> nor <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peers,</hi> nor <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> nor <hi>Judges, Juſtices</hi> or <hi>Lawyers Corrupted?</hi> Whoſe <hi>Corruptions</hi> formerly occaſioned a Zeal to ariſe in ſome to reprehend and teſtifie againſt them.</p>
                  <p>What they quoted againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> in p. 17. <hi>To the Parliament of the Common-wealth of</hi> England for ſelling <hi>Abby-Lands</hi> and <hi>Glebe-Lands gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Prieſts, that they might be given to the Poor,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and above</hi> 7000. <hi>Quakers declaring againſt the Miniſtry, that take Tythes;</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this moſt touches and offends ſome <hi>Prieſts</hi> concerned; 'tis terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to them to think ſuch a conſiderable People ſhould be ſo averſe to their <hi>Self-Intereſt,</hi> their making ſuch <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Gain</hi> of <hi>Preaching.</hi> This, (I warrant you) comes more near them, than Adviſing to ſell <hi>Whte-Hall,</hi> &amp;c. for <hi>Alms-Houſes,</hi> for all <hi>the Blind and Lame to be there,</hi> &amp;c. (as they quote the words) which was in the <hi>Common-Wealth's</hi> days. It ſeems <hi>G. F.</hi> was more for the Charitable Uſe of ſuch <hi>Places</hi> in thoſe days, than for the Proud and Voluptuous to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt themſelves, and make their Neſts in them.</p>
                  <p>As to what they quote againſt <hi>G. Fox,</hi> Jun. out of his Works, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed 1665. (p. 87, 88.) I need not inſiſt upon it, it being occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally firſt writ in the time of the <hi>Common Wealth</hi>'s <hi>Government,</hi> and related to <hi>Parliaments,</hi> then choſen by the Voices of the People, that is, ſuch People, as did not truly deſire the good of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>People</hi> (as he ſaith) and ſuch as were <hi>Covetous, oppreſſing Men, who oppreſſed the Poor</hi> (where <hi>vox Populi,</hi> was not <hi>vox Dei</hi>) he writes againſt their having the <hi>only Power</hi> to chuſe <hi>Law-makers;</hi> and alſo againſt the great <hi>Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:58919:23"/>and unwarrantable means uſed for the <hi>Choice</hi> of <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in thoſe days; and which in theſe days often wants Reforming in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, as the <hi>Votes</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> have frequently ſhewn. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>G. F.</hi> Jun. had an honeſt intent in what he writ on this ſubject; which impartially read altogether, looks a great deal better, and far more Innocent, than theſe Carpers and Pickers make of it, by their picking out here and there Pieces and Patches, and leaving out what is moſt plain and explanatory of the intent of the whole, and that juſtly touches and affects themſelves: As where (under the ſame Head) <hi>G. F.</hi> ſaith,</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">It hath been the <hi>Complaint</hi> of the <hi>Sobereſt</hi> and <hi>Honeſteſt Men</hi> in ſeveral Counties, when they ſhould have choſen <hi>Parliament-Men,</hi> that they could not <hi>Chuſe</hi> ſuch a Man, as, <hi>they judged,</hi> would act <hi>ſingly</hi> for the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Country;</hi> becauſe they were <hi>over-voted</hi> by the <hi>Wild, Diſaffected, People,</hi> who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times have been ſtirred up by their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> to <hi>vote</hi> for <hi>ſuch a Man,</hi> as the <hi>Prieſts</hi> knew would <hi>act</hi> for their <hi>Covetous, oppreſſing Self-intereſt.</hi> And in ſome places ſome <hi>Great, Proud Men,</hi> who deſired to be in <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> have <hi>Feaſted</hi> the People, and ſent <hi>Gifts</hi> to them with <hi>Flatteries,</hi> thereby ſtriving to get the People to <hi>vote</hi> for them, promiſing them to <hi>ſtand for their Liberties,</hi> when it hath been but to ſerve their own <hi>Self-ends.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>G. F.</hi> further ſaith, <q rend="margQuotes">Seeing the <hi>great Oppreſſors</hi> of the Land (viz.) <hi>Preiſts</hi> and <hi>Lawyers,</hi> and the great <hi>Wicked, Covetous, Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Men,</hi> are ſo much concerned in the chuſing them; ſo that if <hi>Parliaments</hi> ſo <hi>choſen</hi> ſhould continue, the <hi>People</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> are not like to be <hi>ſet free</hi> from their <hi>Oppreſſion</hi> (tho' <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> have been made to do many good things by a Power which many of them ſcarce knew.)</q> I dare Appeal to any Judicious obſerving Perſons, whether the like <hi>Corruptions</hi> are not too frequently uſed in this <hi>Nation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now pray obſerve, that I do not in the leaſt deſign to oppoſe the Peoples fair and lawful Elections, according to the true and juſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Conſtitution of Parliaments.</p>
                  <p>Again, they Charge <hi>E. Burroughs</hi> in his Works, p. 522. <hi>A running to the Powers of the Earth. What have you Miniſters loſt the Lord to be your Strength, that you muſt flee for help to Men? Muſt they make Laws to eſtabliſh you, and ſet you up? Is not this the Whore that Rode upon the Beaſt,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> After the words, <hi>Flee for help to Men,</hi> they leave out, <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you from the Spirit of God in his People:</hi> And alſo divers following
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58919:24"/>Paſſages, which touch their own Spirits, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Is he (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Prieſt) crying to you to Perſecute the Innocent? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And would he have ſome <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot</hi> again in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> and ſome Perſecution and Baniſhment acted upon the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God?</hi>
                     </q> Thus <hi>E. B.</hi> which was in the Year 1659.</p>
                  <p>Again, theſe Men proceed in their Charge againſt <hi>E. B.</hi> p. 524. <hi>viz.</hi> (To the <hi>then Parliament) you do but cauſe People to Drink of the Whore's Cup, and you are but them</hi> (i. e. the <hi>Beaſt) which carry the Whore, to wit, the Falſe Church: And this is plain dealing to tell you the Truth,</hi> p. 18.</p>
                  <p>Pray obſerve again here, they have left out both the fore-going and following Paſſages, which ſhew the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of theſe Expreſſions, where he ſaith, <q rend="margQuotes">If theſe Prieſts have not yet planted <hi>Vineyards,</hi> that will yield them <hi>Fruit,</hi> and if their <hi>Flock</hi> will not yield them <hi>Milk</hi> freely, why ſhould you unjuſtly impoſe upon Peoples Conſciences, and compel <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Mony</hi> from them for the <hi>Maintenance</hi> of theſe Men? Ye ought not to do it: For while ye Compel and Force Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by Violence, contrary to good Conſciences, to maintain and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> (then follows) <hi>you do but cauſe People to Drink the Whore's Cup,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And after the words <hi>[Plain Dealing to tell you the Truth]</hi> there follows in <hi>E. B</hi>'s <hi>(Ibid.) viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">whether ye will reject it, or receive it. Wherefore caſt them off, and let them not lurk under your Wings, for one day they will <hi>Rebel</hi> againſt you, and another day <hi>Flatter</hi> with you; and for a ſeaſon they will ſhew forth much Love and Kindneſs in <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> even while they are hatching <hi>Miſchief</hi> againſt you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And they will cry out <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Error</hi> of others, that themſelves may ſeem <hi>Clear,</hi> while as the ſame lodgeth in their own Hearts.</q> Thus <hi>E. B.</hi> in 1659.</p>
                  <p>By all which 'tis evident he ſtruck at <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and thoſe who then upheld the Prieſts in thoſe days (by <hi>Perſecution</hi> and <hi>forced Maintenance</hi>) it was thoſe who turn'd out the Epiſcopal Prieſts; and what need any of theſe now <hi>Prieſts</hi> be offended thereat, if they were Clear?</p>
                  <p>'Tis ſtrange theſe Men ſhould now quote <hi>Propheſies,</hi> as matters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, the ſaid People, which have been manifeſtly fulfilled, and openly brought to paſs in a great meaſure, in the Eyes of this, and other Nations.</p>
                  <p>As again they quote <hi>News coming out of the</hi> North, which was Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Year, 1655. p. 18. The paſſage which they quote, is under that <hi>Head,</hi> which is directed <hi>To the Heads of this Nation, and all the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58919:24"/>Dominions of the Earth, and to all who are under the Dominion of the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Powers, Nations and Kingdoms, every where in all the World. To all you Kings, Princes, Dukes, Rulers, Judges, Juſtices,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Now obſerve the general extent of this Direction, and what theſe Men partially quote, and pick out, and patch together, to render us Seditious and Obnoxious. The Words quoted againſt us are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Dreadful is the Lord, and Powerful, who is coming in his <hi>Power,</hi> to execute true Judgment upon all you <hi>Judges,</hi> and to change all your <hi>Laws,</hi> ye <hi>Kings;</hi> and all you Rulers muſt down and ceaſe.—And all you <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderling-Officers,</hi> which have been as the Arms of this great Tree, which the Fowls have lodged under — all your Branches muſt be cut down; for you have been all the Fruitleſs Branches grown on the Fruitleſs Tree. Page 20. Sing all ye Saints, and Rejoice, clap your Hands, and be glad, for the Lord Jehovah will Reign, and the Government ſhall be taken from you, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Rulers, Judges</hi> and <hi>Juſtices, Lawyers</hi> and <hi>Conſtables;</hi> all this Tree muſt be cut down, and Jeſus Chriſt (<hi>in us</hi> added) will rule alone, with more words quoted backward and forward, p. 19.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now obſerve, theſe (though many illuſtrating Paſſages be left out) being writ in the Year 1655. we may appeal to the whole Nation, whether that TREE of the <hi>then Government</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> with the Branches thereof, hath not been <hi>cut down,</hi> and removed, and whether God's over-ruling Power and Providence, was not concerned therein, and in the various <hi>Revolutions</hi> ſince? And the reſt that concerns other <hi>Dominions, Earthly Powers, Nations,</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> with the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> thereof, who dare determine, that ſuch <hi>Propheſies,</hi> as concern them, may not come to paſs, and be further fulfilled? And alſo what theſe Men have left out in their ſaid Quotation, after the Words, <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>[To change all your Laws ye Kings]</hi> The Lord alone he will place the Law in People's Hearts, who is the Everlaſting Law-giver, and Juſtice the Lord will ſet in People's Hearts.</q> And after the words [Jeſus Chriſt will rule alone] follow theſe, <q rend="margQuotes">Glory and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for ever be unto him. Be warned all betimes, and awake, and repent, and turn to the Lord betimes, that ye may find Mercy by putting off the evil Deeds and Works of Darkneſs, that you may be received into the Kingdom of Glory, and lay aſide all Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, Pride and Covetouſneſs, (and ſpedily repent) Uncleanneſs and curſed Speaking. Lying, Slandering and Swearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which is according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. and alſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.4, 5. and ch. 4.31. and <hi>James</hi> 1.21.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:58919:25"/>
                  <p>They further Charge <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> p. 501. for ſaying, <q rend="margQuotes">We ſtand Witneſſes againſt <hi>Parliaments, Councils, Judges, Juſtices,</hi> who make or execute Laws in their <hi>own Will,</hi> over the Conſciences of Men, or puniſh for Conſcience ſake; and to ſuch we cannot yield our Obedience.</q> [And here they corruptly add an &amp;c.] printed in 1659.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> here, Where is the <hi>Offence</hi> in theſe words? Would theſe Men have the Conſciences of Chriſtians ſubject to obey all Laws made in the Wills of Superiors, (and that over Conſcience too?) We though they had allowed this approved Exception, <hi>i. e. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs Laws are made contrary to the Law of God?</hi> They ſhould have been ſo juſt, as to have taken notice of what <hi>E. B.</hi> ſaith in his next following Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph, (p. 501.) with reſpect to <hi>Chriſt</hi> and to <hi>Magiſtracy, viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">That as we Preach Chriſt Jeſus alone, in the things of God, to be our <hi>Law-giver,</hi> ſo we do own him to be our <hi>King;</hi> and own <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> in <hi>Civil Things,</hi> not reſiſting any, but following his Example, who was made perfect through Suffering, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to what they Charge <hi>G. F. To the Parliament of the Common Wealth of</hi> England, p. 5. reflecting on their <hi>Coif-men</hi> and ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Lawyers</hi> about their Fees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If any <hi>Lawyers</hi> now be offended thereat, we leave them to plead their own Cauſe, if they can; and <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> to be kind to their Tenants, and Charitable and Generous to the Poor, as all Rich Men eſpecially ought to be: And let none of the <hi>Lawyers</hi> (when warned againſt Covetouſneſs) reflect, as one of the <hi>Lawyers</hi> did againſt Chriſt, <hi>Maſter, thus ſaying, thou Reproacheſt us alſo,</hi> Luke 11.45. but read Chriſt's anſwer, <hi>verſ.</hi> 46.</p>
                  <p>It may be obſerved by all ſerious <hi>Readers,</hi> how apt theſe our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries are to <hi>pervert</hi> and make an ill uſe of matters well intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and innocently deſigned according to our <hi>Chriſtian Principle,</hi> as,</p>
                  <p>Upon a <hi>Declaration from the People of God</hi> (called Quakers) <hi>againſt all Plotters and Fighters,</hi> &amp;c. preſented to K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. 1660. they have made this perverſe note againſt us in their Margent (p. 20.) <hi>viz. Which Government that they might not ſupport, they declare againſt the uſe of the Carnal Weapon, in</hi> 1660.</p>
                  <p>Which is a falſe Conſtruction and Perverſion of the ſaid <hi>Declaration,</hi> for it was not written with any ſuch intent; witneſs our Contribut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Proportions and full Shares towards the ſupport of the <hi>Civil Government,</hi> both in <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms.</hi> So much of the <hi>Declaration,</hi> as they have quoted, follows, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">All Bloody Principles and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we, as to our own Particulars, do utterly deny, with all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58919:25"/>
                        <hi>Wars,</hi> and <hi>Strife,</hi> and <hi>Fightings,</hi> with outward Weapons for any end, or under any pretence whatſoever: And this is our Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to the whole World. And we do certainly know, and ſo teſtifie to the World, that the Spirit of Chriſt, which leads us into all Truth, will never move us to Fight and War againſt any Man with outward Weapons, either for the Kingdom of Chriſt, nor for the Kingdom of this World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſaid to be ſubſcribed by <hi>G. F. Sam. Fiſher,</hi> and many more.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now let it be farther obſerved, that notwithſtanding this Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and Chriſtian Declaration againſt <hi>our</hi> uſe of the Carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon; theſe Adverſaries make another Marginal <hi>Note</hi> to the contrary, upon <hi>Sam. Fiſher</hi>'s <hi>Meſſage from the Lord to</hi> O. Cromwel <hi>and the</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>of</hi> England, printed 1656. and in his works, Re-printed 1679. p. 19, 20. after the note <hi>againſt the uſe of the Carnal Weapon,</hi> their other note is <hi>[Although none before ſo much for it as they.]</hi> Their proof is <hi>S. F</hi>'s ſaid <hi>Meſſage,</hi> which they have thereby greatly pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to render us <hi>Seditious and Dangerous</hi> to the Government, as their Title imports: Whereas, <hi>S. F.</hi> writ the ſaid Meſſage, in the name of the Lord, agreeable to what God's Holy Prophets have formerly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told: He ſaith,</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>I will hold my Peace now no longer, ſaith the Lord, as concerning this Evil, which they ſo profanely commit, and do daily againſt my Choſen,</hi> (i. e. by Perſecution) <hi>but will utterly ſubvert and overturn them;</hi>
                     </q> [This is according to <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.25, 26, 27.] <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>and bring the Kingdoms and Dominions, and the Greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>into the hands of the Holy Ones of the moſt High</hi> [This is accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18, 27.] <q rend="margQuotes">And give unto my Son and his Saints to reign over all the Earth, and to take all the Rule, and Authority, and Power,</q> that ſhall ſtand up againſt my <hi>Son</hi> in his <hi>Saints:</hi> [This alſo is according to <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 5. and to <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18, 27. and to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8, 9. and 45.5. and 110.1, 2, 5.] <q rend="margQuotes">And I will put my high praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es into their Mouth, and a two-edged Sword into their hands, and they ſhall Execute Vengeance upon the Heathen, and Puniſhments upon the People, and ſhall bind their Kings in Chains, and their <hi>Nobles in Fetters of Iron,</hi> and Execute upon them the Judgment that is written, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus far <hi>S. F</hi>'s Meſſage recited, agreeable to plain Scripture, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. pleaſe to read it at large,</p>
                  <p>Surely, theſe Perſons, who ſtumble at ſuch <hi>Meſſages,</hi> and would make us <hi>Criminal</hi> for ſuch <hi>Propheſies,</hi> underſtand not the Voices of the true Prophets: They take things literally, which are Metaphorical
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58919:26"/>and Spiritually intended; as that of the <hi>Two-edged Sword;</hi> they put Sword in Capital Letters to make People believe, that <hi>none before</hi> 1660. <hi>were ſo much for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Carnal Weapon,</hi> as the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> according to their ſaid <hi>Note;</hi> as if they ſuppoſed it muſt needs be a <hi>Carnal Sword,</hi> the <hi>Quakers</hi> are minded to make Uſe of, when they can have an opportunity; tho' their patience and long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, (under various <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> and Severities, and Revolutions) have ſufficiently proved the contrary. But if the Saints <hi>Two-edged Sword,</hi> mention'd <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.6. muſt be taken for an Outward, Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial or <hi>Carnal Sword,</hi> why not the <hi>Rod</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> wherewith the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ſhall <hi>break the Heathen, (Pſal.</hi> 2.9.) for an outward material <hi>Rod</hi> of <hi>Iron</hi> or <hi>Steel?</hi> But theſe Perſons might have better conſidered the point in a Spiritual Senſe, that there is another ſort of <hi>Rod</hi> or <hi>Sword,</hi> than that Outward, Material one of <hi>Iron</hi> or <hi>Steel.</hi> There is the <hi>Rod</hi> of his <hi>Mouth, (i. e.</hi> of Chriſt's Mouth) Iſa. 11.4. <hi>Out of his Mouth went a ſharp Two-edged Sword,</hi> Rev. 1.16. There is the <hi>Sword</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which is the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which the Saints took unto them, Eph. 6.17. <hi>And he hath made my mouth like a ſharp Sword,</hi> Iſa. 49.2. <hi>Therefore have I <hi>hewed</hi> them by the Prophets, I have ſlain them by the words of my Mouth,</hi> Hoſ. 6.5. So that there's both the <hi>Rod,</hi> the <hi>Sword, hewing</hi> and <hi>ſlaying,</hi> as well as <hi>binding,</hi> Myſtically and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually ſpoken of by the Holy Prophets, Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Theſe things are hinted for better information, and moderating theſe our <hi>Adverſaries;</hi> and that their <hi>Hearers</hi> may not be influenced with their <hi>Anger</hi> againſt us.</p>
                  <p>As to what they quote in p. 21. Firſt ſome broken pieces out of ſomething they call <hi>The Quakers Declaration to</hi> Oliver, and out of <hi>Geor. Rofe</hi>'s Book, Entitled, <hi>The Righteouſneſs of God,</hi> and ſomething to <hi>Cromwell</hi> in't; theſe <hi>two</hi> I have not: But in ſhort may ſay thus much, that <hi>Oliver,</hi> and his <hi>Officers,</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> had a day and <hi>Power</hi> given them, and were a <hi>Dread (for a time)</hi> to their Adverſaries, (when the one was for ſeeking God in Prayer, and the other for Swearing, Curſing and Damning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) But they (i. e. <hi>O. C.</hi> &amp;c.) loſt their <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Day,</hi> through their <hi>Abuſe</hi> of it: Which was plainly told them, and their <hi>downfal</hi> as plainly foretold them by <hi>G. F. E. B.</hi> and divers others of our Friends. Theſe are <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>Fact;</hi> I am not concern'd to vindicate them, or their <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Government:</hi> The Lord has laid them aſide, who is no <hi>Reſpecter of Perſons; nor doth he accept the Perſons of Princes,</hi> Job 34.19.</p>
                  <p>As to what they quote out of a Letter, directed <hi>To the Council of Officers of the Army;</hi> and out of a <hi>Declaration wrote by</hi> E. B. <hi>in the Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>and ſubſcribed by ſeveral of the Principal Leaders
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58919:26"/>of them,</hi> (as theſe Men ſay) Printed 1659. — I ſhall forbear Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting upon theſe forementioned <hi>Inſtances</hi> in their 21ſt and 22d pages, they being in Subſtance fully anſwered in a Book of mine, Intitled, <hi>Chriſt's Lambs defended from Satan's Rage,</hi> (Printed 1691. being firſt writ in the Year 1677.) particularly in p. 19, 20, 21, 22, 23. and in many other places throughout that Book, as in p. 34, 35, 36, 37, &amp;c. where the ſaid <hi>Declaration,</hi> in particular, with the import of the foregoing is fully ſpoke to, and <hi>Objections,</hi> explained.</p>
                  <p>To their other <hi>Marginal Note,</hi> (p. 22.) <hi>viz. And may reaſſume it again, when they ſhall judge it meet.</hi> The Antecedent of this <hi>Note</hi> I underſtand to be their foregoing two Margent-notes (p. 20.) which <hi>three Notes</hi> joined together run thus, <hi>viz. which Government, that they (i. e.</hi> the People called <hi>Quakers) might not ſupport, they declare againſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Carnal Weapon in</hi> 1660. <hi>altho' none before, ſo much for</hi> it <hi>as they, and may reaſſume it again, when they ſhall judge it meet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This looks like a very <hi>Invidious Deſign</hi> to raiſe Suſpicion and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie in the Civil Government againſt us. But we hope and truſt in the Grace and Goodneſs of our God, that we ſhall both conſtantly and ſincerely approve our ſelves Innocent and Clear from theſe Mens prejudicial Inſinuations and Jealouſies, and to their diappointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of our Aſſemblies,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>Now concerning our ſeveral Religions <hi>Chriſtian Meetings,</hi> (as in good Conſcience we affirm they all are.) Theſe our Accuſers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear moſt invidious againſt them, as if influenced by ſome treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Judaſes,</hi> or envious Apoſtates. They begin to quote Mr. <hi>Bugg,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Kieth</hi> (as they ſtile them) their Authority againſt us. And what ſays their Mr. <hi>Bugg?</hi> They tell us, Mr. <hi>Bugg's Pilgrims Progreſs,</hi> Chapters 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>give an account of their ſeveral Meetings, and of their Fund, Exchequer, or Common-Bank.</hi> And what ſays there Mr. <hi>Kieth</hi> to it (ſeeing he is join'd with <hi>F. Bugg</hi> for a witneſs againſt us?) Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> (ſay they) <hi>who has been a</hi> Quaker <hi>above thirty Years,</hi> (more ſhame for him now to vilifie them) <hi>in his</hi> Second Narrative, p. 5. ſays, <hi>I am not able to Print Books, as they</hi> (Quakers) <hi>can, they are many, and have a Common-Stock; I am but one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which we Anſwer, we deny their Terms of <hi>
                        <hi>Fund,</hi> Exchequer</hi> or <hi>Common-Bank;</hi> we know no <hi>Common-Stock</hi> we have, that can properly be called a <hi>Fund,</hi> or an <hi>Exchequer,</hi> for improvement of a <hi>Stock,</hi> or advancing, and increaſing Mony upon, as a <hi>Fund,</hi> Foundation, or ſetled Bottom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What <hi>Fund</hi> for Improvement can a Collection for poor be, that is ſoon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58919:27"/>and ſpent? Tho' we have free and voluntary <hi>Collections</hi> in our Monthly and Quarterly Meetings for the Charitable Supply and Relief of the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Indigent</hi> among us, that they may not be Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable or Burdenſome to our Neighbours of other <hi>Perſuaſions,</hi> nor to the <hi>Pariſhes</hi> wherein they dwell. Thus we relieve our own <hi>Poor,</hi> and alſo pay our ſhare (or Proportions ſeverally) to other <hi>Poor</hi> of the reſpective <hi>Pariſhes</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> where our Friends inhabit. And now as we are a People, we muſt needs have divers Charges upon us, as <hi>Our</hi> Poors <hi>Rents,</hi> and charge of <hi>Meeting-Houſes, Rents</hi> and <hi>Reparations</hi> in many Places. As alſo for the neceſſary Supply and Relief of our Friends, when impoveriſhed or diſabled under, or by extream Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Diſtreſs in this, or other Countries, as in <hi>Ireland</hi> when they had greatly ſuffered by reaſon of the late War; and of late in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where in divers parts they have wanted Bread and Subſiſtence, through the late Years great Failing of their <hi>Harveſts:</hi> And alſo for the Relief of our Friends, who have been for many Years Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives in <hi>Algiers, Macqueneſs</hi> and <hi>Sally</hi> under ſore and miſerable Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Extremities, whereby <hi>many</hi> have loſt their Lives.</p>
                  <p>Upon theſe and other Occaſions and Neceſſities relating to our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Friends and Brethren, our Friends in this Nation, who are capable, have been free and willing without any Compulſion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute their Chriſtian Aſſiſtance, Charitable and Neceſſary Supplies, and accordingly Diſtributions have been made thereof purſuant to theſe good and neceſſary Ends: So that we have no <hi>Fund</hi> of <hi>Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> nor any <hi>Tax</hi> impoſed by any of our <hi>Meetings,</hi> but the <hi>neceſſary Occaſions</hi> tenderly recommended in the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in theſe Matters, and accordingly left to every ones <hi>free Liberty,</hi> as God ſhall incline their Hearts to conſider the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Needy,</hi> and <hi>Diſtreſſed,</hi> &amp;c. And if theſe our Accuſers who ſeek to <hi>Jealous</hi> and <hi>Criminate</hi> us in theſe matters, were charitably diſpoſed, as Chriſtians, they would not render us Criminal, Dangerous or Seditious for ſuch Religious Acts of Charity and Chriſtianity. But would better conſider the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> Practice in ſuch Caſes, than to miſrepreſent our Meetings (wherein ſuch Chriſtian Care is taken) as oppoſite to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This Savours rank of an Uncharitable Perſecuting Spirit, as their long <hi>Marginal-Note</hi> on p. 22, 23. doth, beginning with theſe words — <hi>They have a Government within the Government, independant from it, and oppoſite to it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is like <hi>Judas</hi> and the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and the <hi>Falſe Witneſſes</hi> againſt Chriſt to make him an Enemy to <hi>Caeſar;</hi> thus they would make us, the People of God, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> greatly obnoxious, (as if we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58919:27"/>promoted <hi>Regnum in Regno,</hi> not only Independent, but Oppoſite to the <hi>Civil Government,</hi> which none of our Meetings are, being all Peaceable and Innocent, both for the Worſhip of Almighty God, and Service of one another, in true <hi>Chriſtian Love,</hi> in order to promote the real <hi>Practice of Piety, Chriſtianity,</hi> and true <hi>Religion</hi> among us, as a People, and to prevent the contrary, as much as in us lies, by Warning and due Admonition, againſt all diſorderly, looſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, Immorality and Profaneneſs, tending to the Scandal of our Holy Profeſſion. And for ſuch good Ends there were <hi>Helps</hi> in <hi>Government,</hi> in the true Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. and all in Subjection to <hi>Chriſt's Government,</hi> who is <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Law-giver</hi> to His Church, and upon whoſe Shoulders the <hi>Government</hi> is laid. And this is not oppoſite to the <hi>Civil Government</hi> in the Nation, neither hath the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Government,</hi> or the <hi>Nation,</hi> ever ſuſtained any Hurt or Prejudice by theſe our <hi>Meetings,</hi> or by the Chriſtian Care or Service thereof; and their being <hi>Monthly, Quarterly,</hi> and <hi>Yearly,</hi> is for conveniency of the Times, and due Notice, and in no wiſe to Confront the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> no more than our <hi>Firſt-Days,</hi> and <hi>Weekly Meetings:</hi> for our <hi>Meetings</hi> are Innocently upheld in the <hi>Name of the Lord,</hi> for his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service, and have accordingly been manifeſt theſe many Years, under the various <hi>Revolutions of Government;</hi> and we hope we ſhall in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſtand for, and innocently Vindicate our Chriſtian and Juſt Liberty therein, againſt this <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Spirit,</hi> which unjuſtly ſeeks to Influence <hi>Authority</hi> againſt us, and our Religious Exerciſe in the Practice of our Chriſtian Religion. But bleſſed be the Lord, who by his Power hath better inclin'd the King and Government to Moderation and Gentleneſs towards all their Peaceable and Serviceable People.</p>
                  <p>As we do not aſſume to our ſelves a Government or Dominion over our People, or their Faith, nor place a Supremacy or Headſhip in Perſons or Aſſemblies, but in Jeſus Chriſt our Head and Governour; ſo we know <hi>no ſuch Supream Aſſembly</hi> among us, <hi>as gives Laws, and makes Orders, for the Government of our People, and ſuppreſſing Books writ againſt us</hi> (as is falſly ſuggeſted) we know no ſuch Supremacy or Dominion exerciſed among us, though we have Chriſtian Aſſemblies, both general and particular, held only in the Name and Power of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                  <p>Neither have we our <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> for the <hi>Government</hi> of our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to make by <hi>Aſſemblies;</hi> but to ſee thoſe put in practice, which Chriſt our Head and <hi>Law-giver</hi> hath taught us, and revealed to his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and that agreeable to the Holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and no ways
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58919:28"/>injurious to the outward <hi>Government.</hi> But for the promoting of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> in the Earth, and as Fellow-helpers in Chriſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking one another to <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Good Works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as for <hi>Paſſing Cenſure upon Offenders,</hi> ſo did the <hi>Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what have they againſt <hi>Paſſing Cenſure upon Offenders?</hi> Why may we not, as a <hi>Chriſtian Society,</hi> Cenſure <hi>Offenders,</hi> and <hi>Diſorderly Walkers,</hi> and ſuch as cauſe <hi>Diviſions</hi> and <hi>Offences,</hi> contrary to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel? It is evident the Primitive Chriſtian Churches did both Inſtruct, Exhort, Reprove, Rebuke and Reject.</p>
                  <p>Theſe our Perſecutors over and over twit us with a <hi>
                        <hi>Fund</hi> raiſed in all Counties by way of Collection:</hi> This their falſe pretence of a <hi>Fund</hi> is ſpoke to and detected already. As for <hi>what</hi> is <hi>Collected</hi> (as they ſay) the Diſpoſal thereof is neither Order'd nor Govern'd by our <hi>Second Days Meeting</hi> (as is very falſly related) nor is the <hi>Mony</hi> ſo <hi>Collected,</hi> for <hi>Stipends</hi> for our <hi>Teachers,</hi> that is groſly falſe alſo: we have no <hi>Mercenary Teachers</hi> for <hi>Stipends</hi> or <hi>Wages,</hi> nor among us <hi>Attendants</hi> upon the <hi>Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that have Money, either of that which is Collected, or any other, for Attending, as is alſo <hi>falſly Inſinuated.</hi> For thoſe among us, that <hi>Attend</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> do it <hi>Gratis,</hi> and <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as to their own <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>Maintenance</hi> of the <hi>Poor,</hi> and thoſe that are impoveriſhed, and made <hi>Indigent</hi> or <hi>Neceſſitous,</hi> either by any Calamity befallen them, or through great <hi>Sufferings</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> for Conſcience ſake. 'Tis not meet they ſhould ſtarve for want, but be Miniſtred unto for their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>Relief.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All our Charitable <hi>Contributions</hi> and <hi>Collections</hi> for theſe good Ends as afore-mentioned, are warrantable, and warranted by the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians</hi> Practice: See <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.26. <hi>For it hath pleaſed them of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia and Achaia, to make a certain Contribution for the poor Saints which are at Jeruſalem.</hi> See alſo 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2, 3. <hi>Now concerning the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection for the Saints, as I have given order to the Churches of Galatia, even ſo do ye. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the firſt day of the Week, let every one of you lay by him in ſtore, as God hath proſpered him, that there be no Gatherings when I come. And when I come, whomſoever you ſhall approve by your Letters, them will I ſend to bring your Liberality to Jeruſalem.</hi> See alſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> chap. 8. how <hi>Paul</hi> commendeth their <hi>abounding in Contribution</hi> to the <hi>Saints.</hi> And chap. 9. How he ſtirreth them up to a <hi>Bountifulneſs</hi> in that caſe. See alſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.9. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.1. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. for the Saints Incouragement in that <hi>Miniſtration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58919:28"/>
                  <p>Now therefore the Invidious Deſign of theſe Men in their falſe Noiſe of the <hi>Quakers Fund,</hi> and ſupporting of their <hi>Government</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, to render them Obnoxious, Dangerous or Seditious, the Righteous Judge of all (who knows our Innocency) will Judge theſe, and ſuch unjuſt Inſinuations and Invectives, and to Him we commit our <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Cauſe,</hi> who hath hitherto helped us, and ſtood by us, and in Him we Confide, and doubt not He will plead our Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>As to <hi>G. Keith</hi>'s Book, called, <hi>The pretended Yearly Meeting of the Quakers, their Nameleſs Bull of Excommunication,</hi> Printed 1695. out of which theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> take a large Citation, in their 22, 23, 24 Pages. I ſhall not need to inſiſt upon it, nor upon his Envious Compariſon, between the way taken by our ſaid <hi>Yearly Meeting,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition,</hi> but refer the <hi>Reader</hi> to <hi>Tho. Ellwood</hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>G. K.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>Truth Defended, and the Friends thereof Cleared from the falſe Charges, foul Reproaches, and envious Cavils caſt upon them, by</hi> G. K. from p. 59. to p. 64, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>As to the <hi>Door of our Yearly Meeting being kept by ſome Perſon or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> this (we hope) is no Offence in it ſelf, whatever theſe Perſons, or their Tool, <hi>F. B.</hi> would make of it, the <hi>Door</hi> not being <hi>lock'd, barr'd,</hi> or <hi>bolted,</hi> as prohibited. 'Tis meet ſuch Doors ſhould be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in ſuch a Populous City, to prevent diſorderly <hi>Intruders,</hi> and <hi>Buſie-bodies;</hi> and I think no <hi>Civil Society,</hi> who have the neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns thereof to Inſpect, will be offended at ſuch <hi>Attendance</hi> and <hi>Care</hi> at the <hi>Doors.</hi> For why ſhould <hi>Intruders</hi> or <hi>Buſie-bodies</hi> be admitted, to gratifie their meer <hi>Curioſities,</hi> or evil Eye, or to meddle in other Peoples Affairs, which concern them not? The <hi>Care</hi> of our <hi>Poor,</hi> and of the <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Converſations</hi> of thoſe among us, lies upon us, and not upon others, who are not of us, or our <hi>Society.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to our Teſtimony againſt <hi>Tythes,</hi> and forc'd <hi>Maintenance</hi> of a <hi>Miniſtery, &amp;c.</hi> 'tis no new Teſtimony among us, but what we have believed to be a <hi>Chriſtian Teſtimony</hi> ever ſince we were a People, as did divers of the <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and of the beſt <hi>Reformers,</hi> in their Day and Time; witneſs <hi>John Wickliff, Will. Swinderby, Walter Brute, Will. Thorp,</hi> the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> with others mentioned in the Book of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> who did bear Teſtimony againſt <hi>Tythes,</hi> and <hi>Compelled Maintenance,</hi> and other Corruptions of the <hi>Popiſh Clergy:</hi> This their Teſtimony againſt <hi>Tythes,</hi> in the Goſpel Times, was made a principal Article againſt them by the Papiſts; as more largely appears in the Firſt <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn</hi> of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> II. <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and <hi>Henry</hi> V. And eſpecially <hi>Will. Thorp,</hi> in his <hi>Examinatian</hi> before the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> gives an ample Teſtimony againſt <hi>Tythes,</hi> and the <hi>Pride</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58919:29"/>of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> ſince the old <hi>Law</hi> for <hi>Tythes</hi> is aboliſh'd by Chriſt. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly tells the <hi>Arch-Biſhop,</hi> viz. <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Thoſe Prisſts, that will challenge or take Tythes, deny that Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, and do the Prieſts Office in the Old Law, for whom Tythes were granted; for elſe Prieſts take now Tythes wrongfully.</hi>
                     </q> See Book of <hi>Mart. vol.</hi> 1. p. 700. printed 1641.</p>
                  <p>And as to our Caution (to thoſe concerned among us) againſt <hi>Printing</hi> or <hi>Publiſhing</hi> any thing not of <hi>Service</hi> for <hi>Truth,</hi> or <hi>Scandalous, Reproachful,</hi> or to uphold <hi>Diviſion</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> warning given by our ſaid Meeting againſt ſuch Books or Writings, we hope, will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be Offenſive, nor deem'd Seditious, by any Moderate or Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Perſons.</p>
                  <p>And for the <hi>Care</hi> of our <hi>Meeting,</hi> to have <hi>Records</hi> of the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of <hi>our Friends for Conſcience ſake duly gathered, truly entered and kept,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Such Caution was alſo honeſt and juſt, but ſuch <hi>Records</hi> are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>to render the Governours and Government odious for Perſecution to Poſterity,</hi> as it is now unjuſtly noted againſt us, in their 25 Page, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any diſtinction between the <hi>preſent favourable Government,</hi> and thoſe under which we have formerly ſuffered ſevere <hi>Perſecutions;</hi> and our <hi>Records</hi> thereof, are not deſigned to render the <hi>Government odious,</hi> but to have recourſe to, for Application to be made to our <hi>Superiours</hi> for <hi>Relief,</hi> that they may not be Ignorant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                  <p>And as to the <hi>Author</hi> to <hi>Satan Diſrob'd,</hi> p. 82. quoted his Informing, <hi>That in this</hi> Regiſter <hi>there are many groundleſs and downright Falſhoods, which it is very fit the World ſhould know; becauſe they take great Care to ſwell this</hi> Regiſter, <hi>and have threatned to publiſh it to after-Ages,</hi> (p. 26.)</p>
                  <p>Pray obſerve, what a likely <hi>Story</hi> this is? How he ſhould he know, what's recorded in ſuch a <hi>Regiſter,</hi> if he never <hi>Saw</hi> it, nor <hi>Read</hi> it? As I preſume he has not, it not being publiſhed; neither do I know of any among us, that have ſo <hi>threatned</hi> to <hi>publiſh</hi> it to <hi>after-Ages:</hi> But this is not the firſt <hi>Aſperſion,</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Snake,</hi> and <hi>Satan Diſrob'd,</hi> hath uujuſtly caſt upon us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">What they quote againſt <hi>E. B.</hi> in his Works, p. 273. under the Year 1657. <hi>viz. The Sufferings of the People of God</hi> [here they add <hi>(that is</hi> Quakers] <hi>in this Age, is greater ſuffering, and more unjuſt than in the Days of Chriſt, or of the Apoſtles, or in any time ſince:</hi>
                     </q> [here they leave out, <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>Queen</hi> Mary<hi>'s Days brought not forth a Suffering more Cruel, <hi>in many reſpects,</hi>
                        </hi> as doth appear.]</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58919:29"/>
                  <p>Now, tho' I may not undertake to Vindicate all thoſe <hi>Expreſſions,</hi> or the next following, yet the words <hi>[In many Reſpects]</hi> which theſe Men have left out, do ſo far help the matter, and explain his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and intention, as not to compare the then <hi>Sufferings</hi> of the <hi>Lord's People</hi> in <hi>every reſpect,</hi> or in <hi>all reſpects,</hi> to the <hi>Sufferings</hi> in the <hi>Days</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or his Apoſtles, or in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Days, but <hi>in many reſpects.</hi> And thoſe <hi>Reſpects E. B.</hi> partly explains in the ſame, and in the next Paragraph, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As <hi>Firſt,</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Martyrs</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, had more juſt Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and Proſecution in <hi>Law,</hi> than the People of God have now; for now ſome of the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in <hi>England</hi> caſt Men into <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and confine them, and cauſe their Goods to be ſpoiled <hi>without</hi> any <hi>Law,</hi> or the due Execution of a <hi>Law.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Herein it doth appear to exceed the Suffering of the Saints in former Age, in that many Suffer now cruel Things, about Trivial, Fooliſh, Matters, as for <hi>not putting off the Hat,</hi> or for <hi>Theeing</hi> (i. e. <hi>Thouing</hi>) Men, (and alſo for denying <hi>Swearing.</hi>) We do not read that the worſt of <hi>Tyrants</hi> in the Apoſtles Days, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or ſince, ever cauſed any to ſuffer for <hi>Such</hi> things as theſe, or ever queſtioned any upon ſuch ſmall Accounts; for <hi>Hundreds</hi> have ſuffered upon <hi>Suſpicion,</hi> when nothing at all can be charged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: And this is contrary to <hi>Magna Charta.</hi> And <hi>in many other reſpects</hi> (which might be named) this ſuffering is greater, than hath been in any Age.</q> Thus <hi>E. B.</hi> explains himſelf.</p>
                  <p>And further to ſhew the greater <hi>Injuſtice</hi> of ſuch <hi>Perſecution,</hi> under the then <hi>Common Wealth,</hi> in 1657. he gives this Reaſon, <q rend="margQuotes">Becauſe <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in the Exerciſe of Religion, was never ſo much promiſed and profeſſed, as in this Nation at this day; and yet for the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of a pure <hi>Conſcience,</hi> many are <hi>Woful Sufferers,</hi> even by ſuch, who in words profeſs <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> themſelves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> This was under the <hi>Common Wealth</hi>'s Government, in 1657.</p>
                  <p>And as to the following quoted againſt <hi>E. B. viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">What was done to <hi>Chriſt</hi> or the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> was chiefly done by a Law, and in a great part by the due <hi>Execution</hi> of a <hi>Law,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now according to <hi>E. B</hi>'s own <hi>Explication,</hi> his words ſhould run thus, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">The <hi>Suffering</hi> of the People of God, <hi>in many reſpects,</hi> in this Age, is greater, and more <hi>Extraordinarily Arbitrary,</hi> than in the days of Chriſt or his Apoſtles, and more <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt</hi> (that is) on their parts, who profeſſed <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and knew better than the Ignorant <hi>Perſecutors</hi> in the days of Chriſt, and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</q> For <hi>E. B.</hi> in 1657. and in p. 337. tells them then of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58919:30"/>People of God being perſecuted by many of the Rulers, Prieſts and People, ſent to <hi>Priſon,</hi> and <hi>Baniſh'd</hi> out of Towns, and <hi>Whipt</hi> and <hi>Beaten, ſcorn'd</hi> and <hi>revil'd,</hi> that the <hi>ſame</hi> things were done to the Apoſtles, and to the Servants of the Lord; which (ſaith he) are now done unto the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God, &amp;c.</hi> So that the one was as unjuſt in it ſelf as the other.</p>
                  <p>I confeſs (tho' <hi>E. B.</hi> was a Man truly inſpired with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and of <hi>Propheſie,</hi> and endued with Heavenly <hi>Gifts</hi> above many of his Years, being but a Young Man;) yet he was not ſo skilled in <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terms,</hi> as to expreſs himſelf therein altogether free from Exception. For inſtead of <hi>[due Execution]</hi> it ſhould rather have been <hi>[by a Regular or Judicial Procedure]</hi> he intending, as to <hi>Form</hi> or <hi>Order</hi> of Law, tho' the ſufferings of the People of God, both in the days of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s, were very unjuſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them, and with far greater Barbarities and Cruelties un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Death, than in the Common-wealth's days in <hi>Old England.</hi> But in <hi>New England</hi> ſome were cruelly Whipt, and others unjuſtly put to Death: And in the Vallies of <hi>Piedmont</hi> in 1655. <hi>Morland</hi>'s Hiſtory gives account (in the Year 1658.) of the Lamentable Cruelties, Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities and Tortures many of thoſe People ſuffered unto death.</p>
                  <p>But as to this ſaid Charge againſt <hi>E. B.</hi> I have ſufficiently anſwered, and clear'd the matter, as on our parts and ſufferings, over and over to <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> as in the <hi>Quakers Vindication againſt</hi> Bugg<hi>'s Calumnies</hi> in one Sheet, p. 2. and my <hi>Sober Expoſtulation,</hi> p. 63, 64, 65, 66. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of taking any Serious Notice thereof, he frequently repeats the ſame Charge with his Additions, Scoffs and Perverſions. As in his <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> (ſubjoned to theſe <hi>Three Norfolk-Prieſts Brief Diſcovery</hi>) p. 28. he has a fling at us about it after his flouting, fallacious way of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, in theſe words, <hi>This your Prophet and Son of Thunder, in his Works,</hi> p. 273. <hi>tells the World, that the ſufferings of the</hi> Quakers <hi>are greater, yea, and more unjuſt too, than the ſufferings in the days of Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Martyrs; yea, all the Ten Perſecutions by your Doctrine, were nothing to the</hi> Quakers <hi>ſufferings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, what a notorious and horrid Lie and Perverſion this is upon us, <hi>F. B.</hi> himſelf cannot be ignorant, how I have anſwered him two or three times over to the contrary in this point.</p>
                  <p>To their quoting <hi>Joſ. Wyeth</hi> in his <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity,</hi> p. 6. aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting <q rend="margQuotes">Our Principles are now no other, than what they were, when we were firſt a People, for Truth changes not.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And alſo for Concluſion, they quote <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> in his <hi>Brief Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks</hi> on <hi>T. C</hi>'s Book, annext to the <hi>Counterfeit Convert,</hi> Printed 1694.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58919:30"/>p. 72. ſaying, <hi>I may ſee cauſe otherwiſe to word the matter, and yet our Intentions be the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the <hi>firſt</hi> I ſay, Theſe Men have not convicted us of any ſuch <hi>Change</hi> of our <hi>Principles,</hi> from what they were, when <hi>firſt</hi> we were a <hi>People,</hi> as they would inſinuate, as if we were changed to ſuch <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith as ſeem much more agreeable to the Word of God, and more Conformable to the</hi> Church of England <hi>than formerly,</hi> as in their Margent, p. 26, 27. And yet theſe Men do now more hidiouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim againſt us, as <hi>blaſphemous</hi> and <hi>ſeditious,</hi> than ever they did before. Now, when (in their Eſteem) we are far more Orthodox than at firſt in our <hi>Principles.</hi> But they will needs have it, that <hi>they have juſt Cauſe to diſtruſt theſe our Profeſſions, as being deſign'd to ſerve a Turn,</hi> becauſe we <hi>are far from diſowning our ancient Books</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>in which theſe Blaſphemies are contained,</hi> Margent Note, p. 27.) So they conclude all <hi>Blaſphemies</hi> they have quoted out of our Books againſt us: but we want <hi>Proof</hi> ſtill of this great and loud <hi>Charge.</hi> And they have given no clear <hi>Definition</hi> of our <hi>Principles,</hi> nor diſtinguiſh'd <hi>Principles</hi> from the Circumſtance of <hi>Words, Expreſſions</hi> and <hi>Arguments,</hi> which may be variouſly given in defence of the ſame <hi>Principles.</hi> But which is worſe, give their partial, broken, mangled and perverted Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for our <hi>Principles,</hi> and perhaps an Unapt Expreſſion or two, pickt up out of Good Matter. And the main Things or Principles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have all along, even from the firſt chiefly differed from many of the Clergy, are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 1ſt Our ſincere belief of the True <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Perfection:</hi> And 2dly. Our Chriſtian Teſtimony againſt <hi>Tythes, forced maintenance,</hi> and <hi>Perſecution,</hi> (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Popiſh Ceremonies and Superſtitions, not yet purged out,) as inconſiſtent with Chriſt's free Miniſtry, concerning which we are manifeſtly the very ſame in Principle and Perſuaſion we were from the Beginning.</p>
                  <p>To the 2d part (quoted againſt me) I have already anſwered; there may be various manners of <hi>wording</hi> and <hi>expreſſing</hi> the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and yet our Intentions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he ſame. As where I explain my <hi>Friends</hi> Meaning and Intentions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be agreeable to mine, and more fully diſtinguiſh and clear it according to the Harmony of his other Concurrent Paſſages, in the ſame and other Books; as ſometimes in theſe precedent <hi>Obſervations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to <hi>Bugg</hi>'s <hi>Poſtcript,</hi> 'tis according to his other <hi>Scribles, Falſhood;</hi> and <hi>Jeers</hi> frequently repeated, and moſtly anſwered in the foregoing <hi>Obſervations,</hi> and other <hi>Anſwers</hi> of mine: He is ſo full of <hi>Tautologies, Repetitions</hi> of the ſame <hi>Falſhoods, Boaſtings, Scoffing</hi> and <hi>Flouting;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58919:31"/>and ending with Falſhoods, as <hi>obſerving us timerous about their Petition,</hi> and that <hi>we make the World believe we fear Perſecution.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have endeavoured to prevent his, and ſome Prieſts endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours (tending thereto againſt us) to Authority; this has diſquieted him and them. And therefore to be revenged, he repeats his old detected Lies and Calumnies againſt us, as that we <hi>call the Scriptures, Serpent's Meat, <hi>Beaſtly Ware,</hi>
                     </hi> &amp;c. with many more abominable Lies, ſince often told of the ſame, yet perſiſts therein like a Hardned Wretch; ſo that it is not worth the while to ſpend much more time in tracing the Crooked Steps of ſuch a <hi>Mercenary Agent,</hi> who gives no <hi>ſolid</hi> nor <hi>pertinent Reply</hi> to any ſerious Anſwer, but clamours, ſcoffs, boaſts, vilifies, and throws as much <hi>Dirt,</hi> as he can, upon us, ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his precious time to ſeek our <hi>Ruin,</hi> by <hi>Reproaches</hi> and <hi>Calumnies</hi> to enrage the Prieſts, and incenſe Authority (if he could) againſt us. But the Lord will Rebuke him, and Reward him according to his Deeds. I wiſh he may yet ſeek and find a place of Repentance (if yet to be found) before he be cut off; and however, that others may take warning by his Lamentable <hi>Relapſe</hi> and Treacherous Apoſtaſie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:58919:31"/>
               <head>A Brief Examination OF A <hi>Defaming Pamphlet,</hi> Without Author's name to it:
<list>
                     <item>Reproachfully ſtiled, <hi>Some few of the</hi> Quakers <hi>many Horrid Blaſphemies, Hereſies, and their Bloody Treaſonable Principles deſtructive to Government.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Delivered to the Members of both Houſes of the LORDS and COMMONS, in the Month of <hi>March,</hi> 1698/9.</item>
                  </list>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">PART. II.</head>
               <p>THIS <hi>Title</hi> looks with <hi>Perſecution, Fury, Deadly Envy</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> in the Face of it; it is like the work of certain <hi>Judaſſes,</hi> and their Prieſts, who are fallen into ſuch a faint and feeble Condition, as to be beholden to <hi>Apoſtates</hi> to help and aſſiſt them in their private <hi>Cabals,</hi> to <hi>Plot</hi> and Contrive Miſchief againſt the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and to bring forth ſuch furious <hi>Clamour, Calumnies</hi> and <hi>Perverſions,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58919:32"/>thereby labouring to incenſe the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> againſt the Peaceable People called <hi>Quakers.</hi> Now let's Examine ſome of their Principal Objections, or Allegations quoted, for <hi>Proof</hi> of their <hi>Furious, Perſecuting Title.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I. <hi>Concerning the Holy Trinity.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. Their firſt Objection: <hi>The Scriptures do not tell the People of a Trinity, nor Three Perſons, &amp;c.</hi> Againſt Geo. Fox, <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 246.</p>
                  <p>Here, in the ſame Paragraph, Period and Anſwer, theſe Words are left out, <hi>viz. [And the Father, Son and Holy Spirit, are always one.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſerve hence, what may be term'd <hi>the Scripture Trinity,</hi> or <hi>Divine Three</hi> in the <hi>Deity,</hi> the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> is plainly confeſs'd. As alſo in <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 99.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">As for the Unity we own, and Chriſt being the <hi>brightneſs of the Father's Glory, and expreſs Image of his Subſtance,</hi> we own: As alſo, <hi>in ſome Principles of the Elect People of God,</hi> Printed 1671. p. 43. Of the Word <hi>Trinitas,</hi> there is no mention made in <hi>Scripture,</hi> yet the Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and all theſe are <hi>One.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now pray obſerve, if any be offended at this, and if our <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> will produce us plain <hi>Scripture-Proof</hi> for the Terms <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>Three Perſons,</hi> then 'tis meet we ſhould <hi>Retract</hi> thoſe Words before, <hi>i. e.</hi> That the <hi>Scriptures</hi> do not tell People thereof.</p>
                  <p>'Tis worthy our Obſervation, what Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> in the <hi>Life of John Earl of Rocheſter,</hi> p. 104. ſpeaking of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Which for want of Terms fit to expreſs them by, we call Perſons, and are called in Scripture the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Whereby it ſeems then they do not think the Word <hi>Perſons,</hi> either a fit or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Term to expreſs the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> by; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe Men ſhould not be too ſevere in Impoſing it, or Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in their Cenſuring others about it, to occaſion Diſturbance in Peoples Minds, and ſuch Diſputes as probably they cannot well quiet, or bring to a clear Solution.</p>
                  <p>By any of our Queſtioning, or not uſing the Term <hi>Perſons</hi> in this caſe, we do not deny the Doctrine or thing intended, <hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> which Three are one. And we would not have any ſo Injurious, or Diſingenuous, as to conclude we deny the ſame,</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58919:32"/>
                  <p n="2">2 Q. Againſt <hi>Will. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 12, 13, 14, 15. they pick up ſome <hi>Pieces</hi> of his <hi>Arguments</hi> (but Anſwer them not) levelled againſt this Doctrine held by ſome, which they leave out, <hi>viz.</hi> "The Trinity of Diſtinct and <hi>Separate</hi> Perſons in the Unity of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. This our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> leave out, and which by this time a Day, (we hope) none will maintain ſuch a <hi>Separation</hi> in the Deity, between the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> being <hi>one God,</hi> bleſſed for ever. They alſo take no notice of what he Writes for this <hi>Scripture Trinity, Sandy Found.</hi> p. 32. <hi>viz.</hi> "Miſtake me not, we never have diſown'd the <hi>Father, Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> which are <hi>one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in p. 36. <q rend="margQuotes">As concerning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I declare on behalf of that Deſpiſed People, Vulgarly called <hi>Quakers,</hi> the Grace of which we teſtifie, hath never taught us to acknowledge another God, than he that's <hi>Father</hi> of all things, who fills Heaven and Earth. Neither to confeſs <hi>another</hi> Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> than he that appear'd ſo many <hi>Hundred Years</hi> ago, made of a <hi>Virgin,</hi> like unto us in all things, <hi>Sin</hi> excepted, or any other Doctrine, than was by <hi>Him</hi> declar'd and practis'd; and alſo being God's Innocent Heritage, in Principles, Life and Death, to bear an Unanimous Teſtimony for the only true <hi>God,</hi> true <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and Heavenly Doctrine; which in their Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is openly atteſted.</q> Thus far <hi>W. P.</hi> in his own and our Friends Vindication.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Here is the Three Perſons thou dreams of, which thou wouldſt divide out of one like a Conjurer,</hi> &amp;c. quoted againſt <hi>G. W.</hi> and other <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> (as they ſay) in their Book, Intituled, <hi>Iſhmael and his Mother caſt out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to this <hi>Quotation</hi> (though not truly taken,) yet as the Words are in the ſaid <hi>Iſhmael, &amp;c.</hi> quoted, <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> hath poſitively diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own'd the Words, and affirms, <q rend="margQuotes">They are none of his, and that he writ not that part of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>Townſend,</hi> which was in the Year 1654. and that he neither ſhall ſtand by, nor own theſe Words; and that after he ſaw them in Print, he was ſorry his <hi>Name</hi> was to that <hi>Paper,</hi> without diſtinction between what he writ, and what he did not write in it, wherein the Words are which gave the Occaſion, and which appear too <hi>Raſh</hi> and <hi>Irreverent,</hi> either to Vindicate Solid <hi>Truth,</hi> or oppoſe any wrong Notion.</q> For a more full account of <hi>G. Whitehead</hi>'s <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Clearneſs</hi> in this very Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he refers the <hi>Reader</hi> to his <hi>Anſwer</hi> to Dr. <hi>Forde,</hi> Intituled, <hi>The Chriſtianity of the People commonly called</hi> Quakers, <hi>Printed</hi> 1690. p. 28.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58919:33"/>
                  <p>Now pray obſerve, That in the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the <hi>Godhead,</hi> there is the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> being thoſe Divine <hi>Three Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in Heaven,</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Word,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and that thoſe <hi>Three</hi> are <hi>One,</hi> of one Subſtance, Power and Eternity: As we have not denied, but confeſs'd this Doctrine, herein we don't diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II. <hi>Concerning Chriſt, our Bleſſed Lord.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>That the outward Perſon, which Suffer'd, was properly the Son of God, we utterly deny,</hi> againſt <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> p. 246.</p>
                  <p>Here I take him to mean the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in reſpect to his <hi>Divine Being,</hi> as He is of <hi>One Subſtance</hi> with the <hi>Father,</hi> which his Body that Suffered Death was not: Though He was truly the <hi>Son of God,</hi> as He took upon Him that Body, and as made of a Woman, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Being conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, and born of the Virgin Mary.</hi> Take <hi>W. P</hi>'s own Explication, in the ſame Page and Paragraph, which is unfair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly left out, where he plainly confeſſeth,</p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">That He, that laid down his Life, and ſuffered his Body to be Crucified by the <hi>Jews,</hi> without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>only Son of the Moſt High God,</hi> &amp;c. one with the Father, and of a Nature Eternal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> Theſe Words our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> leave out.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Your Imagined God beyond the Stars, and your Carnal Chriſt, is utterly denied, &amp;c.</hi> Here they quote <hi>Sword of the Lord drawn,</hi> p. 5. By <hi>C. A.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which Book I have not; but theſe Words are denied (as well as the Perſon that writ them) as <hi>Offenſive,</hi> and as neither proper to the true Chriſt, or <hi>Omni-preſent God,</hi> who therefore is not an imagined God, nor is the true Chriſt a Carnal Chriſt, but a Spiritual and Moſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Chriſt. See <hi>Antidote againſt the Venom of the Snake in the Graſs,</hi> p. 145.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>The Devil was in thee, thou ſayſt, thou art Saved by Chriſt, without thee, and ſo haſt recorded thy ſelf a Reprobate.</hi> Againſt <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 250.</p>
                  <p>Which was, becauſe this Adverſary was Ignorant of the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Chriſt within him,</hi> as the Words there follow, which are unjuſtly left out. For inſtead of owning the <hi>Myſtery of Chriſt within,</hi> the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary (in the place quoted) pleads the <hi>Continuance of Sin in the Saints, for their Humiliation,</hi> Gr. Myſt. p. 250.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:58919:33"/>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>What was his (Chriſt's) Perſon, being mean and contemptible, to them (his Diſciples) more than another Perſon?</hi> Againſt <hi>Will. Bailey</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> p. 307.</p>
                  <p>The Parentheſis is wrong placed here, to pervert the Senſe; 'tis thus in the Book quoted, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">They loved his Perſon for the ſake of the Frame and Quality of the Spirit that dwelt in Him; or elſe what was his Perſon (being mean and contemptible) to them, more than another Perſon? but for <hi>that</hi> which dwelt in him, they loved him; let none miſtake, I do not ſlight it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that by this his Perſon was more than any other, <hi>i. e.</hi> more excellent, though made very low by Suffering.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>That Finite and Impotent Creature [Speaking of Chriſt.]</hi> Here they quote <hi>Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 20.</p>
                  <p>Which is a ſhameful Abuſe and Lie; he ſpeaks not a Word of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in that Paragraph, but of the <hi>Finite</hi> and <hi>Impotent Creature</hi> in <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> as being capable of Forgiving Injuries done him, which the Notion of an Adequate and Rigid Satisfaction allows not God.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>The Sufferings of the People of God (Quakers)</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quakers</hi> is added, and the Subſequent Matter Anſwered before.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>The Blood of Chriſt was no more, than the Blood of another Saint.</hi> Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt <hi>S. E</hi>'s Letter.</p>
                  <p>Not warrantable Expreſſions, and diſown'd in the ſaid <hi>Antidote,</hi> p. 223, 224, 225. Where the Benefit of Chriſt's Blood, is truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
                  <p>Their Charge againſt <hi>W. P.</hi> about <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Co-eſſentiality, and Co-eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with the Father, of his being made Man,</hi> &amp;c. p. 4. Anſwered by <hi>W. P.</hi> himſelf, hereafter.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. <hi>Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh, was but a Figure</hi> [i. e. <hi>a Figure or Type of the Inward Chriſt, or Light within.</hi>] This is quoted againſt <hi>G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head's Truth Defending the</hi> Quakers, p. 22.</p>
                  <p>They abuſe me ſtill in this; it was none of my Aſſertion, <hi>That Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh was but a Figure:</hi> Neither is there ſuch a word in that page quoted, but in the <hi>Prieſt's Queſtion,</hi> p. 20. as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is anſwered, and it is a manifeſt <hi>Forgery</hi> upon me, that <hi>Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh, was but a Figure or Type of the Inward Chriſt, or Light within:</hi> I poſitively diſown theſe words, as a down-right <hi>Forgery</hi> and <hi>Abuſe</hi> put upon me. What a horrid ſhame is it, that any <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or their <hi>Agents</hi> ſhould have a hand in preſenting the <hi>Parliament</hi> with ſuch <hi>Lies</hi> and <hi>Abuſes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:58919:34"/>
                  <p n="12">12. <hi>One outward thing cannot be the proper Figure or Repreſentation of another, — The Outward Lamb ſhews forth the Inward Lamb</hi> [i. e. <hi>The Paſchal Lamb was not the Figure or Type of the Outward Chriſt; but of the Light within, of which Chriſt himſelf was but a Figure.</hi>] This is quoted againſt <hi>W. Penn</hi>'s <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> p. 97.</p>
                  <p>Their ſubſequent <hi>Perverſion</hi> is notorious, and as groſly falſe. Tho' it is not the way of the <hi>Scripture</hi> to teach us (as <hi>W. P.</hi> ſaith in the page quoted) that <hi>One outward thing is, or can be the <hi>proper</hi> Figure or Repreſentation of another;</hi> yet it is a twofold <hi>Falſhood</hi> and <hi>Perverſion,</hi> to make it the <hi>Quakers Doctrine,</hi> that the <hi>Paſchal Lamb</hi> was not <hi>Figurative</hi> or <hi>Typical</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> as without us, but of the <hi>Light within:</hi> As alſo, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf was but a <hi>Figure</hi> of the <hi>Light within.</hi> Theſe I teſtifie againſt as a Two-fold Falſhood and Perverſion againſt the <hi>Quakers:</hi> And how will theſe Men prove that the outward <hi>Paſchal Lamb</hi> was the <hi>proper</hi> Figure or Repreſentation of Chriſt's outward Perſon, pray? What proper Reſemblance had they? Was not rather the <hi>Lamb,</hi> in reſpect of its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, a proper Figure of Chriſt's Innocency, as the <hi>Lamb</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> once Offered for Sin?</p>
                  <p n="13">13. <hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>ſee no need of directing Men to the Type for the Anti-type, nor yet to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>either to Jeſus Chriſt, or his Blood,</hi> &amp;c. quoted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>G. W</hi>'s <hi>Light and Life of Chriſt within,</hi> p. 8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note,</hi> here after <hi>Anty-type,</hi> they leave out [<hi>viz.</hi> neither to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Temple] I ask theſe Men, where the Scripture doth ſo direct Men to go to the outward Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for Jeſus Chriſt? Nay, Doth it not contrariwiſe direct them? See plain Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.12, 13, 14. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. <hi>And indeed this</hi> [i. e. <hi>Juſtification by that</hi>] <hi>we deny,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Q.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> their <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> p. 148.</p>
                  <p>Here they wrong the Quotation again: <hi>Juſtification</hi> by what? But by what Chriſt <hi>fulfilled wholly without us:</hi> This is left out, For if <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, Regeneration</hi> and the <hi>New Birth</hi> be neceſſary to the compleating our <hi>Juſtification</hi> and Acceptance in Chriſt, then 'tis not compleated <hi>wholly without us,</hi> tho' obtain'd for us, without us, by Chriſt as the one <hi>Offering</hi> and our <hi>Mediator.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15. <hi>Faith in Chriſt's outward Manifeſtation has been a deadly Poiſon, theſe latter Ages have been infected with.</hi> Againſt <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Quakeriſm a new Nick-name,</hi> p. 6.</p>
                  <p>'Tis making Faith in the Hiſtory thereof, that is, in oppoſition to his Power and Work in the Soul, and to Godly living, as is evident in the place quoted.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58919:34"/>
                  <p n="16">16. <hi>And ſince they believe that outward Appearance</hi> [i. e. <hi>of Jeſus at</hi> Jeruſalem] <hi>they need not Preach what is not to be again.</hi> Againſt <hi>W. P. Ibid.</hi> p. 12.</p>
                  <p>He means, they need not always preach it, where 'tis believed; and confeſſeth, all true <hi>Quakers</hi> own that Viſible Appearance of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. <hi>So, when you come to know this [to wit, the Operation of Chriſt, or the Light within] you will ceaſe remembring his Death at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Againſt <hi>The Doctrine of Perfection Vindicated,</hi> p. 19.</p>
                  <p>I don't believe this to be juſtly or impartially quoted; let them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it at large, and whoſe Book it is.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. <hi>So all Chriſtendom hath talked long enough of Chriſt's Fleſh and Blood.</hi> Againſt <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>Several Papers for ſpreading the Truth,</hi> p. 59.</p>
                  <p>This alſo looks like an unjuſt Quotation; let them produce it, with the reaſon thereof at large; or elſe be aſhamed of ſuch Picking, Nib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Curtailing to deceive the Reader.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. <hi>Not to Jeſus, the Son of</hi> Abraham, David <hi>and</hi> Mary, <hi>Saint or Angel, but to God the Father all Worſhip, Honour and Glory be given.</hi> Againſt <hi>W. Shewen</hi>'s Treatiſe of <hi>Thoughts and Imaginations,</hi> p. 37.</p>
                  <p>I know his intent was not to Jeſus <hi>Only, as</hi> the Son of <hi>Abraham, David</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> but as he is God over all, bleſſed for ever! All Worſhip, Hononr and Glory belongs to him. And as he is the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Son of God, to whom all Power and all Judgment is committed, it is, that all Men ſhould Honour the Son, even as they Honour the Father, <hi>John</hi> 5.22, 23. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. <hi>Can outward Blood cleanſe the Conſcience?</hi> Againſt <hi>Iſaac Penington</hi>'s <hi>Queſtions,</hi> p. 25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not without the Spirit; for the Spirit, the Water, and the Blood, agree in One.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. Theſe nameleſs Adverſaries again charge us with a two-fold Falſhood, namely, <hi>That tho the</hi> Quakers <hi>do deny the outward Blood of Chriſt to have any Vertue or Efficacy towards cleanſing of the Conſcience, yet they attribute this to their own Blood, which they deny to the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> p. 5.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are <hi>both</hi> moſt odious <hi>Perverſions,</hi> which we ſolemnly teſtifie againſt. They alſo perverſly add for Proof againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> in this point, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="22">22. <hi>For ſpeaking of their own Sufferings, and the Shedding of their Blood, (which was never done in</hi> England, <hi>unleſs ſome Boy gave them a Bloody Noſe.</hi> [This is a very ſcornful Untruth by the way.] <hi>They ſay thus to thoſe, whom they call their Perſecutors, That you will by no means be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58919:35"/>thence cleanſed</hi> (i. e. <hi>from the Guilt of the</hi> Quakers <hi>Blood) but by the ſame Blood, which you ſo Cruelly Shed.</hi> (Againſt <hi>The Guilty Clergy-Man <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed,</hi> p. 17. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1657.)</p>
                  <p>Now pray obſerve; the Parentheſis (i. e. <hi>from the Guilt of the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>Blood</hi>) is perverſly added, and their <hi>Citation</hi> as lamely taken, the Antecedent matter on which the Subſequent depends, and to which 'tis relative being left out, and both the Intent and Senſe of the Author wholly perverted, by theſe Men's applying it all to the <hi>Quakers</hi> own Sufferings and Blood, and therefore take <hi>T. S</hi>'s whole <hi>Paragraph</hi> in the place quoted, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Be not prevailed with to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe Barrabas,</hi> and give over <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be crucified, to gratifie the Murderous Appetites, either of your <hi>Prieſts</hi> or the <hi>Multitude;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that altho' you may (with <hi>Pilate) waſh your hands,</hi> and (to thoſe Eyes that are dazled with Fury and Prejudice againſt Innocent <hi>Jeſus</hi>) appear clear from <hi>his Blood;</hi> yet before the pure <hi>Eyes</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> will the condemning Stain thereof be found upon you ſo freſh, that you will by no means be thence cleanſed, but by the <hi>ſame</hi> Blood, which you ſo cruelly ſhed.</q> (<hi>The Guilty covered Clergy-Man,</hi> p. 17.)</p>
                  <p>I cannot believe this was <hi>Literally</hi> meant by the <hi>Author,</hi> being a Man known to be of a better Underſtanding and Experience, than repreſented by thoſe <hi>Adverſaries.</hi> I'm ſure it is not the <hi>Quakers Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> to attribute <hi>Cleanſing the Conſcience</hi> to their own <hi>Blood</hi> or <hi>Sufferings.</hi> The <hi>Guilt</hi> of <hi>Innocent Blood,</hi> ſhed by the hands of cruel <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> may be charged upon <hi>Perſecutors</hi> in after-Ages; as Chriſt told the <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> Matth. 23.34, 35. <hi>Behold, I ſend unto Prophets, and Wiſe Men, and Scribes, and ſome of them ye ſhall Kill and Crucifie, and ſome of them ſhall ye Scourge in your Synagogues, and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them from City to City. That upon you may come all the Righteous Blood, ſhed upon the Earth, from the Blood of Righteous</hi> Abel, <hi>unto the Blood of</hi> Zacharias, <hi>Son of</hi> Barachias, <hi>whom <hi>ye</hi> ſtew between the Temple and the Altar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And was not this above <hi>Eight Hundred Years</hi> before Chriſt was Born, that <hi>Zacharias</hi> was thus <hi>Slain?</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.21. ſurely, the Wickedneſs of the Wicked ſhall be upon him. And are not many <hi>Guilty</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt, who never actually ſhed it? And as the <hi>Iniquities</hi> of all met upon him, are not they all <hi>Guilty</hi> of his <hi>Blood,</hi> and chargeable with it, who remain <hi>Impenitent Perſecutors</hi> of him in his Members, and who <hi>Crucifie to themſelves the Lord of Life a-freſh?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:58919:35"/>
                  <p n="23">23. <hi>If there be any other Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. anſwered fully before, and the Miſtake diſcover'd.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. Chriſt's Body, or what he had from the Virgin, <hi>Strictly</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as ſuch, was not the Seed [<hi>i. e.</hi> the Seed of the Woman pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.] Againſt <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> p. 97.</p>
                  <p>Here they add the <hi>Parentheſis</hi> in <hi>Crotchets,</hi> but Anſwer not the Scope or Intent of the Matter or Arguments urged, both before and after what they have quoted. <hi>W. P.</hi> denies not, but confeſſeth, Chriſt to have <hi rend="margQuotes">been Born of the Virgin, and that he was the promiſed Seed, the true Chriſt (who bruiſeth the Serpent's Head) the Son of the living God, and alſo God over all, both before and after he took Fleſh of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin: But that, as the Serpent is a Spirit, the Seed Chriſt muſt be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and Spiritually known by his Light, Life and Power, to bruiſe under, and caſt out, the Serpent.</hi> See how at large <hi>W. P.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains it, and confeſſeth to the true Chriſt, the promiſed Seed, both as in the Fleſh and in the Spirit: <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> 1ſt part, Chap. 19.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. <hi>Let us but Soberly conſider what Chriſt is, and we ſhall the better know whether Moral Men (tho' Heathen) are to be reckoned Chriſtians. What is Chriſt but Meekneſs, Juſtice, Mercy?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Can any then deny a Meek Man to be a Chriſtian?</hi> This againſt <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Addreſs to Proteſtants,</hi> Second Edition, <hi>Anno</hi> 1692. p. 119.</p>
                  <p>Here they have added <hi>(tho Heathen)</hi> and after <hi>Mercy,</hi> they leave out <hi>[Patience, Charity and Virtue in Perfection] W. P.</hi> did not deſign there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to leſſen the <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Dignity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (who is the Author of theſe Virtues) no more than the Apoſtle did in ſaying, <hi>He</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>is <hi>made</hi> of God unto us, Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> (ſpoken in the Abſtract.) And the Prophet ſaying, <hi>God is my Light and my Salvation;</hi> tho' God and Chriſt alſo be the Author of Redemption and Salvation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III. <hi>Concerning the Holy Scriptures.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="26">26. <hi>Whether the firſt Pen-men of the Scriptures was</hi> Moſes <hi>or</hi> Hermes? <hi>Or whether both theſe are not one?</hi> &amp;c. This (with more <hi>Queſtions</hi>) quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt <hi>John Whitehead, Quakers Refuge,</hi> p. 17.</p>
                  <p>Thus theſe adverſaries (as <hi>F. Bugg,</hi> and the Author of <hi>the Snake</hi> uſe to do) to Defame us, leave out theſe following words, (relative to each thing queſtioned) <hi>viz.</hi> — <q rend="margQuotes">
                        <hi>is not the ſubject of my Argument at this time.</hi>
                     </q> Hence 'tis plain, the Perſon who recited the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (which was not <hi>John Whitehead,</hi> but <hi>R. R.</hi>) waveth theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and cited them not as the Subject of his own Argument about
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58919:36"/>the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> but of ſome others; he would not be concern'd to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute thoſe <hi>Queſtions</hi> or <hi>Doubts.</hi> For he further confeſſeth, in the ſaid <hi>Quakers Refuge,</hi> quoted, <q rend="margQuotes">That ſuch <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Prophecies</hi> as have been Written and Propheſied by the Holy Men of God, as they were moved by his Spirit, Treating of the Myſtery of God in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and Salvation of Mankind, by Jeſus Chriſt, and the Duty of Man in his Obedience to, and Worſhip of the ſame God, as his reaſonable Service; for the Gift of ſo great Salvation, are the great Concerns now under our moſt ſerious Conſideration.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>From hence it's clear, the Author was no Contemner of Holy Scripture, nor intended any Contempt thereof; as is more fully cleared in my ſaid <hi>Antidote, againſt the Venom of the Snake in the Graſs,</hi> p. 83, 84, 85.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. <hi>The Scriptures are not the Word of God [Yet he ſays of his own Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,] To you all this is the Word of the Lord.</hi> Againſt <hi>G. F. Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 246. Ibid. p. 225.</p>
                  <p>Note <hi>firſt,</hi> by the <hi>Word of God</hi> he means <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Eſſential Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Word</hi> in the firſt place. <hi>Secondly, To you all this is the Word of the Lord;</hi> in that place he ſpeaks of the <hi>Light</hi> within, and the <hi>Spirit</hi> that was in them, that gave forth the <hi>Scriptures, Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 225. yet confeſſeth the Scriptures of <hi>Truth</hi> are <hi>God's Words,</hi> which Chriſt the <hi>Word</hi> fulfills, p. 246.</p>
                  <p>And if elſewhere, concerning what he gave forth from the <hi>Living Word,</hi> that it was the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> he intends only, as Words immediately proceeding from the Motion of the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and not of his own Writings <hi>Abſtractly,</hi> as he is miſunderſtood, and miſrepreſented.</p>
                  <p>What we are Charged with (in their next Paſſages, concerning the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and concerning <hi>Beaſtly Wares, the Letter,</hi> &amp;c. p. 6, 7.— 'tis fully Anſwer'd and Diſtinguiſh'd in the <hi>firſt Part;</hi> And our Adverſaries injuriouſly dealing with us, and miſrepreſenting us, fully detected.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV. 29. <hi>Concerning the Sacraments</hi> (ſo call'd) <hi>Circumciſion, Water-Baptiſm, Paſchal-Lamb, Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine, Sprinkling Infants,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>Theſe are ſpoken to before: only this I propoſe, That what any of our Friends have written heretofore againſt <hi>Sprinkling Infants,</hi> as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58919:36"/>Unſcriptural, if they'll pleaſe to bring us plain Scripture-Proof for that Practice (as they uſe it) then we are bound to revoke what's written againſt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>V. <hi>Concerning the Reſurrection of the Body.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="30">30. They quote ſome <hi>Arguments</hi> out of <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Reaſon againſt Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and his <hi>Invalidity of</hi> J. Faldo<hi>'s Vindication, and</hi> Tho. Ellwood<hi>'s Anſwer to</hi> G. Keith<hi>'s Firſt Narrative</hi> (<hi>and</hi> Rich. Hubberthorn<hi>'s Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> the Doctrine of the Glorified Saints in Heaven, not being Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect) both diſtinguiſhing between the <hi>Natural Body,</hi> and the <hi>Spiritual Body,</hi> according to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. whoſe Arguments not being Anſwer'd by theſe Oppoſers, I ſhall need ſay the leſs to them; only would have them ſo Charitable, as that if they believe that the <hi>Reſurrection-Bodies</hi> of the Saints, ſhall be the ſame <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Carnal Bodies,</hi> that now they are upon Earth, that they would not Condemn us as <hi>Blaſphemers,</hi> for Believing our <hi>Reſurrection-Bodies</hi> ſhall be <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Glorious,</hi> far excelling theſe <hi>Natural, Carnal,</hi> and <hi>Earthly Bodies.</hi> For elſe how ſhould the Saints Bodies be like unto Chriſt's Glorious Body?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI. 31. <hi>That the Quakers make themſelves Equal to God, and a Part of God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>This repeated <hi>Falſhood</hi> is detected, and anſwered in the <hi>Firſt Part;</hi> and ſo are their Inſtances of the <hi>Soul;</hi> againſt <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 273. and p. 100. and p. 91. and p. 229. where the Word <hi>Soul</hi> is diſtinguiſh'd in a two-fold Senſe: <hi>Firſt,</hi> in Relation to <hi>God,</hi> his Divine Spirit, or <hi>Breath</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi> Secondly, to <hi>Man,</hi> as thereby made a <hi>Living Soul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="32">32. <hi>We are of his Fleſh and Bones, and have his Subſtance.</hi> (Againſt <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. 248.)</p>
                  <p>This is <hi>falſly</hi> Quoted. 'Tis not there ſaid in the Affirmative, <hi>That we are ſo;</hi> but an Inverſion upon the Adverſary, from <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.30. &amp; <hi>John</hi> 6.56.</p>
                  <p n="33">33. <hi>Chriſt is not diſtinct from his Saints.</hi> (Againſt <hi>Great Myſtery,</hi> p. 207.)</p>
                  <p>He means, <hi>not divided or ſeparate from his Saints,</hi> as by his following Words, <hi>Chriſt is in his Saints,</hi> (<hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> p. ibid.)</p>
                  <p n="34">34. <hi>Chriſt is the Elect.</hi> Gr. Myſt. p. 88.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58919:37"/>
                  <p>So ſaith the <hi>Prophet</hi> of Him, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.1. <hi>G. F.</hi> alſo calls <hi>Chriſt's Sheep,</hi> the <hi>Elect.</hi> Gr. Myſt. p. 88, 89.</p>
                  <p n="35">35. <hi>The Light within is Chriſt.</hi> Gr. Myſt. p. 310.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>True,</hi> but not <hi>truly Quoted:</hi> but thus, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">The Light which every Man that cometh into the World, is Lightned withal, is Chriſt, <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> ibid.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Chriſt the <hi>Light</hi> ſaith, <hi>I in them, and Thou in Me,</hi> John 17.23, 26.</p>
                  <p n="36">36. <hi>The Soul is not a Creature, but Infinite in it ſelf, without beginning.</hi> Gr. Myſt. p. 29, 90.</p>
                  <p>This is miſ-cited, and wrong mixt; they turn and confound <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions</hi> into <hi>Affirmatives.</hi> That which is <hi>Infinite in it ſelf,</hi> relates to <hi>that</hi> which came out from the Creator, namely, that Divine Life, or Soul, which gave Life and Being to Man's Soul. 'Tis not ſaid, <hi>Man's Soul</hi> or <hi>Spirit,</hi> is not a Creature, as diſtinguiſhed more fully in the <hi>Firſt Part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="37">37. <hi>They that have the Spirit of God, are equal with God.</hi> Er. Howgill<hi>'s</hi> Works, p. 232.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are none of <hi>F. Howgill</hi>'s Words, but his <hi>Adverſary</hi>'s: what a Falacious Courſe do theſe our Adverſaries take to prove us Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal? <hi>F. H</hi>'s Words are: <q rend="margQuotes">He that hath the Spirit of God, is in <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>Equal.</hi>
                     </q> The Matter is Anſwered in the <hi>Firſt Part;</hi> and ſo is that Quoted out of <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand,</hi> p. 8.</p>
                  <p n="38">38. <hi>The Righteouſneſs which God effects in us, is not Finite, but Infinite.</hi> G. W. <hi>Voice of Wiſdom,</hi> p. 36.</p>
                  <p>This was Inferr'd from the <hi>Prieſts</hi> owning, <hi>That the Righteouſneſs whereof Chriſt is the Subject, and that whereof he is the Efficient, are of one Species, or Kind:</hi> And from <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Chriſt being formed in us:</hi> And 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. The <hi>Saints</hi> being made Partakers of the Divine Nature: And <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.14. I concluded, <q rend="margQuotes">Then God's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs in us is not Finite, but Infinite.</q> 
                     <hi>Voice of Wiſd.</hi> p. 36, 37. Now, I ſuppoſe, they place the <hi>Miſtake,</hi> or <hi>Error ſuppoſed,</hi> between the Words [<hi>Effects</hi> and <hi>Infinite</hi>] as if nothing could be ſaid to be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite,</hi> that had a beginning, or that is <hi>effected;</hi> which is to ſuppoſe, whatſoever is <hi>Infinite,</hi> has no Beginning, as well as no <hi>End;</hi> but <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> is not always taken in that <hi>Senſe;</hi> for 'tis ſometimes apply'd to things that had a <hi>Beginning,</hi> as in <hi>Nah.</hi> 2.9. &amp; chap. 3.9. But my meaning ſimply of the Word <hi>[Infinite]</hi> was, That God's <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> (which he effects in us) is Everlaſting, and without End, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119, 142. And <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>of God <hi>made</hi> unto us Wiſdom, and Righteouſneſs, and Sanctification, and Redemption,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.30. I hope
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58919:37"/>none will deny him to be <hi>Infinite,</hi> or his Work of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and the Effect thereof to be Quietneſs and Aſſurance <hi>for ever, Iſa.</hi> 32.17.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII. <hi>Of Chriſt's Coming to Judge the Quick and the Dead,</hi> P. 9.</head>
                  <p n="39">39. <hi>But Three Comings of Chriſt, not only that in the Fleſh at</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>and that in the Spirit, but alſo another coming in the Fleſh, yet to be expected, we do not yet read of.</hi> [Againſt <hi>G. W</hi>'s Light and Life, page 41.]</p>
                  <p>But is this to deny or oppoſe Chriſt's coming to Judge the Quick and the Dead? 'Twas never ſo intended. And Queſtioning ſome Men's <hi>Carnal</hi> Expectations of a <hi>Fleſhly</hi> coming of Chriſt, to be ſeen with their <hi>Carnal Eyes;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="margQuotes">was this to deny his coming in the Glory of his Father, with his Angels, to Reward every Man according to his works? Mat.</hi> 16.27. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.26. No ſure, for that's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and undeniable. Likewiſe, to queſtion ſome Men's Notion of a <hi>Fleſhly</hi> coming of Chriſt, <hi>Perſonally</hi> to Reign a <hi>Thouſand Years on Earth,</hi> is this to oppoſe his Kingdom, or that Prophecy of his Reign a Thouſand Years, mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.2, 4, 5, 6, 7? No ſure: Let our Adverſaries produce plain Scripture-Proof, in <hi>Terminis,</hi> for Chriſt's Coming and Reign, in that manner, and the Queſtion is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd.</p>
                  <p>To their other Citation out of <hi>Nature of Chriſtianity,</hi> p. 29, 30. <hi>Thou may'ſt look until thy Eyes drop out, before thou wilt ſee ſuch an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of him</hi> (meaning with his carnal Eyes.) This is true in Fact, for thoſe very Eyes decay and periſh; and Chriſt's laſt coming in Power and great Glory (in his glorious Body) accompanied with <hi>All</hi> his mighty Angels (at the <hi>Reſurrection</hi>) muſt be ſeen with ſtronger, clearer, and more celeſtial Eyes than periſhing Eyes of Fleſh.</p>
                  <p>And though we have believed Chriſt's Second Appearance or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>without Sin unto Salvation,</hi> mentioned <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. (that is, to ſave Men from their Sins) to be a Spiritual Appearance and Work; yet this is not to deny Chriſt to be the <hi>Judge both of the Quick and the Dead,</hi> or his coming to judge the Quick and the Dead, in the great and laſt Day.</p>
                  <p n="40">40. <hi>And as for that,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.15. <hi>concerning the Coming of the Lord from Heaven; which theſe Men would blindly put a-far off.</hi> Q. againſt <hi>Brief Diſcovery,</hi> p. 9. in Anſwer to <hi>John Horn,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Anno</hi> 1659. Here they
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58919:38"/>leave out [As to a coming of Chriſt with <hi>Fleſh and Bones</hi>] (meaning <hi>without any Blood in it,</hi> for ſuch a Body they then held) and <hi>[The Apoſtle ſaith, We which are alive, and remain unto the coming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent them which are aſleep]</hi> Theſe are left out alſo in their Citation.</p>
                  <p>In the Ancient Bible of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the words are, <hi>We which live and are remaining <hi>in</hi> the coming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent them which ſleep.</hi> From my inferring the Saints knowledge of Chriſt's Spiritual Coming, who is Lord <hi>from</hi> Heaven, I would have none ſuppoſe, that we at all doubt of the <hi>Coming</hi> of the <hi>Son of Man (the Lord Jeſus)</hi> and <hi>ſhewing</hi> himſelf from Heaven at the great Day, and all his Holy Angels with him; as teſtified in Holy Scripture, by himſelf and Servants.</p>
                  <p>On <hi>Phil.</hi> 20.21. after the words <hi>[Their Converſations was in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven]</hi> They add <hi>[To wit, a Heaven within them]</hi> Thus the Quotation is wronged in this, and divers other words.</p>
                  <p n="41">41. <hi>There is none have a Glory, and a Heaven, but within them</hi> (Gr. Myſt. p. 214.</p>
                  <p>Here they leave out what follows, <hi>viz. [Which was before Man had a Being]</hi> The words ſhould be Tranſpoſed, <hi>viz. There's none have a Glory and a Heaven within them, but which was before Man had a Being.</hi> For what true and heavenly Glory or Joy any have <hi>within them,</hi> 'twas before Man had a Being; this appears to be the intent of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, the word <hi>But</hi> being miſplaced; and yet what the Saints have and injoy in this Life, is much ſhort in degree of <hi>that</hi> more full At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, and exceeding Weight of Glory, in that which is to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII. <hi>Concerning Government,</hi> P. 10.</head>
                  <p n="42">42. [<hi>The</hi> Quakers <hi>hold none Lawful, but in their own Hands; for that they have only a Right to Rule over the whole Earth, and that it is Lawful for them to Fight, and ſubdue the World under them; and that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>Theſe we utterly deny, and teſtifie againſt, as <hi>groſs Calumnies</hi> caſt upon us, contrary to our Peaceable, Chriſtian Principle and Practice, both as to <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Fighting.</hi> We ſeek no Worldly Kingdom or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion to our ſelves, but the Promotion of <hi>Chriſt's Peaceable Kingdom</hi> in Men, wherein we deſire ever to approve our Selves his Innocent Subjects, whoſe <hi>Weapons</hi> are not <hi>Carnal</hi> but <hi>Spiritual,</hi> being Crucified with him to the Ground and Cauſe or <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Fighting.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58919:38"/>in his Power teſtifie againſt this <hi>Malicious Perſecuting Spirit,</hi> which hath thus fouly miſrepreſented us, as a People againſt all <hi>Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and <hi>as holding it lawful for us to Fight and Subdue the World under us and that we expect it too.</hi> O for <hi>Shame,</hi> for <hi>Shame,</hi> you Malicious Perſecutors! <hi>Ceaſe, Ceaſe,</hi> ſuch your horrid Falſhoods, and Malicious Attempts, to incenſe the <hi>Government</hi> thereby.</p>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Adverſaries</hi> quote a piece of a <hi>Declaration</hi> of the <hi>Quakers</hi> (as they call it) beginning thus, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">We have choſen the Son of God to be our King, and he hath choſen us to be his People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> p. 10.</p>
                  <p>Out of which <hi>Declaration</hi> they have here left out ſeveral material Paſſages to clear our <hi>Innocency</hi> from <hi>Fighting,</hi> as charged upon us, as, <q rend="margQuotes">His Kingdom (i. e. <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Kingdom</hi>) is not of this World, neither is his Warfare with Carnal Weapons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither hath he choſen us for that end, neither can we yet believe that he will make uſe of us in that way, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </q> but as for Chriſt's Right to <hi>Rule</hi> the <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> (he being the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, and the <hi>King of Kings, and Lord of Lords</hi>) the Holy Scriptures are very clear and full: And we could heartily wiſh, the <hi>Nations,</hi> and the <hi>Princes</hi> of the Earth, more Subject to Chriſt's Government than generally they are; then there would be more univerſal Love, Charity, Tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Amable Correſpondence in the Nations and Kingdoms of this World, than as yet there is.</p>
                  <p>As to <hi>S. Fiſher</hi>'s <hi>Meſſage</hi> (in 1656.) again recited in part; For the <hi>Reign of Chriſt and his Saints,</hi> 'tis cleared in the <hi>Firſt Part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to what they recite out of <hi>E. B</hi>'s Epiſtle <hi>To the Camp of the Lord in</hi> England (p. 67.) containing many <hi>Warlike Expreſſions,</hi> he was never underſtood to mean <hi>Litterally</hi> amongſt us, or by any of us, that ever I could perceive; but of a <hi>Spiritual Warfare</hi> with <hi>Spiritual Weapons;</hi> as when the Lord ſaid, <hi>I have hewen them by my Prophets, and ſlain them by the words of my Mouth,</hi> Hoſea 6.5. and Pſal. 149.6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Let the High Praiſes of God be in their Mouth, a Two-edged Sword in their hand; to execute Vengeance upon the Heathen, and Puniſhments upon the People: To bind their Kings with Chains, and their Nobles with Fetters of Iron. To Execute upon them the Judgment written; this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour have all his Saints.</hi> —Though theſe <hi>Doctors</hi> are pleaſed to take theſe <hi>Litterally</hi> againſt us in <hi>S. Fiſher</hi>'s <hi>Meſſage:</hi> Thus they ſhew their <hi>Learning,</hi> and how they are Principled for <hi>Fighting</hi> againſt <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> if they eſteem themſelves Saints, as we may preſume they do, which ſtill ſhews, how Ignorant they are of the <hi>Voices</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Prophets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:58919:39"/>
                  <p>To their <hi>Marginal Note</hi> upon <hi>E. B</hi>'s ſaid Epiſtle <hi>To the Camp of the Lord,</hi> viz. N. B. <hi>It was a Secret of their Government, not fit to be divulged.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What a manifeſt untruth is that, when they ſee it <hi>divulged</hi> in his Works (quoted by them) p. 64. to 67.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>IX. <hi>Concerning Kings, and Kingly Government.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>What is recited under this Head, is anſwered in the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> except this Prophetical Paſſage, <hi>viz. The Lord will cleanſe the Land of you Rulers, Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>This was propheſied againſt the <hi>Perſecutors</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> of <hi>God's People,</hi> in 1655. which in a great Meaſure is come to paſs, and may yet further be fulfilled, if any ſhould riſe up to renew the like work of <hi>Perſecution</hi> againſt the <hi>Lord</hi>'s <hi>Heritage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X. <hi>Concerning Parliaments.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Many are ſo doting on the Name of a Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. againſt <hi>Fra. Howgill</hi>'s <hi>Works,</hi> p. 5. with more words abruptly cited, ſo that the ſenſe and intent of the Author cannot be underſtood; and I find them not in the place cited.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>XI. <hi>Of the Lords.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What a dirty naſty thing it would have been, to have heard talk of a Houſe of Lords amongſt them. (To the Council of Officers,</hi> p. 7.) that was among <hi>them</hi> in <hi>O. Cromwell</hi>'s days (which was about 1656.) 'Twas ſpoken <hi>ad Hominem,</hi> as their Principle, who were againſt <hi>O. C</hi>'s <hi>making Lords, or having a Houſe of Lords among them, there was once more Sincerity and Humility among them, than ſo to exalt themſelves contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to what they had profeſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>XII. <hi>Of the Commons,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The <hi>Recitations</hi> under this Head, are anſwered in the <hi>Firſt Part;</hi> in which I would not be underſtood in any wiſe to oppoſe the Peoples <hi>Legal</hi> and <hi>Juſt Rights</hi> to <hi>Elections,</hi> or chuſing <hi>Members</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> according to the Juſt <hi>Intent</hi> of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> choſen to make <hi>Laws</hi> for the <hi>Safety</hi> and good of the <hi>People;</hi> knowing, that <hi>Salus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli Suprema Lex eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:58919:39"/>
                  <head>XIII. <hi>Of the</hi> Quakers <hi>rejecting all Humane Laws and Authority, but their own.</hi>—</head>
                  <p>This is a notorious <hi>Calumny,</hi> and the <hi>Contrary</hi> publickly teſtified by us (as a People) for our owning and obeying <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> as <hi>God's Ordinance,</hi> and by our peaceable <hi>Converſation</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> ever ſince we were a People. And I cannot ſee what <hi>Offence</hi> can be in theſe words, <hi>It is God's proper Right to give Laws unto Man,</hi> ſeeing 'tis by his Divine <hi>Wiſdom, that Kings Reign, and Princes Decree Juſtice,</hi> Prov. 8.15. The other Paſſages recited under this 13th Head are alſo anſwered in the <hi>Firſt Part.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>XIV. <hi>Of the</hi> Quakers <hi>taking upon them Authority to abrogate the Laws of the Land, and Aſſociating for the ſame with their Hands, Lives and Eſtates.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>What they brokenly recite under this Head, in ſeveral Paſſages is chiefly againſt the payment of <hi>Tithes</hi> under the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> and againſt ſuch <hi>Preachers,</hi> as Preach for <hi>Tithes</hi> and <hi>Mony,</hi> to be teſtified againſt in the Lord's Power and Spirit; which has been according to our <hi>Chriſtian Teſtimony,</hi> (as we really believe and are perſuaded in Conſcience) ever ſince we were a People. Which is not to <hi>take upon our ſelves Authority to abrogate the Laws of the Land;</hi> as is wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully charged upon us under this Head: For we neither <hi>take upon us</hi> ſuch <hi>Authority,</hi> nor do we pretend to any ſuch <hi>Power,</hi> nor do we <hi>Aſſociate</hi> our ſelves for that end; 'tis an unjuſt Calumny caſt upon us. But only as the Lord has perſuaded us in our own Conſciences by his <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> we are obliged to be <hi>Faithful</hi> in our <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> though many have been, and are <hi>Sufferers</hi> for the ſame. We do not reſiſt Authority, but rather <hi>poſſitively Submit,</hi> wherein we cannot <hi>actually obey</hi> with Safety and Peace of Conſcience. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we are perſuaded our Adverſaries cannot make it appear by plain Scripture, that Chriſt's Miniſters (who are <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>New Covenant</hi>) are allowed by him to Preach for <hi>Tithes, Hire</hi> or <hi>forced Maintenance,</hi> or that he requires their <hi>Hearers</hi> to pay <hi>Tithes,</hi> for this is contrary to his own precept, <hi>freely ye have received, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give:</hi> And to his <hi>Changing the Prieſthood of</hi> Levi that took <hi>Tithes,</hi> and diſanulling the <hi>Law,</hi> that enjoyned the payment of them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58919:40"/>and <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. Divers of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> and eminent <hi>Reformers</hi> (as in the <hi>firſt Part</hi> noted) bore the like Teſtimony with us, againſt the Payment and Impoſing of <hi>Tithes</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> But this grates hard againſt ſuch avaricious <hi>Prieſts,</hi> whoſe <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> is therein concerned. And ſeeing <hi>T. Ellwood</hi> is quoted againſt the Payment of <hi>Tithes</hi> under the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> I refer the <hi>Reader</hi> to his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> in that caſe, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The Foundation of Tithes ſhaken.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>XV. <hi>Of the High and Divine Authority which the</hi> Quakers <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate to themſelves; and that they do intend (when able) to root up, and deſtroy all other Governments.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>This is ſtill as <hi>bitter,</hi> as <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>calumnious</hi> as the other, to render us Obnoxious, and to incenſe to <hi>Perſecution</hi> againſt us. We arrogate no ſuch Authority to our ſelves; but deſire Humbly to Meet in the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of Chriſt Jeſus, whoſe Preſence is in our Aſſemblies, in the midſt of us, as we humbly Meet in his Name. And our giving Chriſtian Counſel, Admonition, Inſtruction and Recommendation (of things juſt and honeſt) in his Name unto our <hi>Friends,</hi> under the ſame Chriſtian Profeſſion with us; this is no Deſign to <hi>root up, or deſtroy</hi> any outward Civil <hi>Government</hi> (in Temporal Affairs, or for a Terror to Evil-does) but tending to the Eaſe and Praiſe thereof, by due and timely Admonition, to prevent Diſorders and Scandal, as that termed <hi>Preventing Juſtice,</hi> doth prevent Enormities, Miſchiefs, and the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, conſequently, muſt needs be an eaſe to the Civil Government. And as for our Admoniſhing againſt unruly, diſorderly Spirits, who either luſt to be Contentious, or to cauſe <hi>Diviſions,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> or reprehending ſuch who ſlight, contemn, and ſcorn wholſome <hi>Advice</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Counſel:</hi> This our Chriſtian Care and Practice for good <hi>Order, Peace</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the Churches of Chriſt among us, is both neceſſary and warrantable, and according to the Practice and Example of the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians,</hi> and Churches of Chriſt. So that (as hath been teſtified already in the <hi>firſt Part</hi> of this <hi>Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi>) all our <hi>Meetings,</hi> both <hi>Yearly, Monthly, Quarterly,</hi> &amp;c. are for Innocent, Good and Chriſtian Ends, and Religious Exerciſe and Service. And theſe <hi>Adverſaries</hi> ſaying, <hi>Theſe Meetings are not for Worſhip, but only for their Government,</hi> p. 17. Is a known <hi>Falſhood,</hi> we having in them often-times both earneſt <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Supplication</hi> to God, and Edifying one another in true Faith and Love, and provoking one another to <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>good Works.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:58919:40"/>
                  <p>To their Charging our ſaid <hi>Meetings, That we keep them with our Doors ſhut or guarded, expreſly againſt the Act of Toleration, that extends only</hi> (they ſay) <hi>to Meetings for Religious Worſhip, and excludes all from any Benefit by that Act, who keep their Doors ſhut at their Meetings,</hi> p. 17. Thus far againſt the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>See how hard theſe <hi>Perſecutors</hi> are put to it, and how ſtrenuouſly they endeavour to exclude us from any <hi>Benefit</hi> of the <hi>Act of Toleration,</hi> conſequently to raiſe Perſecution againſt us. But they are very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and partial, as well as <hi>miſtaken</hi> in their <hi>Conſtruction</hi> of it. For I hope in the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of <hi>Religion, Meetings</hi> for promoting the Practice of pure <hi>Religion</hi> may be included and allowed, together with thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely for <hi>Religious Worſhip.</hi> And it is a falſe Conſtruction to ſay, The ſaid <hi>Act excludes all from the Benefit thereof, who keep their Doors ſhut at their Meetings.</hi> This is a <hi>wrong Conſtruction</hi> upon the <hi>Statute;</hi> the words whereof being, <hi>With the Doors lock'd, barr'd or bolted;</hi> 'tis not with the <hi>Doors ſhut,</hi> for there may be need for that ſometime to keep out the <hi>cold Wind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It ſeems, the <hi>Malice</hi> of theſe <hi>Perſecutors</hi> is ſo deadly againſt us, that they do not only harp upon their repeated Rendering the <hi>Quakers,</hi> as <hi>ſetting up a Government within the Government,</hi> to make them Seditious, but alſo Treaſonable; for which end they cite the following Paſſage, out of <hi>Weſt anſwering the North,</hi> p. 80. viz.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Any Party of Men under a Government to make Laws, not being Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Authoriz'd ſo to do, for the binding of others, and thereunto to require Obedience, is the ſetting up of themſelves above the Law, and treading it under their Feet, and rendering of them, whom they do ſo bind, their Slaves and Vaſſals; and ſo is Treaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis probable, theſe <hi>Perſecutors</hi> think, they have given us a <hi>deadly Blow</hi> with this Paſſage, and therefore have put <hi>Treaſon</hi> in <hi>great Letters.</hi> But they greatly miſapply and pervert the ſame. For being printed about the Year 1656, it was directly intended as a Stroke upon the <hi>Perſecuting Juſtices</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in thoſe times in the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who, contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Chap. 29. and the Fundamental <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of this Nation, did, in their own Arbitrary Wills, iſſue out <hi>Orders</hi> of <hi>Seſſions,</hi> or <hi>Warrants,</hi> to apprehend and <hi>Impriſon</hi> our <hi>Friends,</hi> and ſo to confine them, and bar them from travelling on the <hi>High-ways;</hi> and ſome have been taken up, and <hi>whip'd</hi> as <hi>Vagrants,</hi> in thoſe times, by ſuch as were intruſted with the Execution of the <hi>Law,</hi> and due Adminiſtration of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> 'Twas againſt ſuch, and thoſe their Arbitrary and Unwarrantable Proceedings, that the ſaid Paſſage (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly recited againſt us) was directly intended and levelled. And
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58919:41"/>therefore what theſe Men have recited out of <hi>News out of the</hi> North, (p. 18.) printed 1654. containing matter of <hi>Prophecy</hi> againſt thoſe and ſuch corrupt Perſecuting <hi>Rulers, Judges, Juſtices, Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c. in thoſe days charged with ſuch <hi>Perſecution</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> importing their <hi>Downfall;</hi> I ſee no cauſe for theſe <hi>Propheſies</hi> now to be alledged againſt us, ſeeing they are in a great meaſure fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>After the words — <hi>And thou Beaſt</hi> — theſe Men add <hi>[the Civil Government.]</hi> See what Picking and Botching work they make to throw dirt upon us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>XVI. <hi>Their Treatment of Kings,</hi> (p. 19.)</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You, and your Kings, and Lordly Power (by which you thought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe Lordſhip over my Heritage) ſhall be Enſlaved by the Devil,</hi> &amp;c. againſt <hi>E. B</hi>'s <hi>Trumpet,</hi> printed <hi>Anno</hi> 1655.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> This is not of all Kings, but all Perſecutors of the Saints of God, who would Lord it over <hi>His</hi> Heritage are Enemies to Chriſt, and under the Dragon's Power, conſequently ſuch are enſlaved by the Devil alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; how <hi>Great and High</hi> ſoever they are in the Earth, and will go down with the Uncircumciſed into the Pit, if they repent not, ſee <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32 chap. And dare any of theſe Prieſts affirm the contrary?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>XVII. <hi>Their Treatment of the Clergy,</hi> &amp;c. p. 19.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Idle Gormandizing Prieſts of</hi> England <hi>run away with One Hundred and Fifty Thouſand Pounds a Year, under pretence of God's Miniſters,</hi> &amp;c. (againſt <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Guide miſtaken,</hi> p. 18. <hi>Anno</hi> 1668.)</p>
                  <p>I confeſs many things were Zealouſly and Sharply writ againſt the <hi>Covetous, Mercenary, and Perſecuting Prieſts,</hi> pretended <hi>Watchmen</hi> and <hi>Shepherds</hi> in this and other Nations, but (in Language) according as the Holy <hi>Prophets</hi> did againſt the <hi>Shepherds</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and their <hi>Covetous Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11. <hi>His Watch-men are blind, they are all ignorant, they are all</hi> dumb Dogs, <hi>they cannot bark, ſleeping, lying down, loving to ſlumber: Yea, they are</hi> greedy Dogs <hi>which can never have enough, and they are Shepherds that cannot underſtand: They look to their own Way, every one for his gain from his quarter.</hi> And <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>A wonderful and horrible thing is committed in the Land, the Prieſts bear rule by their means.</hi> See alſo Chap. 23.9, 10, 11. And <hi>Micah</hi> 3.11. againſt the <hi>Prieſts that teach for Hire, and the Prophets that divine for Money.</hi> 'Tis very ſtrange, theſe <hi>Doctors</hi> ſhould expoſe the aforeſaid <hi>Complaint</hi> againſt the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> unleſs they had clear'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58919:41"/>thereof; for ſuch <hi>Recitals</hi> againſt their <hi>Corruptions</hi> do excite Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple but the more to inſpect their ways, and to conſider, whether they are warrantable according to Holy Scripture. I refer the <hi>Reader</hi> to <hi>W. P</hi>'s own Anſwer at the end of this Treatiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>XVIII. <hi>Their Treatment of the Diſſenters.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An Ill-bred, Pedantick Crew, the Bane of Religion, and Peſt of the World, the old Incendiaries to Miſchief, and the beſt to be ſpared of Mankind,</hi> &amp;c. (Againſt <hi>W. P. Quakeriſm a new Nick-name,</hi> p. 165.)</p>
                  <p>This is not the <hi>Quakers Treatment of Diſſenters</hi> in general, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, as hereby falſly repreſented. But <hi>W. P</hi>'s occaſional <hi>Treatment</hi> of <q rend="margQuotes">Such a Proud, Railing, Buſie-body, and ſuch a ſort of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who think their <hi>Coat</hi> will bear out their worſt <hi>Expreſſions</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> and practiſe an haughty <hi>Revi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing</hi> for Chriſt, as one of the greateſt Demonſtrations of their <hi>Zeal;</hi>
                     </q> as in his antecedent words. After theſe words of <hi>W. P. [Againſt whom the boiling Vengeance of an Irritated God is ready to be poured out.]</hi> Theſe Men leave out, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">[To the Deſtruction of <hi>ſuch, <hi>if they repent not,</hi>
                        </hi> and turn from their Abominable Deceits.]</q> Certainly neither the fore-going <hi>Citations</hi> (under their 18th Head) nor that which they ſubjoyn againſt the bitter Stock of <hi>Hirelings,</hi> and their Sin-pleaſing Principles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> could ever be intended for the <hi>Quakers Treatment of Diſſenters,</hi> Indefinitely, or without Exception; for we always diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> and <hi>Immoderate,</hi> the <hi>Charitable</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable,</hi> the <hi>Ingenuous</hi> and <hi>Diſingenuous,</hi> even among <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of ſeveral ſorts, and others alſo. When Men are charging <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> and <hi>Sedition</hi> upon a People out of Books, and <hi>Quotations</hi> (as theſe Men do) they ſhould be more fair and juſt therein, than theſe Men have been. They are very <hi>Injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>Offenſive</hi> both in <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Citation;</hi> we only <hi>Defenſive,</hi> and not under a neceſſity of reciting and reprinting their whole <hi>Citations</hi> in every part: Let <hi>their Books</hi> and <hi>ours</hi> be compared, to evince them more fully, and clear our <hi>Innocency</hi> from theſe Adverſaries groſs <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, Perverſions, Miſapplications, Miſrepreſentations,</hi> and <hi>fruitleſs At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58919:42"/>
                  <head>Ingenuous Reader, pleaſe to take <hi>W. P's</hi> own following Anſwer to ſeveral Charges againſt him.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LIBEL,</hi> p. 4. quotes <hi>W. P</hi>'s <hi>Sandy Foundation,</hi> p. 20. thus, <hi>viz. That Finite and Impotent Creature [ſpeaking of Chriſt]</hi> — Which is ſo groſs a Strain of <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Abuſe,</hi> that no Ingenuous Perſon can read it without an Abhorrence of the <hi>Author</hi>'s Temper and Work; and ſhews, how little <hi>Credit</hi> ought to be given him in the reſt of his <hi>Work.</hi> For it is plain, <hi>W. P.</hi> made the <hi>Abſurdity</hi> lie here, That the <hi>Doctrine</hi> he oppos'd makes it Impoſſible for God to forgive, without a rigid Satisfaction; and yet Man, who is a <hi>Finite and Impotent Creature,</hi> is not only capable of it, but commanded to do it: See <hi>Sandy Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> p. 18. Sect. 7.</p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Libel,</hi> p. Ibid. <hi>Chriſt's Co-eſſentiality and Co-eternity with his Father, of his being made Man, Dying for Sins, Riſing and Aſcending into Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. they make <hi>W. P.</hi> to call, <hi>Confuſed Babble, and by Rote-Canting, By-paths of vain Tradition and Invention, Romancing, dark Reſults of Factions, and Corrupted Counſels,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas 'tis plain from his Book at large, as well as from the Words themſelves (which they have cited) he writ not in Contempt of the <hi>Matter,</hi> but in Reproof of the <hi>Man:</hi> For he taxes him with <hi>Babbling, by Rote-Canting,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancing over the weighty Myſteries of Eternal Life;</hi> which words they left out, becauſe being in, they would have diſappointed them of an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Abuſing <hi>W. P.</hi> So that (in ſhort) he reproved the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and Inſenſible <hi>Manner</hi> of the <hi>Prieſt's</hi> Writing, and not the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> treated of; which <hi>W. P.</hi> expreſly calls, the <hi>Weighty Myſteries of Eternal Life.</hi> Which yet plainer appears from p. 28. upon occaſion of ſome <hi>Queries</hi> made by <hi>W. P.</hi> to ſhew the <hi>Indiſtinction</hi> and confuſed Way of the <hi>Prieſt</hi>'s Writing, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Thou muſt not, <hi>Reader,</hi> from my Querying thus, conclude, we do deny (as he hath falſly charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us) thoſe glorious <hi>Three,</hi> which bear Record in Heaven, the <hi>Father, Word,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> neither the <hi>Infinity, Eternity</hi> and <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for that we know, he is the <hi>Mighty God;</hi> nor what the <hi>Father</hi> ſent his Son to do on the behalf of Loſt Man, <hi>declaring to the whole World, we know no other Name by which Attonement, Salvation and plenteous Redemption comes.</hi> But rather to let thee ſee, how unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactorily
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58919:42"/>he has impoſed <hi>Religion</hi> on the World, and how exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing open he lays his Principles to the Objection of every reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Inquirer.</q> For the Prieſt's Book was intituled, <hi>A Guide to the true Religion,</hi> after going forward and backward <hi>four times</hi> in his <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> and therefore deſerved an Anſwer, as <hi>W. P.</hi> did in his Book, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Guide Miſtaken.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Page 19, and 20, The <hi>Libel</hi> quotes <hi>W. P. giving hard words to the Clergy;</hi> — which <hi>W. P.</hi> is far from <hi>diſowning,</hi> allowing him (as in Reaſon) his own <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Intention:</hi> Are they not <hi>Idle, Gormandizing Prieſts,</hi> that Feed the People with that which is not <hi>Bread,</hi> and yet live upon theirs? That teach for <hi>Hire,</hi> and make a <hi>Trade</hi> of the <hi>Miniſtry?</hi> Have not they been the <hi>Bane</hi> of <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> through Ages, that have either been the Ground or Fomentors of the <hi>moſt bloody</hi> and <hi>infamous Revolutions</hi> of the World? Go ask the <hi>Martyrologies</hi> of all Nations, who are the <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot-<hi>Men</hi>
                     </hi> againſt Tender Conſciences and Reformation? <hi>W. P.</hi> does not charge every Perſon of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> ſome being of a more Moderate Temper, and better <hi>Principles;</hi> but he would have theſe of the <hi>Clergy</hi> that take his Words hardly, or any of their <hi>Hearers,</hi> inquire how many of the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſtood to their <hi>Principles</hi> in the Times of K. <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. <hi>Edward</hi> VI. Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> they will find of the whole <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Body,</hi> containing about 12 <hi>Thouſand</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not 5 <hi>Hundred</hi> of all Ranks and <hi>Degrees,</hi> that ſhewed <hi>Conſcience</hi> for their <hi>Religion,</hi> but took their <hi>Turns</hi> at all. And how <hi>few,</hi> through the many <hi>Revolutions,</hi> ſince our late <hi>Civil Wars</hi> began, have been true to their <hi>Principles,</hi> many (yet living) know, to the Scandal of <hi>Religion,</hi> as well as the <hi>Nation?</hi> After this <hi>W. P.</hi> thinks himſelf very little account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for what he has ſaid to a <hi>moſt Temporizing</hi> and <hi>Hypocritical Parſon (J. C.)</hi> of the Men of his Qualifications; for he having excluded the <hi>Quakers, Socinians, &amp;c.</hi> from Salvation, muſt not take it hard of any of us called <hi>Quakers,</hi> if they think ſuch <hi>Turn-Coats,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites</hi> have nothing to do there.</p>
                  <p>Libel, p. 4. <hi>That the outward Perſon which ſuffered, was properly the Son of God, we utterly deny.</hi> Againſt <hi>W. P. Serious Apology,</hi> p. 146.</p>
                  <p>The Anſwer is, That if what <hi>W. P.</hi> hath ſaid, and plainly meant, is not true, then the <hi>Body</hi> that Suffer'd muſt be of the <hi>Divine Nature;</hi> and conſequently that which is of the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> is <hi>Mortal:</hi> But that which is <hi>properly</hi> the <hi>Only-begotten of God,</hi> muſt naturally be <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</hi> So that (<hi>properly</hi> and <hi>ſtrictly</hi> ſpeaking) that which could <hi>die</hi> cannot be the <hi>Only-begotten Entire Son of God;</hi> and yet it was <hi>his Body,</hi> that <hi>died,</hi> and as ſuch it may in a Senſe be ſaid, <hi>He died;</hi> and in no other reſpect does <hi>W. P.</hi> deny <hi>that</hi> which <hi>died,</hi> to be the <hi>Son of God.</hi> See his Book,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58919:43"/>
                     <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> at large, upon this Paſſage, which ſufficiently explains it ſelf, and expoſes their great Diſingenuity that Cite it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Page</hi> 146. Prieſt <hi>Jenner</hi> chargeth us with <hi>Denying the Lord that bought us, becauſe</hi> (as he falſly ſays) <hi>we deny that Perſon (the Son of God) that died at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>to be our Redeemer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="margQuotes">Which moſt horrid Imputation (ſays <hi>W. P.</hi>) has been Anſwer'd more (I believe) than a <hi>thouſand</hi> times, that is, That he that laid down his Life, and ſuffer'd his Body to be Crucified by the <hi>Jews,</hi> without the Gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Only <hi>Son</hi> of the <hi>Moſt High God.</hi>
                     </q> But to Aſſert the Body which Suffered and Died, was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the Entire <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> this brings Him more under the Charge of making him but a <hi>meer Man,</hi> than us, who acknowledge Him to be <hi>One</hi> with the <hi>Father,</hi> and of a <hi>Nature Eternal,</hi> and <hi>Immortal.</hi> For he was <hi>Glorified with the Father, before the World was.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that it may yet farther appear, that what we give for our meaning is ſuch (beſides what is already cited) turn over Leaf to Page 149. and obſerve, what Confeſſion the ſaid <hi>W. P.</hi> then made, as to the Matter Controverted.</p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <p>We do Believe in <hi>One Holy God Almighty,</hi> who is an Eternal Spirit, the Creator of all things.</p>
                     <p>And in <hi>One Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> his Only Son, and <hi>Expreſs Image of his Subſtance,</hi> who took upon Him Fleſh, and was in the World, and in <hi>Life, Doctrine, Miracles, Death, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion,</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation,</hi> perfectly did, and does continue to do the Will of God; to whoſe <hi>Holy Life, Power, Mediation, and Blood, we only aſcribe our Sanctification, Juſtification, Redemption,</hi> and <hi>Perfect Salvation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And we Believe in <hi>One Holy Spirit,</hi> that proceeds and breaths from the Father and the Son, as the Life and Virtue of both the Father and the Son, a Meaſure of which is given to all to Profit with. And <hi>he that has one, has all, for thoſe Three are One;</hi> who is the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> and the <hi>Laſt,</hi> God over all, Bleſſed for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58919:43"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
